<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Naaman vindicated as well from the idolatries of the house of Rimmon in Syria, as from the abuses of the atheists and hypocrites in England / by Richard Pearson, priest of the Church of England.</title>
            <author>Pearson, Richard, 1641?-1710.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 269 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53904</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1013</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28783</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10759093</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10759093</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45693</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53904)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45693)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1407:41)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Naaman vindicated as well from the idolatries of the house of Rimmon in Syria, as from the abuses of the atheists and hypocrites in England / by Richard Pearson, priest of the Church of England.</title>
                  <author>Pearson, Richard, 1641?-1710.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>88 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuel Keble,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Samuel, 2nd, V, 18 --  Commentaries.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:45693:1"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:45693:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Naaman Vindicated, As well from the IDOLATRIES OF THE Houſe of Rimmon IN SYRIA, As from the ABUSES OF THE <hi>ATHEISTS</hi> and <hi>HYPOCRITES</hi> IN ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Richard Pearſon, <hi>Prieſt of the Church of</hi> England.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>2 <hi>Kings</hi> Chap. 5. 18. <hi>and part of the</hi> 19 <hi>Verſe.</hi>
               </bibl> In this thing the Lord par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don thy Servant, that when my Maſter goeth into the Houſe of <hi>Rimmon</hi> to Worſhip there, and he leaneth on my Hand, and I bow my ſelf in the Houſe of <hi>Rimmon:</hi> When I bow down my ſelf in the Houſe of <hi>Rimmon,</hi> the Lord par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don thy Servant in this thing. And he ſaid unto him, Go in Peace,</q>
            <p>LONDON.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed for Samuel Reble, at the</hi> Turks-Head <hi>over againſt</hi> Fetter-lane <hi>end in</hi> Fleetſtreet 1700.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:45693:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45693:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Naaman Vindicated,</hi> As well from the IDOLATRIES OF THE Houſe of <hi>RIMMON,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Containing a brief Introduction, together with the Propoſal of the general Method and Deſign of the following Diſcourſe.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>SUCH is the ſtrange Obſtinacy and Perverſneſs of ſome ill Men, that even the beſt things in the World are liable to be abuſed and corrupted by them; Antidotes themſelves may be turned into Poiſon, by a wrong Application; and the Word of God it ſelf, which is the ſavour of Life to others, and the chief means of Salvation, may be, and frequently is, turned into the ſavour of Death unto thoſe that Periſh. Thus, if bad Men can but find out any one Paſſage of Scripture, which (tho' in direct con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction to the purport of many other Places, and after much ſtraining) they can make only to ſeem to countenance or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe them in the doing ſuch things, as their own vile Luſts make them firſt fully reſolved to commit; With what eaſe, ſecurity and credit, do they then conclude they may apply themſelves to the practice thereof? Nor was it therefore without ſufficient Grounds, that the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> ſpeaking of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles, tells us, <hi>That there are ſome things in them, which they that are unlearned and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable wreſt, as they do alſo the other Scriptures, unto their own De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Pet. 3. 16.</note> Into the Catalogue of which <hi>other Scriptures,</hi> this paſſage here about <hi>Naaman</hi> may certainly with as good Reaſon be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:45693:3"/>
as any other in the whole Bible: Since none perhaps has been more abuſed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or wreſted to worſe Purpoſes. From hence, ſome Men think themſelves, ſufficiently authoriſed, to take up ſuch looſe Principles, that, come what will, or let them go where they pleaſe, they'r ſure enough that their Religion ſhall never create them the leaſt trouble<hi>:</hi> Since let them travel the whole World over, they can every where afford ſo to order the Matter, and their own Behaviour, that thoſe of every place where they happen to be, ſhall have no other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, than to think their Religion the ſame with that of their own Country, be that what it will. From hence do they take Courage, if not down right to deride all the Doctrines of the Croſs, and thoſe that Practice them, yet, at leaſt, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, nay, even juſtify and applaud themſelves for all their baſe Shiftings and Turnings, and moſt diſhonourable double deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings both with God and Man.</p>
               <p>As for their inviſible Part, as they would fain believe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to have no ſuch thing, ſo they ſeem not much to ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the reſerving that entirely for God, provided in the mean time they can but wreſt a Licence from him, ſo to diſpoſe of their dear outward Man upon all Occaſions, as that they may be ſtill ſure to keep themſelves in a whole Skin. If they can obtain thus much only, no more ſeems aimed at by theſe pretended Men of Wit, who then grow proud enough to think that they have fairly out-witted their Creator. And how do they hug themſelves, and ſcornfully ſnear out their inward Satisfaction, in having at laſt diſcovered even in thoſe ſo much deſpiſed Volumes, ſuch a rich precious Paſſage, whereby (as they would pretend) they can make God himſelf, even in the moſt material point, contradict his own ſelf; who has ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly profeſſed, That <hi>he will not give his Honour to another,</hi> nor in his Worſhip admit of any Co partners.</p>
               <p>But, <hi>The Lord pardon thy Servant in this Matter,</hi> &amp;c. is the only thing like a Prayer, that can ever be obſerved to come from ſome Mens Mouths; and <hi>Naaman, Naaman,</hi> ſtill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the chief ditty not only of the Drunkards Song, but of all other ſorts of wretched Miſcreants alſo, whether more ſecret or profeſſed Enemies to Religion. If they can but force <hi>Eliſha</hi> here, ſo to reſolve this caſe of Conſcience, as they would have him, he'll then prove to this ſort of People as fit a Prophet, as if he had <hi>Propheſied unto them even of Wine and Strong Drink,</hi> nay indeed, far more acceptable and delicious. And let what will become of all the other Prophets, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, or Evangeliſts, whilſt this alone, in contradiction to all the reſt, and to himſelf too, can be perſwaded by them here, to ſeem to reconcile the Worſhip of God and that of <hi>Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:45693:3"/>
for this piece of ſervice only, they eaſily forgive and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get all his other Righteouſneſs; he ſhall then be allowed by them, to paſs for the only Man of God, nay, for a Friend ſo particular, that they'll endeavour to ſtrain Courteſies with him, and give this Prophet himſelf alſo free leave, <hi>to depart in Peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In ſhort, whilſt Atheiſts and Hypocrites would gladly ſpare all the reſt of the ſacred Writings, they'd eaſily allow this Text with their own Comments thereupon, to paſs for the only uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and Canonical piece of Scripture; to which they readily apply themſelves upon all Occaſions, as their common Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary and ſure retreat.</p>
               <p>What can be better worth the while therefore, than to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to beat them off from this, which they look upon as their ſtrongeſt Hold, by cutting off all their Lines of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication therewith, and ſhewing them how impoſſible it is for them to find therein any true Refuge.</p>
               <p>If, inſtead of thanks for this performance, I ſhall chance to meet with nothing but rage and hatred; I muſt needs ſay, 'tis no other than what was to be expected from ſome Men. But the beſt of it ſtill is, that in this Argument, I can offend none, but either ſuch vile Monſters only, as are firſt offended at the very Being of the great Authour of their Beings, or elſe the deſperate Crew of loathſome Hypocrites, who indeed, if ſearched to the bottom, will be found the greateſt and very worſt of Atheiſts. Of whom how prevalent ſoever among us may be the Intereſts, or how deplorably great ſo ever may be their wretched numbers; 'tis to be hoped notwithſtanding, that no Man, as yet, needs either to be aſhamed or afraid to encounter them. For tho' we have ſometimes known very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Treatiſes, pleading nothing but the Cauſe of Piety and Good Conſcience, wholly ſilenced and ſuppreſſed, whilſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Atheiſtical Principles have been freely ſuffer'd, in the moſt open manner, to diffuſe their Poiſon, without meeting with any of thoſe publick Cenſures which, in this Caſe, might juſtly have been expected; yet I ſhall not be ſo uncharitable to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that the Empire of this ſort of Men is yet become ſo univerſal, as that it will be judged a thing Criminal to contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict them. And as degenerate as the World is grown, I'm ſtill in good Hopes, that (as I have not, ſo) I never ſhall live to ſee in any place of the World, any ſuch unhappy ſort of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, the ſeveral particular Circumſtances of whoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution ſhall be ſuch, as will force the Miniſters thereof, either in good earneſt to believe, or ſo to act, as if they did believe, that the decay of Religion ſhould be for the Intereſt of the State, or their main hope of a civil Eſtabliſhment were chiefly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45693:4"/>
to depend upon the encreaſe of Atheiſm and Irreligion. And yet even in this ſadeſt of all Caſes, there would be this one great Comfort, That we might be moſt ſure and confident, that ſuch a Gouernment muſt needs be but of a very ſhort conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance.</p>
               <p>But in the mean time therefore, under the preſent Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which has made ſuch publick and repeated Profeſſions of diſcountenancing Atheiſm and Prophaneneſs, (whereof, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever others may do, far be it from me, to queſtion the Sincerity, or ſuſpect any politick Compoſition between the Credit of ſeeming to do the one, and the ſuppoſed Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of really doing at the ſame time the quite contrary) How ſecurely, and with the greateſt Confidence may I now apply my ſelf to this ſo highly ſeaſonable and neceſiary Task, in reſcuing this ſo much abuſed Scripture, and endeavouring to wreſt this this dangerous Weapon out of the mad Hands of ſuch Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critical or Atheiſtical Perſons as would make uſe of it only to the great Scandal of others, and to their own eternal Ruine and Deſtruction? In order to which good end, I ſhall guide my enſuing Diſcourſe according to this method, and proceed therein by theſe following ſteps.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>1ſt.</hi> I ſhall conſider briefly, how ſeveral have miſunderſtood this place of Scripture, and to what very ill Purpoſes they have apply'd it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>2dly,</hi> Endeavour to demonſtrate that it can by no means be taken in any ſuch corrupt Senſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>3dly,</hi> Give the true meaning both of <hi>Naaman</hi>'s Petition, and of the Prophets Anſwer thereto.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>4thly,</hi> I ſhall ſhew, That ſuppoſing what ſome contend for, were indeed the true genuine Senſe of this place of Scripture, yet from this Example we Chriſtians could have no ſufficient reaſon to preſume of an allowance, to diſſemble or comply in any of the like Caſes.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, I ſhall ſhew upon what unalterable Reaſons and Accounts ſuch Compliances or Diſſimulations muſt needs be always high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unlawful, and a Crime ſo hainous, that nothing can excuſe that Chriſtian, who deliberately joins, or knowingly only ſeems to join, with others, in ſuch a Worſhip as he is ſufficiently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced is falſe, or in any part thereof Sinful or Idolatrous. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with the Firſt, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:45693:4"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How ſeveral have miſunderſtood this Paſſage, and to what very ill Purpoſes they have apply'd it.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THIS Chapter contains at large the famous Hiſtory of <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Syrian,</hi> who was a Prince moſt renowned in his own Country, and one of the greateſt Favourites of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour to whom he ſerved, and ſtood related. And tho' hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to having lived in Heatheniſh Superſtition and Idolatry, according to the general Cuſtom of his Country; yet being (as we have probable Reaſons to ſuppoſe) a Perſon of no ordinary Probity of Mind, and remarkable for ſeveral very commendable Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which he had arrived at under the light of Nature; God <hi>who will not break the bruiſed Reed, nor quench the ſmoaking Flax,</hi> but delights to Communicate himſelf whereſoever he meets with any good Preparations or Capacity, was pleaſed here, (as 'tis very uſual with him) to find out a way, both to reward and reprove in this <hi>Syrian</hi> Prince, thoſe good Diſpoſitions and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings, by bringing him ſtill to the means of a farther degree of Grace and Illumination. And accordingly, the Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence was pleaſed to order ſuch a wonderful Conjunction of Circumſtances, as might contribute to the Releaſement of this great Lord, from his own far worſe <hi>Captivity,</hi> even through the means of a poor <hi>Hebrew Captive</hi> Maid, then waiting upon his Wife in his Family. By whoſe relation of the ſingular Gifts and Abilities of the <hi>Iſraelitiſh</hi> Prophet, <hi>Naaman</hi> was firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged to take a Journey into the Land of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and there addreſs himſelf to <hi>Eliſha.</hi> By whoſe directions, being now Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouſly healed of the Leproſie of his Body; the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſo convincing an Argument, and ſenſible Experiment of the infinite Perfection of that Being, by whoſe Power this great thing was affected, did, by the divine Grace, ſo powerfully work upon him, as to produce ſtill another far greater Cure of the former Diſeaſe and Leproſie of his Mind alſo: Whilſt he is brought thereupon to the Knowledge and Confeſſion of the one true God, and to a Reſolution for the future, of publickly owning and Worſhiping ſuch his ſupreme Benefactor. But yet there's one thing which this new Convert and young Proſelyte prudently foreſees, that he could not well avoid being ſtill en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to practice, after his return home; and therefore firſt deſires to be reſolved by the Prophet, whether or no he might not be indulged in this one particular, without any
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:45693:5"/>
offence to God. Which ſcruple or caſe of Conſcience, is both briefly ſtated and reſolved in the Words of the Text, now cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to diſcourſe of. <hi>In this thing, the Lord pardon thy Servant, that when my Maſter goeth into the Houſe of</hi> Rimmon <hi>to worſhip there, and he leaneth on my Hand, and I bow my ſelf in the Houſe of</hi> Rimmon; <hi>when I bow down my ſelf in the Houſe of</hi> Rimmon, <hi>the Lord pardon thy Servant in this thing. And he ſaid unto him, Go in Peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now by the <hi>Houſe of</hi> Rimmon, (as the learned have Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectur'd) we are to underſtand no other, than the Temple of the Idol <hi>Saturn,</hi> who was, of all others, moſt highly Celebrat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and greatly worſhiped by thoſe of the Eaſtern Countries. And ſeveral Atheiſtical Spirits and Hypocritical Time-ſervers have in all Ages, greedily laid hold of this Example, for the better Patroniſing of their own wicked Practices; whilſt they have been willing to underſtand theſe Words of <hi>Naaman,</hi> as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining a Petition of Indulgence, that he might, or at leaſt, as a Queſtion, whether or no he might not lawfully, together with that of the true God, join alſo the Worſhip of that I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dol? Whether he might not be permitted upon Occaſion, for the ſatisfaction of his Maſter, and that he might ſtill retain his Prince's Favour, both go along with him into the Idols Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and there bow down himſelf, to worſhip the Idol as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly; or at leaſt to ſeem to do ſo, whilſt he ſhould really, and in his Heart, there Worſhip the true God only? To which likewiſe they underſtand the Prophet's anſwering <hi>[Go in Peace,]</hi> as a plain Licence or Approbation of the Fact, and as much as if he had plainly ſaid, you may very ſafely do ſo, without any offence at all to God, or at leaſt, with confidence of his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for the ſame.</p>
               <p>And then from hence, ſuch Perſons readily conclude in the general, that all others alſo may eaſily obtain the ſame Licence and Indulgence of God, for the like Compliances and Diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations; and that for the ſecuring of their temporal Intereſt, and eſpecially to avoid down right Perſecution, they may ſafely enough join with their outward Man, in ſuch Worſhip as they are perſwaded is Sinful, Superſtitious or Idolatrous, ſo they do but take care all the while to keep their inward Man rightly devoted, and to direct the Intentions of their Hearts and Minds to the true God.</p>
               <p>And indeed, if from this Paſſage any ſuch concluſion could be regularly inferred, this would prove a moſt comfortable, and the only precious place of Scripture to ſome Men. For then Light and Darkneſs might eaſily be made Friends; <hi>Jehovah</hi> and <hi>Belial</hi> brought into a Communion with each other, their ſeveral claims being ſoon accommodated, and the Service of God and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45693:5"/>
that of <hi>Mammon</hi> well enough conſiſtent. Then they, whom the World uſually accounts ſuch, would be indeed the only true Politicians, who can ſide with every Wind, and change or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble their Practice and Profeſſion, according to the moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhionable Religion, of thoſe who ſhall happen to ſway the Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and can exalt or abaſe Men according to their Pleaſure. In a Word, then muſt both the Apoſtles, and all the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Chriſtians be reckoned for the greateſt Fools and Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, in that they ſo ſlung away their Lives, to no purpoſe; whilſt the Doctrine of Paſſive Obedience would be indeed as fond, and to the full as Ridiculous, as ſome Men have im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piouſly, and moſt prophanely endeavoured to repreſent it.</p>
               <p>But, alaſs, the Caſe of <hi>Naaman</hi> here, is very widely, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps no leſs wilfully miſtaken, by ſuch Men as are glad to catch hold of any thing, that may but ſeem to afford them any, the moſt feeble Support or Countenance in their double-Dealings. Who, tho' they may for the preſent highly applaud their own Ingenuity, in finding out ſuch pretty Expedients, and make a ſhift for a while to deceive both others and themſelves thereby, will yet be ſure to find in the Concluſion, that God is a moſt jealous God, and cannot be ſo mocked or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by them; but will prove at laſt a conſuming Fire to all ſuch double minded Hypocrites, and moſt abominable Diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers. And ſo I paſs now to the ſecond general thing, which I am to endeavour to ſhew, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>That this Paſſage of Scripture can by no means be taken in any ſuch corrupt Senſe, as I have alread repreſented; nor conſequently afford any Foundation for any ſuch Inferences to be made therefrom.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THat <hi>Naaman</hi> here in theſe Words cannot be underſtood to deſire, either really to Worſhip <hi>Rimmon,</hi> or <hi>Saturn,</hi> or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Idol, together with the true God, nor yet to beg leave ſo much as to diſſemble in the Caſe, or to endeavour to be thought to do ſo, may, I think, ſufficiently appear from theſe following Arguments, grounded upon the expreſs Context.</p>
               <p>For in the firſt Place, for him to have deſir'd this, would have been directly contrary to the preſent Senſe of his own Mind, and the plain Convictions of his Conſcience. We may I confeſs, meet with ſeveral in Scripture, who Worſhipped the true
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45693:6"/>
God in conjunction with falſe ones: As we read of that mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed People, whom the King of <hi>Aſſyria</hi> had planted in <hi>Samaria,</hi> in the room of the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">2 King. 17. 33.</note> 
                  <hi>That they feared the Lord, and ſerv'd their own Gods alſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the Prophet <hi>Zephaniah</hi> likewiſe ſpeaks of thoſe, who uſed to <hi>Worſhip and Swear by the Lord, and to Swear by Malcham alſo.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Zeph. 1. 5.</note> But yet, they who ſtood thus affected, did not at the ſame time believe, that thoſe whom they ſo Worſhipped, were meer Idols and falſe Gods, and ſuch as could not help them, but were on the contrary (tho' very falſly) perſwaded of their Ability, to help and benefit thoſe that Served them; which was alſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally the only Motive to their ſo Worſhipping, as is evident in the Caſe of King <hi>Ahab,</hi> of whom we read, <note n="*" place="margin">2 Chron. 28. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>That he Sacrificed to the Gods of Damaſcus, which ſmote him, and he ſaid, becauſe the Gods of the Kings of Syria help them, therefore will I Sacrifice to them, that they may help me.</hi> Whilſt on the contrary, I'm apt to believe, we can ſcarce find the Example of any one, who cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> ever yet find in his Heart, really to Worſhip that Being, from whom he could entertain no Hope at all, of receiving any Advantage by his ſo doing. What St. <hi>Paul</hi> affirms of thoſe, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> adore God Almighty, being no leſs true alſo concerning the Wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhippers of Idols and falſe Gods, <hi>viz.</hi> They that come unto them muſt however believe, that they are, and that they are Reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers likewiſe, of thoſe that diligently ſeek unto them. And accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, we ſhall find, that all which either the Prophets or Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles thought requiſite towards the reducing of the Superſtitions <hi>Heathen,</hi> was only by the moſt ſubſtantial Arguments, to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate to them, that thoſe whom they Worſhipped were no true Gods nor had any, the leaſt Ability in them, to help or ſuccour their devoted Servants; as rightly concluding; that after they had once ſufficiently convinc'd them of this Truth, nothing further was then neceſſary, to diſſwade them from their Idolatries.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Naaman</hi> here; was now ſo firmly perſwaded of the Truth of theſe particulars, that ſcarce any Words could more fully ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs his abundant Satisfaction herein, than thoſe which we find him uſe to that purpoſe, in the 15 Verſe of that ſame Chapter: <hi>Behold,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>now I know, that there is no God in all the earth, but in Iſrael.</hi> So that ſhould he, after this have ſtill deſired to reſerve to himſelf the Worſhip of any other, beſides the true God only, he muſt have acted therein quite contrary to the plaineſt Convictions of his own Judgment; directly againſt all Reaſon, and without any of thoſe Motives, which alone can be the Foundation of any mans really giving any Religious Worſhip to any thing.</p>
               <p>But ſtill in the ſecond Place, we may alſo conſider, That this would have been no leſs contrary and repugnant to thoſe firm
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45693:6"/>
Purpoſes and Reſolutions, which he immediately before ſignified, about his abſtaining from all Idolatrous Worſhip for the future: For he does in theſe very words, moſt ſolemnly declare and profeſs his Determination; <hi>Thy Servant will henceforth, offer nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Burnt-offerings, nor Sacrifice unto other Gods, but unto the Lord.</hi> Where, under the words <hi>(Burnt-offerings</hi> and <hi>Sacrifices)</hi> as under the moſt ſignal and noble Species, we are to underſtand com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended all other Acts of external Worſhip whatſoever; as we find the ſame frequently uſed, according to this Latitude of Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification, in ſeveral other Places.</p>
               <p>So that now, if we joyn all the ſeveral parts of his Speech to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, it muſt needs ſound, as if he had, after this manner, addreſſed himſelf to the Prophet: I am now abundantly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced, that thoſe whom I have hitherto owned and ſerved for ſuch, are indeed, no Gods at all; but that the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> is the only true one, to whom I am therefore fully purpoſed for the future (renouncing all the vain Idols of mine own Country) to perform all due Homage, and to bear true Faith, and conſtant Allegiance; and accordingly ſincerely determine, never any more as long as I live, to do any one Act of Worſhip to any other, under that Notion. In one thing only, I muſt needs deſire ſome grains of Allowance and Indulgence; and I hope God will not take it amiſs, if I ſtill retain one Rival with him; nor be ſo jealous, as not to give me free leave, as often as my Maſter goes to Worſhip, in the Houſe of <hi>Rimmon,</hi> (which to be ſure, according to his wonted Superſtition, will be very frequently) that I may alſo go in with him, and ſtill pay my Worſhip and Devotious with him, to that one moſt Renown'd Idol, as I have formerly been accuſtomed.</p>
               <p>Now muſt not <hi>Naaman,</hi> think you, in any ſuch Petition as this, have both been ſtrangely inconſiſtent with himſelf, and groſly repugnant to his own Reſolution? And what would this have been elſe, but to have Breathed both Hot and Cold with the ſame Breath? Than which therefore what can be imagined more unlikely, concerning a Perſon, who, by ſo many other moſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Inſtances, had demonſtrated himſelf, a moſt zealous and ſincere Proſelyte?</p>
               <p>And ſtill, if any ſhould imagine, (as ſome have done) that <hi>Naaman</hi> here begged leave, to Bow down himſelf in the Houſe of <hi>Rimmon,</hi> not indeed as deſigning therein, any farther Worſhip to that Idol, but meerly to diſſemble his true Faith, and as a Blinder to the Eyes of his Maſter, that ſo he might conceal his change of Religion, from the knowledge of the King of <hi>Syria;</hi> whilſt all the time, under that Diſguiſe, he intended with his Heart and Mind, to Worſhip the true God only; as a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Confutation then, of any ſuch ſuppoſal as this, it may.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:45693:7"/>
In the third Place be conſidered, That ſuch were his Words and Actions, and other Circumſtances of his Behaviour, as plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enough ſhew, that he meant to proceed moſt openly and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuouſly in this whole Affair, without any ſuch under-hand Jug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings or Diſguiſes; and that indeed he could not, either deſign or entertain the leaſt Hopes of being ſucceſsful in any ſuch Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulation. For firſt, he declares his renunciation of all Idols, and his purpoſe to Worſhip the true God only, ſo openly, and before ſo many Witneſſes, that he could not but conclude, this would ſoon come to the Ears of his Maſter, upon his return home. And whereas, had he left his Attendance behind him, at ſome convenient diſtance, and ſingly betaking himſelf to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, had only whiſper'd theſe things in his Ear, there might have been then, ſome Colour to have ſuſpected ſome ſuch Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical deſign in him: But now on the contrary, we expreſsly read in the <hi>15th.</hi> Verſe, that as ſoon as he found himſelf Healed, <hi>He returned to the Man of God, he and all his Company, and came and ſtood before him, and ſaid,</hi> what there follows. Nor could he there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore after this, in the leaſt hope, ſo to Seal up the Mouths of all thoſe, and to conjure them to ſuch perpetual Silence, but that ſome one among ſo numerons a Retinue, (which we may well ſuppoſe attended him) would either out of zealous Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, or for their Intereſt, and to currie Favour with the King himſelf, be ſure to acquaint him with the whole Matter. And ſtill, ſuppoſe he could have thought his great Authority over all theſe, to have been ſufficient to prevail with them to hold their Peace; yet even the two Mules-burden of Earth, which he car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried back with him, he muſt needs think, would be apt to tell Tales of him to his Maſter, eſpecially, when it ſhould come to be ſo employed as he deſign'd, towards the making of an Altar, whereon to Sacrifice to the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> according to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Cuſtom, which could not in all probability, be conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Performed by him ſo ſecretly, as not to come at laſt to the knowledge of him, who, (as he was well aware) had ſo many Eyes and Ears, to ſee and hear with.</p>
               <p>Again, ſhould we ſuppoſe, he could be ſecure as to this por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular alſo, yet that conſtant Abſence, which he was now reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved upon, and his perpetual abſtaining from thoſe Idolatrous Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings and Sacrifices, which were daily performed in his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and in which ſo great a Favourite as himſelf uſed formerly ſtill to aſſiſt and accompany his Prince; even this of it ſelf, he could not but conclude, muſt needs betray him. Nor could he hope, by a few external Cringes, now and then in the Houſe of <hi>Rimmon,</hi> to expiate for his notorous Neglect and Contempt, of all their other numerous Idols; or to hinder the plain Diſcovery of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45693:7"/>
his having brought home another Religion, than what he car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried out with him.</p>
               <p>But laſtly, were it poſſible for us, notwithſtanding all theſe groſs Contradictions, and manifold Abſurdities, to take theſe words of <hi>Naaman,</hi> as containing a Petition of this nature, yet the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets Anſwer thereto, <hi>GO IN PEACE,</hi> may of it ſelf, abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuffice to demonſtrate, that we cannot underſtand them in any ſuch corrupt Senſe. For otherwiſe we muſt make <hi>Eliſha</hi> here, plainly to approve of a moſt groſs piece of Diſſimulation, and (like the falſe Prophets) to ſay <hi>Peace,</hi> where God hath ſaid no <hi>Peace;</hi> or elſe, if we believe him to have been a true Prophet, we muſt then, make God himſelf (in oppoſition to the whole Current of his revealed Will in all other Places, as well as in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect contradiction to his own Nature) to allow of a Co-rival, or Co-partner with him in his Worſhip; who has yet told us, <hi>That he will not give his Honour to another,</hi> and that nothing is more abominable to him, than all ſuch kind of Hypocriſie.</p>
               <p>Nor will that Expoſition of thoſe, much mend the matter, who take theſe words of the Prophet, <hi>Depart in Peace,</hi> not as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining any Anſwer at all, or Reſolution, whether he might, or might not do the thing in Queſtion; but that, being wholly ſilent as to this, he gave him therein only the uſual Salu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation at parting, and no more than if he had barely ſaid, <hi>Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> or <hi>God b' w'ye.</hi> For as it ſeems very ſtrange and unlikely, either that <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſhould ſo ſullàinly put him off, without giving him any Satisfaction, about a Point ſo highly important, or that <hi>Naaman</hi> ſhould ſo contentedly depart, with a meer formal Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement, inſtead of a ſolid Reſolution: So I cannot ſee, how the Prophet could have ſafely beſtowed upon him, even ſo much as that uſual Salutation, tho' we ſhould make no more of it) had this Prince been indeed ſo much in Love with Hypocriſie and Diſſimulation, and ſuch a <hi>Convert-Apoſtate,</hi> as ſome have moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juriouſly endeavour'd to repreſent him. For St. <hi>John,</hi> ſpeaking of an <hi>Apoſtate,</hi> ſaith; <hi>Receive not ſuch a one into your Houſe, neither</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Joh. 10. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>bid him God ſpeed; for he that biddeth him God ſpeed, is partaker of his evil Deeds.</hi> Where, (as a Learned Author obſerves) this Form of Interdicting, was in imitation of the the Practice of the <hi>Jews,</hi> in their <hi>Anathema</hi> againſt <hi>Apoſtates,</hi> who were to be excluded, not only from Commerce, but even from the ſmalleſt kind of ordinary Salutations.</p>
               <p>But indeed, tho' I ſhall not deny, that this form of Speech may perhaps, in ſome few places, be uſed only as an ordinary Bleſſing at parting, and ſignify no more than a bare <hi>Farewel,</hi> (as it ſeems uſed, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1. 17. and 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20. 42.) yet upon a diligent Conſideration of all other places, wherein this Phraſe, <hi>Go in Peace,</hi> is to be met with, immediately follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45693:8"/>
upon any Precedent Queſtion or Petition, we ſhall always find it uſed as an Affirmative Anſwer, or plain Conceſſion of the thing enquired after, or Petitioned for; as <hi>Ex.</hi> 8. 18. <hi>Judg.</hi> 18. 5, 6. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 9. and ſeveral other Places. And 'tis moſt certain likewiſe, both that the Prophet intended no leſs by it here in this Place, and that it was accordingly ſo underſtood by <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Syrian,</hi> as an affirmative Reſolution of his Scruple, or a grant of the Thing, (whatſoever it was) which he asked leave to Practiſe. By which I am now reminded to proceed to the third general Conſideration or Enquiry, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What it was indeed that he asked, or what is the true Senſe and Meaning of</hi> Naaman<hi>'s Petition?</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>NOW I find three diſtinct Senſes, according to which ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral learned Perſons have expounded and underſtood this Petition and the Anſwer to it: All which I ſhall think it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary both to recite, and alſo to ſhew, upon what Accounts and Reaſons the two former of them cannot ſafely be rely'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on nor received; but that the laſt only, is, in all probabily the true genuine Expoſition to be embraced.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>1ſt.</hi> Then, ſome take it to refer not to the future, but to the time paſt, and ſo as to contain a Petition, or the hope of Pardon, only for what he had formerly committed, as if he had ſaid, <hi>In this thing the Lord forgive,</hi> or <hi>I hope the Lord will forgive me,</hi> or <hi>not puniſh me upon that account,</hi> viz. <hi>That I have ſo often heretofore accompanied my Maſter into the Houſe of</hi> Rimmon, <hi>and there together with him, bowed down my ſelf to, and Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated that Idol or falſe Deity.</hi> To which the Prophet's anſwering <hi>Go in Peace,</hi> muſt then be underſtood, as a plain Conceſſion of what he deſired, and no leſs than if he had ſaid; <hi>Be of good Cheer, as well aſſured from me, in his name, That God does freely grant you Pardon for all that is paſt, and will not impute unto you what you did ignorantly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, tho' as it muſt be acknowledg'd, that this Expoſition wants not the Countenance of ſeveral Modern Interpreters of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lightfoot</hi> in <hi>Luc.</hi> 4. 27.</note> no mean Note, (among whom is the learned Dr. <hi>Lightfoot</hi> in particular) ſo it cannot be denied, but that, might the ſame
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:45693:8"/>
obtain, 'twould both moſt effectually take away all manner of accaſion or pretence from Hypocrites, to excuſe or patronize their Diſſimulations, by any thing of this Example, and would at the ſame time alſo well enough become <hi>Naamans</hi> Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as a ſingular good Argument and Specimen of his being a true Convert, and of a moſt pious Mind, to be ſo ſollicitous about obtaining God's Pardon, for that hainous Crime of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, which he had formerly committed, tho' in the time of his Ignorance: Yet I am very apt to believe, notwithſtanding all this, that this Expoſition will ſcarcely ever be allowed to paſs for genuine, by any one who ſhall well conſider theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Reaſons to the contrary.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>1ſt.</hi> Becauſe, tho', as to the Actions relating to <hi>Naaman</hi>'s Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, the time may ſeem to be ſomewhat doubtfully expreſſed in the Hebrew Text, yet even there alſo <hi>Naaman</hi>'s own bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down himſelf in the Houſe of <hi>Rimmon,</hi> is plainly expreſſed in the future. To which we may alſo add, that not only the vulgar Latin, and the Septuagint, but the <hi>Chaldee</hi> Paraphraſe, and the <hi>Syriack,</hi> and all other Verſions in the Polyglot, do read all, not in the time paſt, but future. So that for any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Perſon, now at this diſtance, to go about to read it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, in contradiction to ſo great and general Authority, may ſeem very juſtly Condemnable, as too bold an attempt of Alteration.</p>
               <p>Again, Secondly, we may alſo conſider, that there are ſome things here related by <hi>Naaman,</hi> as the plain Motive or Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his bowing down himſelf in the Houſe of <hi>Rimmon,</hi> which yet we cannot but acknowledge, would have been mentioned to no purpoſe, but muſt have been altogether impertinently added under that Notion, ſhould we underſtand him to ask Pardon for what was already paſt. For what needed he then at all to have brought in his Maſter, or to have talked of what he uſed to do? Since, unleſs we will ſuppoſe him to have been all along a meer Hypocrite in his very Idolatry, we muſt needs conclude, that, tho' his Maſter had never gone in thither, nor there leaned upon his Hand, yet <hi>Naaman</hi> would have thought himſelf obliged, as well as others of his Country Men, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to have repaired to the ſame Temple, and there have been actually engaged to have done all he did by way of Worſhip, moved thereto by his own inward Affection and zealous Superſtition, and out of <hi>meer Conſcience towards the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dol.</hi> Whereas on the contrary, if we underſtand him to ſpeak of the time to come, we ſhall then find, that thoſe Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances are very naturally, and upon good Reaſon mentioned
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:45693:9"/>
by him. Since, now he was Illuminated and convinced of his former Error, and become a Proſelyte to the true Religion, he plainly foreſees, and accordingly intimates to the Prophet, that nothing but his deſire, in what he might, to gratify his Maſter, and to pay him thoſe civil Reſpects, which he ſtood obliged to, by the particular Office which he held at Court, could for the future engage him, or prove any Motive or Occaſion, either of his going any more to the Idols Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or of his doing any thing there, for which he might ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect himſelf, to ſtand in need of Pardon or Indulgence.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, He cannot be underſtood to relate to the time paſt, becauſe ſo, his Words will be found much too narrow and reſtrained, ſufficiently to anſwer or expreſs the neceſſities of his real Caſe; as indeed containing neither ſuch a full acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of his former Errors, nor ſuch a comprehenſive Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of Pardon for the ſame, as was requiſite for a true Convert to have made under his Circumſtances. And had he reſpected the time paſt, I make no Queſtion, but that he would have expreſſed himſelf in ſome ſuch more general form as this; <hi>The Lord Pardon me for all the manifold Idolatries I have been formerly guilty of:</hi> Whereas now, we find him uſhering in his Petition with this Preface, <hi>Only, in this thing, the Lord par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don thy Servant,</hi> &amp;c. and then he inſtanceth only in his bowing down himſelf, or Worſhipping in the Houſe of <hi>Rimmon.</hi> But had he then, can we think, in all the time of his Idolatry, been never guilty of Worſhipping any other falſe Gods, nor in any other place but in the before ſaid Chappel only?</p>
               <p>This cannot be imagin'd, unleſs we can at the ſame time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve either that <hi>Naaman</hi> had always been a mere Heretick in his own Country, or elſe that it was the general Cuſtome of the <hi>Syrians,</hi> to Worſhip no other Idol but <hi>Rimmon:</hi> The firſt of which is altogether groundleſs, and moſt irrational to ſuppoſe; and the ſecond directly contrary to plain matter of Fact, as is abundantly atteſted in the moſt authentick Records of this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair. For does not the Scripture expreſly tell us; of the <hi>Gods of</hi> Damaſcus, <hi>and of the Gods of the Kings of Syria?</hi> And more <note place="margin">2 Chr. 28. 23. Jud. 10. 6.</note> particularly of <hi>Baalim,</hi> and <hi>Aſhterotb,</hi> the Gods of <hi>Syria?</hi> And has not the learned <hi>Selden,</hi> a large and curious Tract DE DIS SYRIS? In which he both ſhews, That Idolatry it ſelf had its firſt riſe and beginning in <hi>Syria,</hi> and tells us like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe particularly of <hi>Bell, Aſhtaroth, Dagon, Dammutz, Moloch, Nergal, and the golden Calf,</hi> as Idols whoſe Worſhip and Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal was firſt owing to the <hi>Syrians,</hi> beſides ſeveral other falſe Gods whoſe Names and Worſhip that People afterwards borrowed from other Nations. 'Tis plain alſo from <hi>Lucian,</hi> (who was him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:45693:9"/>
a <hi>Syrian,</hi> and of the City of <hi>Samoſata)</hi> that they Worſhiped the Sun, the Moon, <hi>Jupiter, Saturn, Venus, Juno,</hi> and ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Idols borrowed from the Egyptians, who were almoſt infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite in their Superſtitions and falſe Gods. The ſame Author <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luci.</hi> lib. de Deâ Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riâ.</note> likewiſe particularly deſcribes both the Temples of ſeveral of the <hi>Syrian</hi> Idols, and what Rites they uſed in their ſeveral Worſhips of them.</p>
               <p>Now among ſuch a numerous company of other Idols, which the <hi>Syrians</hi> Worſhiped, we have the greateſt Reaſon to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that <hi>Naaman</hi> alſo (who appears to have been a Perſon of ſo naturally devout a Temper) muſt needs have been enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, as well as others, frequently to offer and to Sacrifice to all thoſe Idols, and that in all or moſt of their Temples; and conſequently that had he here deſigned to ask Pardon for his former Offences of this kind, he could never have thought it ſufficient to have ſpoken only of his bowing in the Houſe of <hi>Rimmon.</hi> For which he might have obtained Pardon, and have been utterly undone notwithſtanding, upon the account of his other multiply'd Acts of Idolatry.</p>
               <p>So that this Queſtion of his, (for both the <hi>Syriack</hi> and <hi>Arabian</hi> Verſions read it, <hi>Will the Lord Pardon thy Servant?)</hi> I ſay, this Queſtion or Petition, call it which you will, muſt neceſſarily be taken to relate not to any thing he had done formerly, but to ſomewhat he might likely be engaged to do hereafter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>2dly,</hi> Therefore, another Expoſition is that of thoſe who right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly referring all to the future, do yet underſtand <hi>Naaman</hi> here, not at all to Queſtion, or to deſire to be reſolved by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, whether what he feared to be engaged ſtill to do in the Houſe of <hi>Rimmon,</hi> were unlawful or not; but ſuppoſing him already ſufficiently convinced, that his bowing there was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a very great Sin, do make all the force of his Petition to conſiſt only in this, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Prophet would not fail to put up his Prayer unto God, for the Pardon of ſuch his fault, if indeed he ſhould (as he ſeem'd to fear) be prevailed upon to commit it. And this Expoſition now ſeems wholly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon the Authority of the vulgar Latin only, which reads my Text thus; <hi>Hoc ſolum eſt, de quo depreceris dominum pro ſervo tuo,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>This is the only thing, concerning which I entreat you earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to pray to God in the behalf of thy Servant, that when my Maſter goeth into the Houſe of</hi> Rimmon, <hi>that the Lord would par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don thy Servant for this thing.</hi> According to which, they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand <hi>Naaman</hi> here to deſire, neither any ſuch thing as leave to Sin, nor yet that God would approve of the Fact, (neither of which we may be ſure, would ever have been granted by <hi>Eliſha)</hi> but that upon conſideration of his own Frailty, and the powerful Temptations he ſhould meet with, foreſeeing that he
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:45693:10"/>
ſhould not avoid relapſing into his former Sin of Idolatry, or at leaſt of Diſſimulation; he does thereupon now only beg of the Prophet, that he would by his Prayers endeavour to intercede with God for his Pardon, after he ſhould actually ſo relapſe. And they make likewiſe the Prophet's anſwering, <hi>Go in Peace,</hi> to ſignify nothing more than a bare Promiſe, that he would ſo Pray to God for him.</p>
               <p>Now it muſt be acknowledged, that this underſtanding of the Words (could we allow it for genuine) may ſeem at firſt wholly to preclude Hypocrites, from all colour and pretence of inferring the lawfulneſs of Diſſimulation, in matters of Religion, from any thing of this Example: For both <hi>Naaman</hi> himſelf was ſo far from thinking any ſuch matter, that on the contrary, (according to this Expoſition) he plainly ſuppoſes, that what he was likely to be engaged to practiſe, was in it ſelf a very great Sin, and ſuch for which he ſhould therefore greatly ſtand in need of Pardon. And beſides, there is a great deal of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between aſſerting, That God may be prevailed upon to forgive, and ſaying, that God will never be at all offended at ſuch an action. And farther ſtill, it is one thing for <hi>Eliſha</hi> to aſſure this <hi>Syrian</hi> that God would actually pardon him, and another thing to promiſe him only, that he would pray to God for his Pardon.</p>
               <p>But notwithſtanding all this, we ſhall upon better conſideration find that even this Explication will not (as it may firſt ſeem to promiſe) ſo effectually remove all ſhelter from Hypocrites, but that they may from thence fetch ſome Encouragement for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their Diſſimulation; and that however it cannot be ſafely received, as containing the true Senſe and Meaning of the Place. And that, for ſeveral very good Reaſons to the contrary.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>1ſt.</hi> Becauſe it is grounded wholly upon the vulgar Latin, which is the only Tranſlation that may ſeem to favour this Senſe; whilſt yet it has no manner of Countenance, either from the Original Hebrew, or indeed any other Verſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>2dly,</hi> Becauſe it depends upon a wrong Hypotheſis, as falſely ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing, that <hi>Naaman</hi> by his future bowing in the Houſe of <hi>Rimmon</hi> intended to perform an act of external Worſhip to that Idol, or at, leaſt, that he was affraid of being engaged ſo far to diſſemble his Religion for the ſake of his Maſter. Whereas, on the contrary, I have already demonſtrated, and I hope, by unanſwerable Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from the plain context, that <hi>Naaman</hi> could entertain no ſuch Hypocritical deſign, nor was at preſent troubled with any ſuch fear or ſuſpicion concerning himſelf: But on the other Hand fully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin'd to deal moſt openly and freely in this whole matter; and to let all the World know what Religion he was of. And that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:45693:10"/>
moreover he had already ſo far proceeded herein, as that now he could not well conceive any reaſonable Hope of being ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful in the concealment of his new Religion, by any future complyances ſhort of down-right Apoſtacy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>3dly.</hi> Becauſe had <hi>Naaman</hi> had any ſuch ſecret Intention, (as according to this ſuppoſition) to continue in a known Sin, by playing the vile Diſſembler; I cannot ſee how <hi>Eliſha</hi> in this Caſe, could ſafely have promiſed him, ſo much as to pray to God for his Pardon. For to be ſure, 'tis never Lawful, for a Man to Promiſe any thing, but what it is alſo Lawful for him after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to Perform. And tho' we may ſometimes, with due Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, Lawfully Pray for what we know not whether or no God will grant; yet we can never Lawfully Pray to God, for what we are before-hand moſt aſſured, neither will nor can ever be granted by him. But now we are moſt certain, that God will never grant Forgiveneſs to any Sinner, while he continues Impenitent: And no better than ſuch, muſt <hi>Naaman</hi> needs be accounted, whilſt we here ſuppoſe him, in one Caſe, reſolved to continue a groſs Diſſembler to his Lives end.</p>
               <p>So that for the Prophet to Pray for the Pardon of one, whom he knew to be thus affected and reſolv'd, would in effect, have been no other, than for him to have deſired of God, that he would be reconciled unto Sin it ſelf: Give a Man leave to be an Idolater; or not to be any longer offended with (what is naturally moſt abominable to him) even the moſt groſs Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie; than which, what can be imagined more abſurd?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>4thly.</hi> It cannot eaſily be conceiv'd, how any ſuch Promiſe as this, (made without any concomitant Caution) ſhould tend to any other purpoſe, than only to encourage the ſuppoſed Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, with greater ſecurity to proceed on in his Offence, by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him probable hopes of Impunity therein. Since he could not but conclude, that the Prophet would never Promiſe to Pray for that, in which he knew he might offend God, but could never hope to be heard of him, and if he could hope to be heard, himſelf might then alſo hope for ſafety in his continued Diſſimulation and Hypocriſie.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, if it ſhould be ſaid, That all that the young Proſelyte here deſir'd, or the other promiſed, was to Pray for his Pardon, not abſolutely, but only upon ſuppoſition of his true Repentance after his Lapſe, or at leaſt, for both theſe together in conjunction; tho' it muſt then be acknowledged, that were the Caſe indeed ſo, the Prophet might ſafely enough, in reſpect of himſelf, both paſs his word for, and likewiſe make good thus much: Yet conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering <hi>Naamans</hi> ſuppoſed Circumſtances, 'tis very unlikely, that <hi>Eliſha</hi> would make ſuch a Promiſe, ſingly, and without adding thereto ſome neceſſary Caution. Nor can it be thought in this Caſe, that he would have been ſo very ſparing of his Words,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:45693:11"/>
as to have diſmiſs'd him (as we find he does) with a bare <hi>DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PART IN PEACE;</hi> but would rather have thought fit withall, to have enlarged himſelf towards him in ſome farther Advice, to this, or the like purpoſe: <hi>If you do hereafter commit the Sin you ſpeak of, I Promiſe you ſo far to comply with your Request, as not to fail Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God, for your Repentance and Pardon thereupon. But yet, let me adviſe you, to have a ſpecial Care, that you do not ſo rely upon any thing of this, as in the least to encourage your ſelf therefrom, in any ſuch feul Act of Diſſimulation: For tho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I may Lawfully thus Pray for you; yet I cannot tell whether or no I ſhall be heard therein; nor can I aſſure you thereupon, that God will, but have rather very great Reaſon to fear, that he will not grant Repentance, nor conſequently Pardon, to a Wretch, who ſhall ſo deliberately Sin against the plainest Convictions of his own Conſcience, and ſo chuſe to Offend, as preſuming before-hand of Repentance afterwards. And however, I must needs tell you, it is much better to chuſe to die, than deliberately to do any thing of which you know you ſhall need to Repent afterwards. And I ſhall therefore, much rather Pray to God before-hand, that he would be pleaſed to inſpire your Heart, with ſuch noble Courage, Generoſity, and Contempt of the World; as may enable you (if need be) cheerfully to forgoe all the Riches and Preferments, all the vain Honours and dangerous Favours of the Court, and to be ready to lay down your very Life, rather than ever entertain the least Thought of venturing to offend God, and wound your own Conſcience, by any ſuch baſe and hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critical Compliances.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After ſome ſuch manner as this now, we have good Reaſon to think, the Wiſdom and Sincerity of the Prophet, would have prompted him to have dealth with his new Convert, had he really found him ſo halting, and hypocritically inclined, as the forego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Expoſition would ſuppoſe him. And theſe Reaſons therefore I hope may ſuffice to ſhew, that the ſame cannot be allowed for Genuine, as well as that it was not in the Opinion of <hi>Eliſha,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſinful Act, which <hi>Naaman</hi> foreſees himſelf likely to be enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to Practiſe, and concerning the Lawfulneſs of which he here deſires to be reſolved.</p>
               <p>I ſhall therefore now proceed to the third and laſt Expoſition, and that which ſeems to deliver the true Senſe and Meaning, of this difficult and very much mis-apply'd Scripture: Of which I take that to be the true Explication, which underſtands <hi>Naamans</hi> Petition here or Queſtion, to relate only to the right Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of a civil or indifferent Action, which was liable to be miſconſtrued; and ſuppoſes his future Bowing in the Houſe of <hi>Rimmon,</hi> to be deſign'd by him meerly as a civil Act, out of Reſpect only to his Maſter, and in pure Compliance with the diſcharge of that particular Office, which he held at Court; as if he had ſaid: There's one thing, which if I ſtill continue, I
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:45693:11"/>
hope God will not take it amiſs at my Hands, or Puniſh me up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that Account: But yet before I venture on it, I deſire you to ſatisfie me, whether he will or not. The thing I mean is this; you muſt know, that I being in very high Place, and Favour with the King my Maſter, do generally go next his Side to ſupport him; and more eſpecially, when he goes to Worſhip in the Houſe of <hi>Rimmon,</hi> my Place requires, that I ſhould ſtill lend him my Hand or Arm to lean upon, that ſo he may Bow with greater Eaſe and State; and I thus aſſiſt him, both to proſtrate himſelf, and to get up again afterwards; which I cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently do, without obſerving the ſame Motions and Geſtures of Body that he does; not that I deſign thereby to do, or ſo much as to be thought to do any farther Worſhip to that Idol as formerly; but am reſolved at the ſame time, openly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, both to my Maſter, and to the whole World, in plain words, as well as by all my other Actions, the quite contrary. Now, may I, think you, upon theſe Conditions, (if I can ſo ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie my Maſter) ſtill keep my Place at Court, and do what it ſo far requires, without any Offence to God? To which <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhas</hi> anſwering, <hi>Go in Peace,</hi> is as much as if he had plainly told him; <hi>You may ſafely do this, without any Offence to him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here now, by the way, I cannot well forbear taking oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to mention a ſome what like Caſe, and which alſo had a like Reſolution given of it, even by Chriſtian and Proteſtant Divines too: Both which had their dare no longer ſince a go, than about the Beginning of the Reformation. When the then Emperour of <hi>Germany,</hi> being about to go to Maſs, according to Cuſtome, commanded the <hi>Elector</hi> of <hi>Saxony</hi> to be there, and to carry the Sword before him; for that's the Duty of the Houſe of <hi>Saxony</hi> upon ſuch ſolemn Occaſions: He having conſulted his Divines in the Caſe, who told him, That he might lawfully do it, ſince he was called upon to do his Duty, not to go to Maſs, went accordingly, accompanied by <hi>George</hi> Marqueſs of <hi>Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg;</hi> but none of the reſt came, as <hi>Sleiden</hi> informs us. Which <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sleid.</hi> Hiſt. Ref. <hi>l.</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi> 127.</note> Caſe notwithſtanding, whether it was rightly ſo determin'd, or otherwiſe, depends (as I take it) upon the time of his ſtay there, and the other particular Circumſtances of his Behaviour, with which that Hiſtorian has left us unacquainted. Tho afterwards conſulting <hi>Thuanus,</hi> I am from that excellent Writer inform'd, that the Elector only went into the Chappel, and leaving the Sword there, preſently came away.</p>
               <p>But I return to <hi>Naaman—.</hi> Tho' againſt this Expoſition alſo, there may perhaps, be raiſed ſome Scruples and Objections, yet none of them, I think, will be found to be of any ſuch great weight or moment, as that they can bear much ſway with any judicious Conſiderator, eſpecially when we ſhall perceive how eaſily they may
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:45693:12"/>
be remov'd, and will admit of a very ſatisfactory Solution. Towards which, I ſhall not think unfit to beſtow yet another diſtinct Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Wherein ſeveral Objections, which either have been, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps may be made againſt this laſt, and (as I ſuppoſe) only true Expoſition, are fairly propoſed and anſwered.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>AND <hi>1st</hi> then, Whereas it is objected, that this Senſe or under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of this Place of Scripture is wholly groundleſs and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carious; the Objection it ſelf may indeed much rather appear to be ſo, when we ſhall conſider what ſufficient Grounds and weighty Reaſons we have to embrace this Expoſition; as that alone which of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering no manner of Force or violence to any of the Words of the Text, does alſo fairly avoid all thoſe Difficulties, Inconveniencies and Contradictions, which I have ſhewn to be the neceſſary Conſequences and Attendants of any other Interpretation; and makes <hi>Naaman</hi> to ask nothing in the leaſt repugnant, either to his now rectified Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or Reſolution; nothing but what was fairly conſiſtent both with his Belief, that there was no other God, and with his Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination alſo, that he would henceforth Worſhip no other, but only the God of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> nothing contrary either to his foregoing publick Declaration, or to any other Action or Intention of his, expreſſed in the Context; in a Word, nothing but what might well comport with the deſigns both of an honeſt, ſincere Proſelyte, and of a Wiſe and Prudent Man, reſolved in the firſt place to give God his due, and not to do any thing by which he might offend Heaven; and then deſirous in the next place, ſtill to ſerve and gratify his Earthly Lord and Maſter, in what he ſafely might, and without danger of incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring any ſuch Offence. Nor yet is <hi>Eliſha</hi> thereby made ſubject to the great Abſurdity of putting him off, with a moſt abrupt and ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len <hi>Farewel,</hi> without giving any anſwer to his Scruple<hi>:</hi> But on the contrary, (according to the plain Senſe of the ſame Phraſe in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Places) is fairly underſtood, to reſolve his Queſtion in the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmative, and yet therein not to grant any thing but what was very fit for him ſo to do, (according to conſideration had of the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Circumſtances of the Caſe) and well becoming both the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Faithfulneſs and Sincerity of ſo holy a Prophet. To all which we may alſo add, as a thing not a little conſiderable, that it cannot be imagin'd, upon what account, or to what purpoſe <hi>Naaman</hi> ſhould talk of his bowing in the Houſe of <hi>Rimmon,</hi> in this Caſe only, when his Maſter ſhould there lean upon his Arm if by his bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:45693:12"/>
there, he had meant any thing of Religious Worſhip to the Idol, or had deſigned therein any more than a meer civil Act or Office of Service and Reſpect to his Maſter.</p>
               <p>Whereas, if we underſtand it under this Notion only, it will then appear, both very natural and pertinent, that he ſhould ſo ſpeak of his Maſters leaning upon his Arm, as the ſole thing which could now occaſion his Bowing in that Temple, or his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any Act there for the future, that could be liable to mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtruction, or which he could think might ſtand in need of a right or favourable Interpretation. So, that you ſee, it muſt needs be very unjuſtly objected againſt this Expoſition, that the ſame is altogether beg'd or precarious, when indeed we find it built upon ſo many very good grounds of Reaſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>2ly.</hi> Whereas, it has been objected, that the ſeveral Acts of <hi>Naaman</hi> and of his Maſter, in the Houſe of <hi>Rimmon,</hi> being both expreſs'd in the Original, not differently, but by one and the ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame word, why ſhould we not therefore underſtand them alſo to have been of the ſame Nature, and done by both of them, out of the ſame deſign of Religious Worſhip? To this I Anſwer, that tho' it cannot be denyed, that the ſame <hi>Hebrew</hi> word is here uſed in, or for the Worſhip of the one, as well as for that of the other alſo, and muſt therefore imply the like external Geſtures of Body, to have been there uſed by them both; yet we can by no means from thence infer any neceſſity of underſtanding the Actions of theſe two Perſons, to be of the ſame kind alſo and nature, in reſpect of the deſign and intention of Mind, with which they were performed; which yet is always the chief thing to be conſidered, as that which creates a wide difference between Acts, which might otherwiſe be thought the ſame, if judged of only according to outward appearance.</p>
               <p>In ſhort, the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> does ſtrictly and properly import not more, than a bare Bending, or Bowing down of the Body, or a Proſtration thereof upon the Ground, with ſtretch'd our Hands and Feet, without ſignifying any thing at all of the particular end or deſign of ſuch bodily Geſtures; but leaving that wholly to be made out, and collected from the Genius and Nature of the particular Place of Scripture, wherein we find the word us'd, or from other Circumſtances of the Context.</p>
               <p>And accordingly, becauſe by ſuch outward Incurvation, or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Body, 'twas Cuſtomary, among thoſe of the <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern</hi> Countries, to ſignifie and expreſs their inward Affection of Mind, that profound Honour and Veneration which they had, as well for their Princes and other great Perſons, as alſo for their Idols and ſuppoſed Gods; therefore the ſame word which properly ſignifies only ſuch Bodily Incurvation in the general, is alſo uſed in Scripture to denote, ſometimes the Acts of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:45693:13"/>
Worſhip, and ſometimes a civil Act of Honour and Reſpect done unto Superiours. So that in this place likewiſe, it being very evident, from the circumſtances of the Context, that the Bowing of the King of <hi>Syria,</hi> and <hi>Naamans</hi> Bowing in the Houſe of <hi>Rimmon,</hi> were accompanied with ſo very different Intentions, the firſt plainly deſigning thereby the Worſhip of his Idol, whilſt the other (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his own expreſs Declaration) could mean no more; than a civil-Reſpect to his Maſter; there is therefore very good Reaſon, that tho' the ſame word be here apply'd to both, we ſhould yet not underſtand it in the ſame Senſe; eſpecially, ſince it does frequently in other Places (and will here) ſo fairly and naturally admit of a different Acceptation.</p>
               <p>And accordingly we may obſerve, that our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, does very judiciouſly, and upon good Grounds, make a different rendring of the ſame <hi>Hebrew</hi> word; whilſt it calls the Kings Act, his <hi>Worſhiping,</hi> but <hi>Naamans</hi> only his <hi>Bowing down himſelf;</hi> plainly intimating thereby, the different Nature of the Acts, from the quite different Intentions therein.</p>
               <p>But ſtill, <hi>3dly.</hi> Others again, conſidering how expreſsly, and without any manner of limitation, or exception of Intention, the <hi>Jews</hi> were forbidden, as a thing unlawful, upon any account or pretence whatſoever, to Bow down themſelves before an Idol, tho' they ſhould at the ſame time declare, that they meant no Worſhip to it, but of God only; or deſign'd by that Geſture, ſome other civil Reſpect; have therefore from thence conclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that <hi>Naaman</hi> being now of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Religion, muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently commit a great Sin, even in going ſo far as he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd, and in that he would Bow down himſelf in a Place where an Idol was, tho' he deſign'd no Worſhip to that thereby, but meerly a civil Reſpect to his Maſter.</p>
               <p>But now this Scruple or Objection, being founded upon a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, or falſe Suppoſition, will therefore eaſily be removed, when we ſhall conſider, that this Precept, as well as ſeveral others, was peculiarly deſigned for the <hi>Iſraelitiſh</hi> People, and given only to the natural <hi>Jews,</hi> while Proſelytes of another Country, (as was this <hi>Syrian)</hi> were not neceſſarily obliged thereby. For o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe we muſt alſo conclude, that <hi>Naaman</hi> ſinned no leſs, in making uſe of the two Mules-burden of Earth, for the purpoſe he deſigned: Since the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> People were expreſsly forbidden, the Erecting of any Altar, or Offering of Sacrifice, in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Place, than in the Temple of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> only, as we find Deut. 12. 13. 14. <hi>Tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> heed to thy ſelf, that thou Offer not thy Burnt-offerings in every Place that thou ſeest, but in the Place which the Lord ſhall chuſe in one of thy Tribes; there thou ſhalt Offer thy Burnt-offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and there thou ſhalt do all that I Command thee.</hi> And ſo <hi>Lev.</hi> 17. 3, 4. <hi>What Man ſoever there be of the Houſe of Iſrael, that killeth</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:45693:13"/>
                  <hi>an Ox, or a Lamb, or Goat in the Camp, or that killeth it out of the Camp, and bringeth it not unto the Door of the Tabernacle of the Congregation, to offer an Offering unto the Lord, before the Tabernacle of the Lord; Blood ſhall be imputed unto that Man, he hath ſhed Blood, and that Man ſhall be cut off from among his People.</hi> But now the Caſe was quite otherwiſe with the Proſelites of another Country, as <hi>Naaman</hi> was; who therefore eaſily obtains Licence, for the Non-obſervance of theſe two particular Prohibitions, which were given with a peculiar reſpect to the natural <hi>Jews</hi> only, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver deſigned indiſpenſably to oblige other Perſons alſo under ſo different Circumſtances.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, It may, perhaps, be farther Objected, (and this indeed is now the only remaining Difficulty I am ſenſible of) That Pardon being nothing elſe but a Diſcharge from the Obligation to Puniſhment, and all Puniſhment ſuppoſing ſome Sin, all For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs, properly ſo called, muſt needs involve under the very Notion of it, the plain ſuppoſition of ſome foregoing Fault or Offence, and conſequently, that <hi>Naamans</hi> Bowing muſt needs be ſinful, at leaſt in his Apprehenſion; ſince otherwiſe he would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver (as we find he does) talk of Pardon for the ſame.</p>
               <p>To which I Anſwer, That tho' all this would be very true and concluſive, if the preſent Queſtion were concerning Actions already done, in which alone, Pardon properly ſo called, can take Place; yet for a Man to ask, or for God to Promiſe this Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour before hand, with reſpect to an Action not yet done, (as according to the preſent Caſe ſuppoſed) would not be ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly a begging or granting of Pardon, in the ſtrict Senſe, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a begging or granting of free Licence to do the thing, or an Aſſurance of the Man, that he may do it, without any Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to God. And indeed, the Original Word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> here uſed, and which we here Tranſlate, <hi>Pardon,</hi> is ſo far from always ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding this more laxe Senſe, that we may find it neceſſarily requiring the ſame in ſeveral other places of Scripture. Thus we read, Num. 30. 3, &amp; 5. <hi>If a woman vow a Vow unto the Lord, and bind her ſelf by a Bond, being in her Fathers Houſe in her Youth; and her Father diſallow her, in the Day that he heareth thereof, then not any of her Vows, or of her Bonds, wherewith ſhe hath bound her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſhall ſtand: And the Lord ſhall</hi> FORGIVE <hi>her, becauſe her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſallow'd her.</hi> The Lord ſhall <hi>Forgive</hi> her, that is, ſhall not be at all Offended at her, nor count it any Sin in her, but hold her perfectly Innocent in this matter, for not keeping that Vow, which could not be ratify'd, or oblige her, without her Fathers Conſent, or in contradiction to the Duty which ſhe ought to ſo near a Relation, who could juſtly challenge ſo great an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority over her. And in the <hi>12th.</hi> Verſe likewiſe of the ſame Chapter, we find the ſame Phraſe uſed in the ſame Senſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:45693:14"/>
the Wiſe, in the like Caſe, with relation to her Husband. And ſo when in a caſe of neceſſity, the People could not cleanſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as 'twas requiſite they ſhould have done, before they eat the Paſſover, we find <hi>Hezekiah</hi> Praying for them after this manner. <hi>The good Lord pardon every one that prepareth his Heart to ſeek the Lord.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Chr. 3. 18, 19.</note> 
                  <hi>tho' he be not cleanſed according to the Purification of the Sanctuary.</hi> And ſo the ſame Word here uſed in this very Caſe, may beſt be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood in the ſame Senſe, not ſo much for <hi>Pardon,</hi> in the ſtrict Senſe of a known Fault, as for the favourable Interpretation of a doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Action: And <hi>The Lord Pardon thy Servant,</hi> ſeems here to be no more than if he had ſaid, <hi>Let not the Lord be offended at me,</hi> or <hi>I hope the Lord will not take it amiſs, or look upon it as any Sin in me, but hold me Innocent, and take it in good part, if I do happen to bow my ſelf in the Houſe of</hi> Rimmon, <hi>upon that particular occaſion only, and declar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my Intention therein, to be no other than ſuch as I have now acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you with.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereas, on the contrary, had he concluded the ſame to have been a Sin, he muſt alſo have concluded, that God muſt needs have been highly offended at him for it; nor could he then have entertained the leaſt hope that ever the Prophet would have given him leave to venture on it. Thus, having beſtowed more time and pains than ordinary, tho' I think, (conſidering how much it has been abuſed and made the common Refuge of Diſſemblers) not more than was requiſite, in propoſing and endeavouring to eſtabliſh the right Expoſition of this place of Scripture, as well as in removing the ſeveral Difficulties and Objections that have been made againſt it. I proceed now to the next general thing deſigned, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſhew,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>That ſuppoſing that which ſome contend for, were indeed the true and genuine Senſe of this Place; yet from this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, we Chriſtians could have no ſufficient Reaſon to preſume of an Allowance for any ſuch Diſſimulation or Compliance; and much leſs have we now any Reaſon, ſo to preſume from this Example rightly underſtood, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered (as it ought to be) under all its ſeveral Circumſtances.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>WHereas we are moſt aſſured that God is a God of Truth, to whom all lying and diſſembling is moſt abominable; Whereas we likewiſe know, that he alone created the whole Man, and does therefore naturally challenge, and can be contented with nothing leſs than the entire Service and Worſhip of our Bodies, as
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:45693:14"/>
well as of our Souls, and that he has profeſſed, he will not give his Honour to another; whereas alſo we are moſt certain, that ſome things are ſo naturally and eternally Evil and Indecent, that no po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Command or Prohibition whatſoever, can alter their Nature, or make them otherwiſe<hi>:</hi> Were it now notwithſtanding all this, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any way conſiſtent with the eternal and unalterable Nature of Good and Evil, or reconcilable to the eſſential and immutable Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the Divine Nature, that we ſhould think it poſſible, for God to allow any thing of Hypocriſy, or to give a Licence to diſſemble, and that in a Man's Religion too; nay ſtill farther, ſuppoſe that from my Text it could be moſt evidently demonſtrat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, (as the quite contrary, I hope, has been ſo) that God did once ſince the Creation of the World, think fit, (for ſome moſt extraordinary Reaſons, known only to himſelf) actually to give leave to one certain Perſon, <hi>viz.</hi> to this <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Syrian,</hi> ſo to diſſemble his Religion, by joining with his Body in Idolatry, whilſt with his Soul he Worſhiped the true God only; yet when all is done, ſuch ſingular Licence could not in any Reaſon have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrued to extend any farther, or to effect any other, than the very particular Perſon only, to whom it was ſuppoſed ſo expreſly given. Nor could we with any ſafety have from thence concluded, that it was lawful for any other beſides, much leſs for any Chriſtian ſo to diſſemble. For we find the Scripture every where full of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny plain Commands to the contrary, as well as of Examples of thoſe who are there highly commended, for chuſing to die rather than ſo comply. Nor can we in the whole Book of God find any one Example of the other ſort (beſides this of <hi>Naaman</hi> under our preſent diſpute) but what is there branded with ſome evident note of Infamy and Condemnation. So that it would by no means follow, that it is lawful for any other likewiſe upon occaſion, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble his Religion, tho' it could be evidently proved, that <hi>Naa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> had expreſs leave from God ſo to do: And how is it poſſible then that we ſhould now make any ſuch Inference from this Example, when it is on the contrary moſt clear, that even <hi>Naaman</hi> himſelf nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther asked nor received, nor ever ſo much as thought of having any leave or Indulgence to practiſe any ſuch Matter, but what was really of a much different Nature.</p>
               <p>And indeed, whoſoever ſhall firſt well conſider the true nature of this particular Fact, together with the true State and ſeveral Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the Perſon, and then diligently compare all theſe with the Fact, State and Circumſtances of thoſe other Perſons, who endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to abuſe this Example to their own vile Purpoſes, will eaſily diſcover ſuch a wide difference and vaſt diſproportion between them in all theſe reſpects, that almoſt any two of the moſt contrary things you can think of, may aſſoon be reconciled together, as any thing of this Precedent can be made ſerviceable towards the Countenanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:45693:15"/>
ſuch Hypocritical Chriſtians, who at any time ſhall baſely reſolve to ſerve the Times, by outwardly communicating with Idolaters, or bodily joining in the Acts of any falſe or unlawful Worſhip.</p>
               <p>For <hi>1ſt.</hi> If we conſider the Nature of the Fact it ſelf, I have already proved, that what <hi>Naaman</hi> here deſigned, was not any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, but a meer civil Act, done not out of any the leaſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to the Idol, but reſpect to his Maſter only, and in diſcharge of that particular Court-Office, which if he ſtill held it, would neceſſarily require thus much from him, done not out of any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to diſguiſe or diſſemble his Religion, nor with the leaſt inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or poſſibility thereby of deceiving any other Perſon, or of being thought to be ſtill what he was not; but accompany'd with the moſt publick Profeſſion, and plain Declaration of his being a Worſhipper of the living God only, and of his utter Abhorrence and Deteſtation or <hi>Rimmon,</hi> and all other Idols whatſoever. And this Declaration likewiſe to be ſeconded, and made good by the conſtant courſe of his other ſuitable Actions and Behaviour, in openly pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to, Worſhiping, and Sacrificing to the true God only, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Rites of the <hi>Iſraelitiſh</hi> People. From whence we may alſo farther conclude, that neither did he deſire to continue this civil Act, out of any covetous or ambitious Temper, that he was extremely fond of retaining his high Station, or poſſeſſed with any cowardly fear of Death in ſo good a Cauſe; ſince by what he was reſolved upon otherways, both to ſay and do, he could not but fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee, that he muſt needs very much hazard the loſs both of his Riches, Preferment, and Life it ſelf, in caſe ſo abſolute a Prince as was his Maſter the King of <hi>Syria,</hi> ſhould happen, (as 'twas moſt likely) to be offended thereat: But only on the other Hand, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing that if in conſideration of his former eminent Loyalty and good Services, as well as in a Senſe of the great need he ſhould ſtill have of him, it ſhould ſo fall out, (as 'twas alſo poſſible) that his Maſter ſtill retained ſuch an extraordinary Favour for him, as to be willing both to bear with his Exerciſe and Profeſſion of a contrary Religion, and to continue him in the ſame Civil Poſt: then <hi>Naaman</hi> alſo would think fit, in point of Prudence, not voluntarily to foreſake the ſame, or put himſelf out of place by refuſing to bow down himſelf, as it required only in that one Caſe already ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; if indeed that action were to be looked upon, as only of an indifferent Nature, and ſuch as could be performed by him, (as he hoped it might) with a ſafe Conſcience.</p>
               <p>And yet after all, we are alſo to conſider, that he durſt not rely upon his own Judgment, or venture upon this doubtful Action, merely of his own Head, without a cautions conſultation of God's Mind herein for his full Satisfaction, or before ſuch time as he had firſt received an expreſs Licence from him by the Mouth of the Prophet; being otherways reſolved and prepared, (as we have
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:45693:15"/>
good Reaſon to conclude) utterly to have quitted both his Place, and together with that, all farther Intereſt in his Maſters Favour, in caſe <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſhould have determined his Queſtion in the Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</p>
               <p>But now, I pray, what manner of Kindred, or Analogie is there between this Fact of <hi>Naaman,</hi> and that of thoſe, who can af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford outwardly to joyn themſelves in ſuch acknowledgly Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Acts, and to communicate in ſuch Sinful, Superſtitious, or Adolatrous Rites of Worſhip, as they do at the ſame time in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly abhor? And this too, not only without declaring their Deteſtation thereof, to thoſe to whom it chiefly concerns them to make ſuch Declaration; but out of an intent to conceal from them, ſuch their Abhorrence, and on purpoſe that they may thereby be thought to approve of their Religion; prompted thereto only by the carnal Motives of vile Covetouſneſs and Ambition, and exceſſive Love of the World, or at leaſt, only to avoid ſome temporal Inconvenience, or that they may keep themſelves in a whole Skin: And all this, not only without all colour of any ſpecial Indulgence from God for their ſo doing, but in manifeſt oppoſition to, and perfect Contempt, of his moſt expreſs and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently repeated Commands to the contrary?</p>
               <p>But ſtill again, if at preſent any devout Chriſtian of the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Form, and more Zealouſly tender of the divine Honour, ſhould be apt to Object it, as a thing ſomewhat ſtrange and leſs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable, either that <hi>Naaman,</hi> now convinc'd of his former Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, ſhould deſire, (or that God ſhould grant him) an Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in a matter of this Nature; which, howſoever it muſt be acknowledged Lawful, can yet hardly be denyed leſs expedient, as being a thing looking ill, and having in it, at leaſt, the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of Evil, as well as that which muſt needs make him more ſubject to the continual Temptation, and hazards of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſe, that he ſhould be ſtill ſo frequently appearing in an Idols Temple, and there uſing the ſame outward Geſtures with his Idolatrous Country-men, tho' upon ſo different account: To this I Anſwer, That tho' I doubt not, but that it would have been both more ſafe and generous for <hi>Naaman</hi> without any more adoe, to have quitted both his Place and Maſter, and to have reſolved for ever after, to become an Inhabitant of the Land, as well as a Profeſſor of the Religion of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> yet there are ſeveral good Reaſons to be given, both why it could not well be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected otherwiſe, than that <hi>Naaman,</hi> ſhould deſire to do as he did, and why God alſo ſhould think fit, ſo to gratifie him in his Deſire, if we do but conſider the particular State he was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and the ſeveral Circumſtances of his Perſon. The great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of all which may ſerve alſo, in ſome good Meaſure, to ſatisfie us, why God will not now, under the State of Chriſtianity,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:45693:16"/>
allow any of us to go ſo far as the bare Imitation of his Action, and much leſs grant any ſuch extravagant Licence of down-right complyance with Idolaters, as ſome Hypocrites have moſt unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably endeavoured to infer therefrom.</p>
               <p>And firſt then, we may conſider what <hi>Naaman</hi> had been, and was ſtill in his own Country, <hi>viz.</hi> A moſt Renowned Prince, mighty in Valour, and one through whom God had given De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance unto <hi>Syria,</hi> as we find all this in the firſt Verſe of this Chapter. In ſhort, he was a Perſon, whoſe great Merits had juſtly Advanc'd him to the higheſt Degree of Honour and Truſt with the King his Maſter, and given him no ordinary ſhare in his Friendſhip and Affections, as may eaſily be collected (had we no other Evidence thereof) from the extreme Sollicitude and Concern he ſhews, for the Cure of his Leproſie.</p>
               <p>But now, if after this double Cure wrought upon him, <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aman</hi> ſhould have choſen to return no more home, but ever after, of his own accord, have perfectly deſerted the Service of his King and Country, this muſt needs have look'd in him, both as ungrateful and ſuſpicious, and would have been apt to caſt a very prejudicial and ſcandalous Reflection upon the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Religion it ſelf; as if a Man could no ſooner become a Proſelyte thereto, but he muſt preſently forget all his former Duty and Allegiance, and ceaſe to be any longer an uſeful Subject to his own natural Prince. Beſides, he could not but conſider, that, as he was bound in Nature, ſtill ſo more ſtrictly, by the Duties of his new Religion, not to expoſe his Wife and numerous Family which he had left behind him, to ſuch eminent Danger, but to take a due Care of their Safety and Welfare, and more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to endeavour their Converſion alſo. And 'twas fit for him likewiſe to try the Experiment however, whether the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued Miracle, which he ſhould carry home with him, in his ſo wonderfully reſtored Health, both of Body and Mind, joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the good Example, and diſcreet Suggeſtions, which the opportunity of a familiar Converſe would afford, might not by degrees, prove at laſt forcible enough, to prevail upon the King himſelf likewiſe, to approve of, and embrace the ſame Religion. Nor did he know, but that God might be pleas'd, through his means, to give ſtill a far greater <hi>Deliverance unto Syria,</hi> than e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he had done before, tho' of a quite different, and far more excellent Nature.</p>
               <p>Theſe now, or the like Conſiderations, might ſomewhat ſerve to counter-poiſe thoſe other Inconveniencies, and that Perſonal hazard of a Relapſe, which he might incur by his return back. But however, 'tis natural for Men to have ſo great a Love for their own Country, eſpecially when they happen to make ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conſiderable a Figure there, as did this <hi>Syrian</hi> Prince, that we
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:45693:16"/>
cannot eaſily blame one under his Circumſtances, for ſo deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining as he did. For it was no ſmall Tryal of the Faith of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the Father of the Faithful, that he could, when he had an expreſs Command for it from God, ſo readily obey, in forſaking his own Country and his Father's Houſe, to ſojourn in a ſtrange Land; how could it be then expected, that ſo young a Proſelite as <hi>Naaman,</hi> ſhould find in his Heart, to do the like, and much more of his own accord, and without any Command at all for his ſo doing?</p>
               <p>Nor will it appear ſtrange, either that being reſolved to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, he ſhould alſo deſire, (if he lawfully could) ſtill to retain the ſame Grandeur and high Station, and all the Advantages at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending it, by obtaining leave ſo to Bow in the Houſe of <hi>Rim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon;</hi> nor yet ſo ſtrange, that God ſhould think fit to grant his Petition, if we do but farther Conſider theſe following Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>1ſt.</hi> We may Conſider, That even the natural <hi>Jews</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, were under ſuch a State or Diſpenſation, wherein they were chiefly moved to Obedience, by the Hopes and Promiſes of temporal Rewards and Advantages, and by the Fears and Threatnings, of temporal Evils and Inconveniencies; whilſt both the Doctrine of Eternal Happineſs, or Miſery in a Future State after Death, and the Evidences to ſupport their Belief, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Reality of the ſame, were (comparatively) but ſparing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and covertly, and far more obſcurely delivered to them. And conſequently, it was allowable in them, to ſet a higher va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue and eſteem upon the World, and outward Proſperity there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, than it is now either Lawful, or Reaſonable for them to do, to whom Life and Immortality are brought to light by the Goſpel, and who Live under the great Advantage of far more clear Diſcoveries and Demonſtrations, both of the Certainty and particular Nature of ſuch a future State. Nor was it reaſonable to expect from <hi>Naaman</hi> any more (at moſt) than from a <hi>Jew;</hi> nor (to be ſure) near ſo much, as is now highly neceſſary in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Chriſtian, who are juſtly required to be endued with a more Heroick kind of Spirit, and ſuch Self-denyal, and generous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the World, as may enable them, upon the like occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, readily to part with any of its moſt ſpecious and valuable Trifles, rather than do any thing, in order to ſecure the ſame, that may give juſt Offence to their Brethren, by having in it ſo much of the appearance of Evil.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>2dly.</hi> We may alſo Conſider, that <hi>Naaman</hi> was no natural <hi>Jew,</hi> but only a Proſelyte of another Nation, who therefore, as ſuch, has a Liberty granted him, for the Non-obſervance of one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Prohibition, which (as I have above obſerved) had always a more particular relation to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> People, and was never
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:45693:17"/>
ſo indiſpenſably deſigned to oblige Aliens. Whereas, had he been a natural <hi>Jew,</hi> he could neither have reaſonably expected, nor would (in all probability) have ever obtain'd the like Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>3dly.</hi> 'Tis alſo farther to be Conſidered, That he was but juſt now become a Proſelyte, and it might be upon that account convenient, at the very firſt to allow ſomething to the natural Weakneſs and Infirmity of a meer Beginner, rather than hazard the diſcouragement of ſo hopeful a Candidate, by the denyal of him in one particular only, which as it was not ſinful in its own Nature, but ſuch as he might Practiſe with retention of his Sincerity, ſo was it alſo of no ſmall Conſequence, as to his World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerns, and could not therefore be amiſs, that he ſhould be therein indulged, till ſuch time however, as his own greater Zeal for, and further Confirmation in the true Religion, added to the opportunity of his making proper Applications to his Maſter, might at laſt procure him a Diſpenſation, not only for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture omiſſion of that particular Ceremony, and civil Service to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Prince, but for his total Abſence alſo from the Idols Temple.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> This Circumſtance is by no means to be forgotten, that ſuch was his particular Country, wherein all Perſons generally being already Idolaters, he could not therefore, by going ſo far as he did, create any occaſion of Offence to any among thoſe, where all would be ſure much rather to be offended at him, for going no farther: Nor yet could he on the other hand, by this civil Action, (ſufficiently declared and underſtood by all, upon what Account it was performed) any ways contribute to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the farther Confirmation of any in their Superſtition and falſe Worſhip.</p>
               <p>But now, by what new Art of reconciling Contradictions, ſhall we ever be able, to make all this agreeable to the Caſe of thoſe, who by their Profeſſion are not <hi>Jews</hi> but <hi>Chriſtians?</hi> Nor yet ſuch as are newly brought over to the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Faith, but Baptized therein long ſince, brought up from their Youth, under all the means and advantages of a thorow Inſtruction, and full Confirmation therein: And, who Living likewiſe in a Country, where very many are ſure to be highly Scandaliz'd at ſuch Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, as well as others Confirmed thereby in their Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, do notwithſtanding venture, in deſpight of Conſcience, and contempt of the plaineſt Prohibitions, to joyn with others in ſuch Acts of Worſhip, as they verily believe to be Idolatrous or ſinful. With what Face can ſuch Wretches plead this Scripture for their Excuſe? Whereas, you ſee, that nothing either of the matters of Fact, or of the State and Circumſtances of the Perſons are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t all agreeable.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:45693:17"/>
And indeed, when all is done, ſuch kind of Perſons ſeem to make uſe of this Expedient, and love to be continually talking of <hi>Naaman</hi>'s Caſe, merely out of a deſign to amuſe and ſtop the Mouths of leſs intelligent Chriſtians, who are naturally apt to upbraid them for their Levity and Diſſimulation, that ſo they may be able with more quiet and leſs diſgrace of the World, to purſue their ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar ends, by the means of ſuch baſe Compliances, rather than that they are themſelves in good earneſt ſatisfied, that there is any real Countenance for them from any thing of this Example, or that they are truly and heartily at all ſollicitous, or concern'd about what is lawful or unlawful for them. Nothing more uſual with the Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite, than to think he Sins with Credit, when he can Sin with Scripture in his Mouth, and force his Excuſe even from that from whence he will find his Condemnation. And indeed of all deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate Offenders, none's like him, who when he has done a wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thing, endeavours to avoid the Odium thereof, and the juſt Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of others, by preſently ſculking himſelf behind ſome Text for his ſecurity; where, at the ſame time he ſecretly laughs at his own Impudence, and the Simplicity of thoſe who can thereby be ſo eaſily put off and ſatisfied.</p>
               <p>But however, as well for an Antidote againſt the ſpreading Poiſon and Infection of ſuch Mens moſt falſe and dangerous Suggeſtions, as alſo for the more abundant conviction and ſatisfaction of all Sincere and Well meaning Perſons, I ſhall next proceed to my laſt general Propoſal, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not only by Arguments drawn from Hiſtory and matter of Fact, but alſo by direct poſitive places of Scripture, as well as from the eternal Reaſons and unalterable Nature of things themſelves, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate, That ſuch Compliances or Diſſimulations muſt needs be always highly unlawful, and a Crime ſo hainous, that nothing can excuſe that Chriſtian who deliberately joins, or knowingly only ſeems to join with others in ſuch a Worſhip or Service, as he is ſufficiently convinced to be falſe, or in any part thereof Sinful or Idolatrous.</p>
               <p>For the more Methodical performance of which Task, I ſhall in the firſt Place conſider</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:45693:18"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Who, and what kind of Perſons they were, that firſt Taught and Practiſed ſuch horrid Diſſimulation in matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and upon what Pretences.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>AND indeed had Men but half that Jealouſie and tender con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern for the good of the Soul, as generally they have for that of the Body, and the periſhing Trifles that belong to it, this ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle Conſideration then, without any more ado, might prove a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Antidote againſt this deadly Poiſon; nor would there need, almoſt, any other Confutation of ſuch pernicious Doctrines, than the bare diſcovery and true Character of the chief Authors and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moters thereof, whom we ſhall find all along to have been no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſtill, than either ſome of the moſt vile and infamous among all the impure Sties of accurſed Hereticks, or elſe ſome main Ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaders in the damnable Society of ſuch Perſons, (for <hi>Men</hi> I know not how to call them, nor yet <hi>Devils)</hi> who have arrived to ſuch a monſtrous height of more than Diabolical Impudence and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety, as to make a Mock at that ſacred Being, which Devils themſelves both believe and tremble at.</p>
               <p>Among thoſe who have been called Chriſtians, he who firſt invented and ſet on foot this curſed Engine of Diſſimulation, ſo deſtructive to Chriſtianity, was a Perſon whoſe very Name carries in it the black Myſteries of Hell, and who came withal from a Country ſo fruitful in ſuch kind of Monſters, that our Saviour himſelf has given them this Character, <hi>That they Worſhiped they knew not what.</hi> After this, I ſuppoſe, I can ſcarce need to tell you, that I mean no other than the wicked <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> or <hi>Simon</hi> the <hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerer,</hi> who (tho' it had been better for him never to have been Born) had <hi>Samaria</hi> for the unhappy Place of his Nativity. No ſooner ſcarce had this Wretch been Baptiſed, hut preſently he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haved, himſelf ſo very unſuitable to his Profeſſion, that St. <hi>Peter,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> c. 8.</note> even ſo early, ſeems to queſtion whether or no he had not already ſinned himſelf beyond Forgiveneſs; and concludes <hi>him to be in the Gall of Bitterneſs, and in the bond of Iniquity.</hi> But afterwards he grew
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:45693:18"/>
ſtill far worſe and worſe, and became at laſt the very Maſter-piece of Satan, and the firſt great Father of almoſt all other Hereticks. Upon which account that glorious Martyr and Diſciple of St. <hi>John, Ignatius,</hi> in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Trallians,</hi> ſticks not to call him, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>The firſt begotten Son of the Devil.</hi> And indeed in this one Engine of his, did the Prince of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſeem to have repoſed ſo great a Confidence, as if he had been in hopes to have ſtifled Chriſtianity in its Infancy, by raiſing up one <hi>Simon</hi> to defeat the other, and to have made this latter no leſs a <hi>Peter</hi> too, or Rock, whereon the Church of Chriſt, inſtead of being built, might ſuffer Shipwrack. I ſhall not need to relate, and indeed Chriſtian Ears would by no means bear the hearing of thoſe many other monſtrous Impurities, which this Arch-Heretick both taught and practiſed. But of all his other moſt deteſtable Impieties, there's none ſeems of more pernicious Conſequence at once to the very Deſign and Genius of the Goſpel, and to all the Articles of our Chriſtian Belief; none ſtrikes more immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately at the very preſent Life and Being, as well as at the future Propagation of Chriſtianity, than that curſed Liberty of his, which he (for ought I know, of all Men firſt) ſo freely Grants to his Diſciples, not only to Diſſemble, but even to deny (in whole or in part) the Faith upon occaſion. We do not find that the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans ever went about to force the Chriſtians to Sacrifice, or created them any Publick Diſturbance upon their refuſal ſo to do, till ſome time under the Reign of <hi>Nero.</hi> Before which therefore there could be no neceſſity, nor indeed occaſion to make any ſuch publick Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion againſt Perſecution, by the inventing of a Doctrine ſo na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally diſhonourable and contrary to the common Sentiments of Mankind, that I am perſwaded it could never otherwiſe have once entred into the Thoughts of any one, no, not even of this vile Miſcreant himſelf, had it not been upon the Emergency of ſome ſuch urgent occaſion: Nothing elſe but the Temptation of ſuch Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, could be the Riſe or Original of ſo ſhameful a Contrivance. When <hi>Nero</hi> therefore began to Perſecute Chriſtians, at the ſame time, we may ſuppoſe, began <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> who was then at <hi>Rome,</hi> to contrive how he might beſt ſecure his Diſciples from forſaking him upon that Occaſion. In order to which, he taught them open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to deny the Faith, and if need ſhould be, to Worſhip Idols alſo. For thus much <hi>Origen</hi> in his Book againſt <hi>Celſus,</hi> does after this manner Teſtifie concerning him; <hi>That tho'</hi> Simon <hi>deceived many, yet from Death and Capital Puniſhment, which other Chriſtians ſo freely underwent, for the ſake of their Religion, he took care to reſcue every one of his Followers, by teaching them to carry themſelves indifferently as to the Worſhip of Idols.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:45693:19"/>
Among the other nameleſs Multitude of deluded Wretches, who followed this grand Deceiver, St. <hi>Irenaeus</hi> has given us a particular Catalogue of ſome of his more chief Diſciples, in thoſe black Names of <hi>Menander, Saturninus, Baſilides, Carpocrates, Cerinthus, Ebion, Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholaus, Cerdon,</hi> and <hi>Marcion,</hi> who all, not only themſelves, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced and followed, but alſo, ſetting up for Maſters of Sects, moſt induſtriouſly propagated among others all the ſame pernicious Errours, and that too in particular under our preſent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſeb.</hi> Hiſt. <hi>l.</hi> 4. c. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Euſebius</hi> expreſly tells us of <hi>Baſilides, That he taught it to be a matter of Indifference, not only to eat of the Sacrifices offered unto Idols, but alſo boldly to deny, and even forſwear the Faith in time of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution.</hi> The ſame <hi>Euſebius</hi> likewiſe informs us concerning <hi>Elxai,</hi> who had been a chief Leader of the Sect of the <hi>Oſſens,</hi> and at laſt joined himſelf to the Party of <hi>Ebion,</hi> that he not only delivered the ſame Doctrine to his Diſciples, but furniſhed them alſo with theſe doughty Arguments, to maintain the ſame: For, ſaith he, <hi>The</hi> Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſaitae <hi>affirm, That it is therefore no Sin at all to deny Chriſt in the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſeb.</hi> l. 6. c. 28.</note> 
                  <hi>time of Perſecution, becauſe he who is fixed in his Heart, tho' he denies him with his Mouth, in a Caſe of Neceſſity, does yet with his Heart con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue ſteadfaſt in the Faith. Upon which account</hi> (they ſay) <hi>that ſuch a one, ſo denying with his Mouth, is guilty of no Sin; ſince God regards the Heart much rather than the Tongue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall not now go about to conſute or diſcover the Fallaſie or Weakneſs of theſe pretended Reaſons; but reſerving this Task to a more proper Place, proceed rather to ſhew how juſtly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous and deteſted the Heads of this curſed Sect were in the Judgment of the true Doctors and main Pillars of the Chriſtian Church. When that eminent Martyr and Biſhop of <hi>Smyma,</hi> the renowned <hi>Polycarp,</hi> who had alſo been a Diſciple of St. <hi>John,</hi> hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, being then at <hi>Rome,</hi> to meet with the Heretick <hi>Marcion,</hi> and was ask'd by him after a ſawning manner, whether or no he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged him? His Anſwer was, (like that of <hi>Ignatius</hi> to <hi>Simon) I acknowledge thee,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>to be the Firſt-born of Satan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cerinthus,</hi> (as <hi>Epiphanius</hi> affirms) was one of thoſe who murmured againſt St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and reſiſted him for going in to <hi>Cornelius</hi> a Perſon uncircumciſed; tho' expreſly commanded to do ſo from Heaven. And both <hi>Irenaeus</hi> and <hi>Euſebius</hi> relate concerning St. <hi>John</hi> himſelf, that when he was going to bath himſelf, and had heard that <hi>Cerinthus</hi> was there, preſently he cried out, <hi>let us be gone hence, leaſt we periſh with him.</hi> And tho' <hi>Epiphanius</hi> particularly applies this to <hi>Ebion,</hi> yet both theſe Authors may be well enough conſiſtent in this Matter, ſince both thoſe Hereticks might probabily be at that time there together, who were obſerved to have been very ſeldom or never a ſunder. Nor is it at all to be wondred at, that thoſe Peſts of Chriſtianity ſhould be ſo abominable to the true Apoſtles and Apoſtolical Men, ſince by the other enormities of their Behaviour, as well as by their
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:45693:19"/>
joining indifferently upon occaſion in all ſorts of Religions, they had rendred the Chriſtian Name it ſelf ſo odious in the ſight of many of the very Heathen, who happening to be leſs acquainted with the true nature of it, ſtood perfectly aſtoniſhed at the unaccountable Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of theſe Men. For according to their Doctrine, ſo likewiſe was the Converſation and Behaviour of all theſe <hi>Gnoſtick</hi> Sects in general; who ſcrupled not in the leaſt, to Communicate in Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip either with Chriſtians, Jews, or Pagans, nor to ſay or do, to profeſs or deny any thing, in order to their Carcaſs preſervation, and that they might keep themſelves in a whole Skin. Upon this very occaſion, perhaps <hi>Flavius Vopiſcus,</hi> in the Life of <hi>Saturninus,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth out of the Hiſtory of <hi>Phlegon,</hi> an entire Epiſtle of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Adrian</hi> to <hi>Servianus</hi> the Conful; in which, ſpeaking of the wonderful Inconſtancy of ſome Chriſtians, he affirms of them, <hi>That ſometimes they uſed to Worſhip</hi> Serapis, <hi>with the</hi> Egyptians, <hi>ſometimes Chriſt, and ſometimes one God with the</hi> Jews, <hi>and ſometimes with the</hi> Gentiles, Where (in the Opinion of <hi>Baronius)</hi> we are to take it for certain, that this is to be underſtood of thoſe Heretical Chriſtians who were of the School of <hi>Baſilides</hi> and <hi>Carpocrates,</hi> who were both <hi>Alexandrians,</hi> and there opening the School of all Impurities, were notorious for being neither firm nor conſtant in the Confeſſion of Chriſts Name, and for teaching their Followers, that they might, without any blame, deny him, and Worſhip the Gods of the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> Concerning the <hi>Valentinians</hi> alſo, who aſſociated themſelves to the <hi>Gnoſticks, Irenaeus</hi> and <hi>Tertullian</hi> thus informs us; <hi>That they held there was no Neceſſity of openly Confeſſing Chriſt, nor of ſuffering Martyrdom for the Chriſtian Religion; that they did eat of Meat offered to Idols, as a thing indifferent, not thinking themſelves to be at all polluted by ſo doing, or by any other Pagan Compliances, when there was occaſion. That they uſed upon the ſame account to revile the Orthodox Chriſtians, becauſe they made Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of ſuch Matters, as mere Idiots and ſimple Perſons who underſtood nothing; vaunting of themſelves in the mean time, as the only knowing and perfect ones, and Veſſels of Election.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And when this firſt Set of Diabolical Apoſtles were themſelves in time extinguiſhed, their deſtructive Principle for ſome Ages after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſtill ſurvived in their Impious Succeſſors. For <hi>Priſcillian</hi> under the Reign of the Emperours <hi>Gratian</hi> and <hi>Valentinian,</hi> Compoſing one Heretical Monſter from the ſeveral Madneſſes of the <hi>Manicheans</hi> and <hi>Gnoſticks</hi> joined together, among ſeveral other horrid Doctrines, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, <hi>That it was lawful to Lye, and to Diſſemble, for the avoiding of Sufferings; that the Truth was then to be retained in a Mans Heart only; whilſt the Confeſſion of the Mouth was requiſite to be made only before Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and Friends, and not before Strangers.</hi> But the Emperour <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> (as I ſhall more largely relate hereafter) well nigh put an end to this diſſembling and moſt perſidious Sect, by ſetting forth, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:45693:20"/>
punctually Executing the moſt ſevere Edicts againſt them, as Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to Humane Society it ſelf, no leſs than to all Religion in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. So that for a long time afterwards, (if I miſtake not) very few or none could be found, who durſt openly profeſs or propogate this Doctrine of Diſſimulation. For tho' it is not to be queſtioned, but that almoſt every Age and Place can produce many Perſons who may have prevailed with themſelves outwardly to comply with ſuch a ſort of Worſhip, as with which, at the ſame time, they could by no means inwardly join and heartily agree, and ſo have been ſelf Condemned in the very Action; yet, I think, but few for ſome Ages before us, have had the Confidence avowedly to maintain, or publickly to juſtifie the ſo doing. Till now of late with us, (to the ſhame, and I fear, the utter confuſion too of this our native Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try) there unhappily ſprang up one, of Fore-head enough, openly to revive, even in Print, this buried and forgotten Doctrine of thoſe who have ſo long ſince dwelt with Devils, for their deſerved recompence. The Man, I mean, is no other than that great Father of our Modern Atheiſts, the execrable Author of the <hi>Leviathan,</hi> who in that helliſh Volume, like a true Caſuiſt of <hi>Lucifer,</hi> thus ſtates the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lev.</hi> c. 42. p. 234.</note> Queſtion, and returns the Anſwer to it, by moſt ſhamefully abuſing this very Text. <hi>If it be asked,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>What if we be commanded by our lawful Prince to ſay, That we do not believe, muſt we obey him, or no?</hi> He Anſwers, <hi>That a Chriſtian Man, in matters of this Nature, if he does but believe on Chriſt in his Heart, has the ſame liberty which the Prophet</hi> Eliſha <hi>granted to</hi> Naaman <hi>the</hi> Syrian. Naaman <hi>was convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the God of</hi> Iſrael <hi>in his Heart, and ſaid,</hi> 2 Kin. 5. 17. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Naaman <hi>here believed with his Heart in the true God; but by his outward Worſhip de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to ſeem, as if he had not believed, leaſt he ſhould offend his King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To all which, I need ſay no more at preſent, but that you have heard of the Man and his Communication. Who, tho' he be gone ſometime ago <hi>to his own Place,</hi> or (as himſelf is ſaid to have Worded it when dying) into the dark Abyſs, has yet alſo left behind him, as but too many more ſecret Diſciples here, ſo one in another Country, who ſeems, (as if he were his eldeſt Son) to have taken Poſſeſſion of all his <hi>Ills,</hi> and to have become (among the reſt of his admirable Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities) Inheritour alſo of his haughty Spirit and ſingular Impudence. For the learned <hi>Puffendorff,</hi> in a late Treatiſe of his Intituled, THE NATURE OF RELIGION IN REFERENCE TO CIVIL SOCIETY, informs us of one <hi>Adrian Hutuyn,</hi> a Civilian in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who in a Book called A POLITICAL EPITOMY, among many other wild Extravagancies, has, as to this Point alſo, exactly Copied after the <hi>Leviathan.</hi> But I ſhall forbear producing any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, or making any farther Remarks upon this Author; It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing enough for my preſent purpoſe, only to obſerve thus much, <hi>viz.</hi> That his very choice of ſuch a <hi>Maſter,</hi> is a plain Indication
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:45693:20"/>
of the Temper and Inclinations of the Scholar. And ſince we here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by know, what kind of Spirit he is of, this alone may ſuffice to enable us to give his Writings alſo a ſuitable Entertainment.</p>
               <p>And indeed, (as I ſaid at firſt) had we no other Arguments to prevail upon us, methinks we ſhould be ſufficiently ſecured from the danger of this Infection, by the meer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orrour and Extreme Prejudice, which we may juſtly conceive, whilſt we conſider the notorious ill Characters of the ſeveral Authors and Promoters of this Doctrine, whoſe bare Names ſet over it, ſhould, methinks, be at the ſame time, both a ſufficient diſtinguiſhing Title to the Poiſon, and conſequently, in ſome Reſpect, a very good An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidote too: Since what elſe but miſchief can be expected from the ſo known Enemies of Chriſtianity and all Religion, and whoſe Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, in all other Points as well as this, was ſo very unlike to that of thoſe, who any way deſerved the Name of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians?</p>
               <p>Which is the Second thing I ſhall now Conſider, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How quite contrary was the Example of our Bleſſed Saviour himſelf, and his Apoſtles, as well as the Practiſe of all the genuine Primitive Chriſtians.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>NOW as to the Example of that great Author and Finiſher of our <note place="margin">John. 18. 37.</note> Faith, our ever Bleſſed Saviour, he expreſly declares of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>To this end was I born, and for this cauſe came I into the World, that I ſhould bear Witneſs unto the Truth.</hi> Which end and deſign of his, he fully made good and executed to the laſt, by laying down <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6. 13.</note> his moſt precious Life, upon that very Account, whilſt he <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed that excellent Confeſſion before Pontius Pilate,</hi> ſpoken of by the Apoſtle; upon which he received his Sentence of Condemnation. And what was that Truth, and that Confeſſion? No other than what is the very Foundation of all Chriſtianity, and at the ſame time, ſo ſhamefully denyed by our <hi>Socinians,</hi> who yet have the Face to call themſelves Chriſtians; <hi>viz.</hi> That he was the true Meſſiah, or really GOD-MAN. For upon his aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this grand Truth; <hi>That he and his Father were one,</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> took up Stones to Stone him, and directly Charge him with
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:45693:21"/>
Blaſphemy, in that <hi>he being,</hi> (as they ſuppoſed) <hi>a meer Man, made himſelf God;</hi> as we find, <hi>John</hi> 10. 30. 31. 33. And ſo <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. 63. When the High-Prieſt, with the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Sanhedrim ſitting in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on him, <hi>had adjured him by the living God, to tell them, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no he was the Chriſt, the Son of God,</hi> Jeſus anſwered him, <hi>THOU HAST SAID,</hi> that is, Thou haſt hit on the very Truth, or, I am really the Son of God.</p>
               <p>Which he alſo immediately farther confirms, with a Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning infinitely more terrible than Thunder and Lightning, or Ten thouſand Earthquakes, enough to have daſhed them into a Fit of Trembling and Conſternation, far beyond that of <hi>Belſhaz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar</hi> himſelf, when he ſaw the Hand-writing upon the Wall: For it follows, <hi>Nevertheleſs, I ſay unto you, Hereafter ſhall ye ſee the Son of Man, ſitting on the Right-hand of Power, and coming in the Clouds of Heaven.</hi> Where this Word, <hi>[Nevertheleſs]</hi> does not immediately relate to any thing either before, or afterwards expreſſed, but to ſomething that is to be ſupply'd, or underſtood: As if he had ſaid; Notwithſtanding, or Although I very well know, that you will not now believe this my Confeſſion; yet hereafter, to your unconceivable Sorrow and Confuſion, you ſhall be fully Convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eed of the Truth thereof, whether you will or no, when you ſhall ſee, (as moſt certainly you ſhall ſee) me coming in all the Majeſty of Heaven, to Judge the World. And here now, (begging a little Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion from my Subject) I cannot forbear adding, That thoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who after the Advantage of ſuch powerful Arguments, (which the <hi>Jews</hi> at that time wanted) towards the Confirmation of this Truth, by Chriſts Reſurrection, Aſcenſion, and ſending of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-Ghoſt, and by the ſo ſudden, and miraculous Propagation of the Goſpel all the World over, can yet find in their Hearts to deny, and even deride the real Divinity of our Saviour, are far more inexcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable than the very <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves; muſt in their Hearts think him, and do by Conſequence no other, than call him (I tremble to think of it) a meer Liar and Deceiver: They do in effect agree with the <hi>Jews,</hi> in their Charge of Blaſphemy againſt him, juſtifie their Actions, in his Condemnation and Crucifixion; and would in all probability, (whatſoever they may think to the contrary) have readily joyned with them in the ſame, had they but Lived in their Time and Circumſtances.</p>
               <p>But I return to my proper Buſineſs in hand, by next Conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, How well the Apoſtles alſo, followed this Example of their great Maſter, in not diſſembling the Truth, nor being aſhamed of the Goſpel, nor terrified from the open Confeſſion of their Faith up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all occaſions, notwithſtanding all the Dangers and Threatnings, that might have prevailed upon them to the contrary. And indeed had we no other Evidences to this purpoſe, our bare Obſervation,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:45693:21"/>
that the World is not ſtill <hi>Pagan,</hi> as the greateſt Atheiſt cannot deny, but that it once was ſo; that we now have, or know any thing of the Goſpel, this alone of it ſelf, is an undeniable Proof, and even a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Demonſtration of that matter. Since all this, under God, muſt needs be wholly owing to the undaunted Courage and Conſtancy of thoſe firſt Planters, without whoſe Light and faithful Preaching of the Word, we muſt ſtill have continued to ſit in Darkneſs, and in the ſhadow of Death. So, that even the greateſt Infidels in all other Points, muſt yet from the viſible effects thereof, eaſily e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough give Credit to thoſe particular Relations of the Goſpel, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Apoſtles Behaviour of this kind; <hi>viz</hi> That being firſt Beaten, and Impriſoned for Preaching Chriſt, and afterwards, ſtrictly charged by the Rulers, that they ſhould no more ſpeak to the People of that Name, they boldly anſwered; <note n="*" place="margin">Acts, 4. 19, 20.</note> 
                  <hi>Whether it be right in the ſight of God, to hearken unto you, more than unto God, judge ye, For we cannot but ſpeak the things which we have heard and ſeen.</hi> And ſo when ſome of the Brethren endeavoured to diſſwade St. <hi>Paul</hi> from his intended Journey to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in proſpect of the imminent Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers that would there attend him, his Anſwer was; <note n="*" place="margin">Acts, 21. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>What mean ye to weep and to break my Heart? For I am ready not to be Bound only, but alſo to Die at Jeruſalem, for the Name of the Lord Jeſus.</hi> And what the ſame Apoſtle affirms of himſelf, was no leſs true concerning all the reſt of his Collegues: <hi>That they did not ſhun to declare to the People, all the Counſel of God.</hi> One ſingle Inſtance indeed to the contrary of this, we find in St. <hi>Peter,</hi> even after our Saviours Reſurrection, who at one time ſo behaved himſelf, as if he deſigned to be thought of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Judgment than really he was, for Fear of, or to currie Favour with the <hi>Judaiſing</hi> Chriſtians: For which Action, notwithſtanding he was moſt ſeverely Reprehended by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> as he himſelf has given us thereof the particular Relation, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 11. &amp;c. Where he expreſly tells us, that upon this Account he withſtood him to the Face, as one greatly to be Blamed for ſuch Diſſimulation, and not walking uprightly according to the Truth of the Goſpel. But aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this ſingle Example, ſo far were they from any way concealing the Truth, or diſſembling their Belief, that the Conſideration of their having Acted quite otherwiſe, was matter of their greateſt Joy and Comfort, whilſt St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking in the Name of all the reſt, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures us, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 12. <hi>Our rejoycing is this, the Teſtimony of our Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that in Simplicity, and godly Sincerity, we have had our Converſation in the World.</hi> Which indeed, is ſo true a Charactor of their Demean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in general, that for conſtantly thus Acting and Profeſſing, they were all at laſt, at ſeveral Times and Places, put to ſeveral Deaths, by their <hi>Heathen</hi> Perſecutors: St. <hi>John</hi> alone excepted, who yet, ſuffering Baniſhment, and a Thouſand other living Deaths; ſhined
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:45693:22"/>
Bright to the very laſt, in all the Glories of a moſt Triumphant Confeſſour.</p>
               <p>But did not then (may you ſay) this Couragious Temper of ſuch admirable Zeal and Conſtancy, and undiſguis'd Simplicity, did it not at length expire and die with thoſe firſt Twelve moſt renowned Chriſtian Worthies? No no, by no means; It ſtill ſurvived for ſome Ages afterwards, in the glorious Names, and ſuitable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations, of thoſe holy Biſhops and Martyrs, St. <hi>Clemens,</hi> St. <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius, Polycarp, Juſtin, Irenaeus, Cyprian;</hi> and in the numerous Train, and long Succeſſion of other leading Officers in the Noble Army of Martyrs. From whence I ſhall ſingle out, and chuſe a little more largely to Relate ſome few Examples of latter Date, which, tho' perhaps they may be leſs known than the before menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, are yet no leſs Remarkable, nor leſs to my preſent pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
               <p>That good Biſhop of <hi>Tagaſte,</hi> a City in <hi>Africa,</hi> not far from <hi>Hippo, Firmus</hi> by Name, but much more firm in Reſolution, ſo much was he in Love with Truth, and Chriſtian Simplicity, and ſo far from that moſt hainous Lie of denying his Faith, that he was ready to Die, mch rather than to be induced to tell that which is called an officious Lie only. For when Officers ſent by the Emperour, for that end had enquired of him, concerning a certain Perſon, whom he had conceal'd with all the Care he could, he moſt ingenuouſly anſwered them, <hi>That he could neither tell a Lie, nor yet betray the Man:</hi> And thus conſtantly perſiſting in the ſame Reſolution, after all the Torments they could invent to make him Suffer, they brought him at length to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, to receive from him his final Doom.</p>
               <p>Now what ſhall we think of this Action? I know very well, what Cenſure ſome, who paſs for Chriſtians, would readily give of it: But let us hear, I pray, what was the Judgment of the Emperour himſelf in this Caſe, who was no other than a <hi>Pagan:</hi> But yet ſo extremely taken with the admirable Candour, Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity and Courage, of this ſo extraordinary Behaviour, that he not only preſently diſcharged <hi>Firmus</hi> himſelf; but for his ſake, freely Pardoned the Perſon alſo, whom the Biſhop had ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed; <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> lib. de Menda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio.</note> as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> gives us the Relation.</p>
               <p>Again, what ſhall we ſay to the wonderful Zeal, and undiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſed Simplicity, of <hi>Mark</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Arethuſa?</hi> Who choſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be miſerably Tormented to Death by the Rabble, than ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Rebuild, (as he was Commanded by <hi>Julian)</hi> or give the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:45693:22"/>
leaſt Sum himſelf, or ſuffer others, who ſo offered to do it for him, towards the Rebuilding of the Heathen-Temple.</p>
               <p>In like manner, <hi>Anthony,</hi> an <hi>Arian</hi> Biſhop, after he was able by no exquiſiteneſs of Torments, to bring <hi>Habetdeus,</hi> an Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Biſhop, over to the Profeſſion of his own impious Sect, at laſt, ſtopping his Mouth, and binding his Hands and Feet, he by force Plunged him into the Bath of Re-babtization, which he had prepared for that purpoſe. And then afterwards endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to perſwade him, that by this Waſhing he was made a Companion and Partaker with him of the ſame Hereſie<hi>:</hi> But the good Biſhop, by a conſtant Confeſſion, moſt Couragiouſly denyed it, ſaying; <hi>O wicked</hi> Anthony! <hi>That can be no Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation unto Death, where the Aſſent of the Will is wanting, I, moſt te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacious of my Faith, did, as long as ever I had the Opportunity, lowd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly defend, and with my Voice confeſs the things which I did and do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve: But after you had Bound me with Chains, and ſtopping my Mouth, took away from me the Faculty of Speaking; I then tranſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the more ſecret Confeſſion of my Faith, kept within the Cloſet of my Breaſt, as well as the monſtrous Acts of that your Violence againſt me, to be both of them read by my bleſſed Saviour, the holy Angels themſelves alſo therein Subſcribing to me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Admirable likewiſe was the Example of <hi>Eulogius,</hi> a Presbyter of the Church of <hi>Corduba,</hi> who being drag'd upon the Account of his Religion, before the chief Counſellours of a <hi>Mahomet an</hi> King, was by one of them with whom he had been familiarly acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, after this manner Subtily, but yet (as the Man meant it) compaſſionately Accoſted: <hi>That Fools and Ideots</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſhould run themſelves upon Death and Ruin, is a thing not ſo much to be wondered at: But as for you, who are a Man ſo adorned, with all the Accompliſhments of Wisdom, and approved for the Honeſty of your Converſation, What Madneſs is it that forces you thus to fling your ſelf into this lamentable Condition? Hearken, I beſeech you to my Counſel, and do not obſtinately run upon your own Deſtruction. Deny only by one ſmall Word, now in this your Hour of Neceſſity, and then after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, whereſoever you can do it ſafely, freely exerciſe and enjoy your own Faith. We Promiſe you, that you ſhall no where be ever ſought after.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To whom, the holy Man, (a little Smiling) thus reply'd<hi>: O that you could but know, how glorious Things are prepared for the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Worſhipers that are of our Religion! Or that I could but once</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Alvari Hiſt. citante Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronio. An. Vol. 10. p. 161.</note> 
                  <hi>convey into yours, what I retain and feel in my own Breaſt, then would you be ſo far from endeavouring to recall me from my purpoſe, that your Thoughts would be wholly taken up, about how you might beſt</hi>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:45693:23"/>
                  <hi>withdraw your ſelf from this deceitful Worldly Honour.</hi> And ſo he began to Preach to them the word of Life<hi>:</hi> But they refuſing to hear the ſame, preſently commanded him to be run thorow with a Sword.</p>
               <p>Nor let any one Object againſt the already produced Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, (as ſome have done upon the like occaſion) That all theſe are Examples only of Biſhops and other publick Miniſters of the Chriſtian Church; upon whom (they are ready to grant) there does lie ſome Obligation, in point of Credit as well as Intereſt, to chuſe to ſuffer rather than deny or diſſemble their Belief: And to this purpoſe, the zealous Diſciples even of that grand Atheiſtical Patron, whom I had occaſion not long ago to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, have thought fit to treaſure up this in Print among the reſt of his (ſuppoſed) witty poſthumous Sayings, <hi>viz. That none ought ſo juſtly to Die for their Religion, as they that Live by it.</hi> Whereas, may they ſay, there is not the ſame Reaſon, that private Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſhould be thus obliged; nor is it eaſy, perhaps, amongſt them, to produce the like Examples. Now to obviate this Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, as well as in regard of the great natural Uſefulneſs of ſuch Precedents, to promote in others the like Zeal and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, I ſhall think it worth the while, to give you ſtill ſome farther Variety of the like Behaviour in all Sorts and Degrees of other Chriſtian Profeſſors. Concerning whom in general, <hi>Juſtin</hi> Martyr, gives us this ample Teſtimony, <hi>That they can never</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Juſt.</hi> Mart. in Dial. cum Tryph. Jud.</note> 
                  <hi>endure ſo much as to ſeem to Worſhip an Idol;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>but ſuffer all kind of Torments and Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments even to the very laſt efforts of Death, rather than either Worſhip Idols, or eat of any thing Offered thereto.</hi> And ſtill in his ſecond Apology to the Chriſtians, he thus deſcribes the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians of his Time; <hi>We who formerly before our Converſion, uſed to employ our ſelves in Butchering one another, do now not only not reſiſt our Enemies, but, rather than tell a Lye, or deceive even thoſe who inform againſt us, willingly confeſs Chriſt, to the loſs of our very Lives: Whereas, (would our Conſciences permit) we might, (as well as you Heathen are wont to do) make uſe of, and behave our ſelves according to your uſual Proverb; Swear with our</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Tongues, remaining ſtill unſworn in your Minds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But deſcending now to particulars, with whom can I bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter begin, or more agreeably place in the fore Front, than that noble and couragious Soldier <hi>Valentinian</hi> the Elder? Afterwards Emperour of <hi>Rome;</hi> but at that time an Officer only in the Army of the Emperour <hi>Julian,</hi> who was ſo far from do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:45693:23"/>
or ſuffering any thing which might give any juſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his being thought to comply with the Heatheniſh Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, that he boldly ſtruck the <hi>Aedile,</hi> who had ſprinkled him with luſtral Water among the reſt, according to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans Cuſtome, and cut out that part of his Garment, even in the ſight of <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate.</p>
               <p>After him ſhall follow, (tho' in time he went before him) another Chriſtian Soldier, called <hi>Gordius,</hi> of the City of <hi>Ceſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea,</hi> and no leſs magnanimous. Whoſe Perſecutors (as St. <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil</hi> gives us the Hiſtory) after they could by no other means <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Baſil</hi> Hom. in Mart.</note> turn him aſide from the Faith, ſet upon him at laſt with ſome plauſible Arguments, perſuading him that he ſhould, if he had ſtill a mind, retain Chriſt in his Heart only, and with his Mouth deny him: <hi>For God</hi> (ſay the) <hi>does not look upon Words, but upon the Mind it ſelf of the Speaker; This is the only way to appeaſe the angry Judge, and to keep God himſelf propitious too.</hi> But he remaining firm and immovable, anſwered them after this manner; <hi>I can by no means yield, to let that Tongue, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of which is wholly owing to Chriſts Favour, ſo ſhamefully deny its Author. For with the Heart we believe unto Righteouſneſs, and with the Mouth we make Confeſſion unto Salvation. Do not err, God cannot be mocked Out of our own Mouthes he Judges, and from our Words he will either Save or Damn us. Did you never hear of that dreadful Sentence of our great Lord?</hi> viz. <hi>He that denieth me before Men, him will I alſo deny before my Father which is in Heaven,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>You Counſel me, that I ſhould at preſent diſſemble the Knowledge which I have of God. Wherefore, I pray? Is it that I may prolong this Life, add to my Days, and while off the bitterneſs of Death? But ſhall I then be contented to looſe the Eternal Years of the heavenly Life? Shall I, to avoid a little preſent pain, forego for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever that future Crown of Righteouſneſs and exceeding weight of Glory? Thus deliberately to chooſe to damn my ſelf, and by ſuch ſhameful Deceit and Fraud to purchaſe to my ſelf the Eternal Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Hell, can be no other than down right Madneſs. Let me therefore rather give you this Advice; That if hitherto you have been miſtaken, you would now at length learn Truth and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; but if you diſſemble your Faith, and ſerve the preſent time, I earneſtly exhort and intreat you, that laying aſide Lying, you would boldly ſpeak the Truth: For every Tongue is to confeſs the Glory of Chriſt, as well as every Knee to bow at his Name.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After theſe two great Leaders, I am ſtill enabled to preſent to your view, all at once, a whole little Army of the ſame Profeſſion, who alſo ſhewed themſelves to be no leſs Chriſts
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:45693:24"/>
faithful Soldiers. Tho' the Story be ſomewhat large, yet I ſhall give you it in full, with all its material and more conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Circumſtances, becauſe the ſame will help us ſo much the better to underſtand both the great Subtilety of the Heathen to enſnare, and what was the chief thing they drove at, and how extreamly careful likewiſe the then Chriſtians were, to avoid giving any juſt occaſion of Scandal, and to abſtain from all Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Evil, eſpecially in ſuch tender Caſes. Now <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate being fully ſatisfied, by many fruitleſs Attempts of that kind, and Experiments ſo often in vain repeated, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was to be done on the Chriſtians, no prevailing upon them to comply with his Purpoſe, by the more common and open ways of down right Force or Threatnings, thought fit at laſt to betake himſelf to the courſes of Fraud and Subtilety, to trap them, (if poſſible) as it were by way of Ambuſh or Surprize, and to overcome them by cunning Artifices and Contrivances. And accordingly, altering the Standards or Enſigns of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, which were before in uſe, cauſed to be expreſſed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, together with his own, the Images of the Pagan Gods; ſo that when his Chriſtian Subjects came to ſignifie their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence thereto, (as 'twas both uſual, and generally concluded Innocent, for them that way to ſhew their reſpect to the Emperour) they might be at the ſame time forced Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly, or indeliberately to Worſhip, or at leaſt ſeem to Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Pagan Idols alſo; or elſe be puniſhed as Traitors and Contemners of him for their Refuſal. Which yet very many (as ſoon as they diſcovered the Cheat) choſe to do, and generouſly ſuffered for it accordingly. Again, when the ſet time came, that the Emperour ſhould according to Cuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oms, give Rewards to the Soldiers, this ſubtile Apoſtate, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering how Ignorant and ſimple a ſort of Men Souldiers ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally were, and by their covetous Temper, how eaſily over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come with Money, before hand inſtructed thoſe whom he employed to diſpenſe his Gifts, that, having both Fire and Frankincenſe in a readineſs, they ſhould command every one, as he came to receive his Donative, to caſt in a peice of Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kincenſe, as if this had been formerly ſo ordered among all the <hi>Romans</hi> of old. But even upon this alſo many ſhewed a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Magnanimity, utterly refuſing both to offer, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any gift from him. Others, truſting to the Pretences and colour of an old Law or Cuſtom, did not in the leaſt think themſelves to have committed any Sin at all. While ſome again, taken with that bait of the propoſed Gain, or aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed through fear of the enſuing Puniſhment, refuſed not even knowingly, to defile themſelves with ſo great a Crime. But
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:45693:24"/>
ſoon afterwards, when ſeveral of all theſe ſorts come Familiar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to converſe together, and ſome in drinking to each other, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to name the name of Chriſt, one of the Company interrupted them ſaying, <hi>That it ſeemed very ſtrange, that they ſhould now invocate Chriſt, whom they had ſo lately denied, when re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the Emperour's Donative, they had caſt Franckinſenſe into the Fire.</hi> Upon this, many of thoſe that had ignorantly offended taking the Alarm, and comming to underſtand what they had done, haſtily departed together; and running up and down the Streets with Tears and Outcries, openly called God and Man to Witneſs, that they are Chriſtians, and ſtill continue in the Faith; that out of mere Ignorance of what was done, their Hands alone, whilſt their Mind abhorred it, were pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted with the Pagan ſuperſtition. But when they came at laſt to the Emperour himſelf, throwing down the Gold he had given them, at his Feet, with conſtant courageous Minds, they entreat of him, <hi>That they may now receive their own proper Gift belonging to them, that is, that they may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer Death: For it was a Matter of which they ſhould never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, if for the Crime they had ſo inconſiderately committed with the Hand they ſhould now be puniſhed in their whole Body for Chriſts ſake.</hi> But <hi>Julian,</hi> tho' extremely troulbled at this, yet envying them the Honour of Martyrdom, would not put them to Death but Baniſhing them his Court, ſtruck them alſo out of the Liſt <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sozom. l.</hi> 5. c. 16.</note> of Soldiers.</p>
               <p>Nor were Chriſtian Soldiers the only Perſons endued with ſuch Chriſtian Courage and Simplicity: The primitive times afforded many thouſands of all other ſorts, who willingly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered up their Lives; Sacrifice, and committed their Bodies to the Sword, to Racks, to Lions, to the Flames, rather than once caſt one Grain of Frankincenſe into the Fire of thoſe Altars. Among whom, though doubtleſs, very great is the number of the wholly unrecorded, and ſuch of whom there is now left no mention or Memory unto Poſterity; yet, I fear, you would be apt to think it ſomething like a little ſort of Martyrdom, were you obliged only to hear, or barely to read over all the Relations of this kind that are ſtill extant. Where we ſhall find all ſincere Chriſtians, at all times ready to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go any kind of Death or Torment, rather than to offer to deny Chriſt themſelves, or ſo much as ſubſtitute or ſuffer any other to do either of then for theſe; rather than purchaſe a a falſe Certificate of the Judge concerning their having done this; nay, where any falſe Report was raiſed to that purpoſe, rather than not openly deny and contradict the ſame; in a Word,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:45693:25"/>
rather than to ſay or do, or be ſo ſilent, as might give any juſt occaſion of their ſeeming, or being thought to have complied with ſuch Sinful and Idolatrous Worſhip.</p>
               <p>Very remarkable to this purpoſe is what St. <hi>Baſil</hi> relates, concerning one <hi>Barlaham,</hi> a very mean and illiterate Man, but <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Baſil.</hi> Orat. in <hi>Barla.</hi>
                  </note> yet moſt truly noble and admirable for his Chriſtian Courage, whom after the Heathen Perſecutors had firſt long and diverſe ways (but in vain) Tormented, for refuſing to Sacrifice; they at laſt endeavoured to circumvent him by this cunning Stratagem. Firſt they compel him to ſtretch out his right Hand, with the Palm upwards, over the Fire of their Altar, and then of a ſuddain poured into his Hand a quantity of flaming Frankincenſe, expecting that the extreme pain would naturally make him ſhake his Hand, to be rid of it, and with the ſame motion alſo ſhake ſome of the Franckincenſe into the Fire, and ſo look to thoſe who ſtood at a diſtance, as if he had voluntarily comply'd with them, in the uſe of that common Ceremony, by which they were accuſtomed to Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip their Idols. But this Chriſtian <hi>Mutius</hi> did not ſtir nor flinch one Jot; but, as if his Arm had been made of Braſs, and equally void both of Senſe and Motion, he ſuffered the flaming Matter to eat into his Hand, till it quite burnt out of it ſelf, rather than by the leaſt Motion ſpilling any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle on the Altar, he ſhould ſo be forced, but to ſeem therein to comply with them in the Idolatrous Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</p>
               <p>And here now, leaſt any one in this caſe, ſhould ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Baron</hi> An. v. 3. p. 54.</note> attribute, more than is convenient either to the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Temper of the Man, or to the advantage of his Sex, I ſhall add hereto one parallel Inſtance, even of a Woman, who upon the ſame occaſion, and under the ſame Tryal, ſhewed her ſelf no leſs Triumphant. For <hi>Cyrilla,</hi> who ſuffered at <hi>Cyrene</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> is certainly worthy of eternal Memory. Who, under the Perſecution of <hi>Maximinus,</hi> having had not burning Coals mixed with Franckincenſe, placed upon her Hand, moſt ſteadfaſtly held them there in like manner for a long time together, leaſt, by the ſlighteſt Motion ſhaking down any thereof, ſhe might ſeem to have offered to the Idol. And ſo ſhe was aftewards cruelly torn in Peices.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:45693:25"/>
After theſe Examples now, what ſhall we ſay or think of thoſe Men, who, more delighting themſelves in the newer name of <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants,</hi> than in that of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> do alſo, upon the like occaſions, allow themſelves the Liberty of a new, and indeed quite contrary behaviour to all theſe venerable Precedents? I ſpeak of thoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons among us, who, travelling into foraign Countries out of no abſolute Neceſſity neither, but only to encreaſe their Wealth, or, perhaps, merely for their Pleaſure and Recreation; yet when they are once there, rather than incur any conſiderable danger, which their own folly too firſt brought them to encounter with; it may be, rather than ſuffer a ſmall Affront; Nay, ſometimes, rather than not ſatisfy their vain Curioſity; can afford to cringe, and bow, and kiſs, or do any thing elſe with the outward Man, that they know will be thought a Complyance; nay, on ſet purpoſe, that they may ſeem and be thought actually to comply with ſuch Practices, as they are fully perſwaded at the ſame time to be ſinful, and even Idolatrous, and of which they pretend to have really an utter abhorrence in their Hearts.</p>
               <p>But ſome mens <hi>new Light,</hi> and <hi>new Faith</hi> too, quite void of <hi>old Patience,</hi> and far more truly called Preſumption, may (it's likely enough) enbolden them to endeavour to juſtify themſelves, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning all theſe unfaſhionable Examples, as the raſh and indiſcreet Actions of private perſons, who had more Zeal than Knowledge, and went, upon their own heads, much farther than they were any way really obliged to. Whereas (may they object) did your Biſhops and publick Governours of the Church, who underſtood the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Duty, did they require any ſuch ſtrictneſs from all Believers? Or did they not rather indeed, in their publick Councils and Canons, allow ſome greater Liberties unto common Chriſtians? Which brings me to a third Conſideration, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How generally condemned they are by the publick Canons, and what ſevere Cenſures the Primitive Church paſſed and inflicted upon Time-ſervers and Diſſemblers of their Faith.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>WHere we may obſerve, that tho' it was the main Care and Study of thoſe antient Worthies, how they might beſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and keep up an exact Diſcipline in the Church, without which (as they wiſely conſidered) it had been wholly impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that Chriſtianity ſhould have long ſubſiſted under the then Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances; yet we ſhall likewiſe find, that they very well knew alſo how to temper their Severities with Mildneſs, granting all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:45693:26"/>
and convenient Liberties, and ſometimes abating of ſome Rigors upon a juſt Occaſion, and ſhortening the allotted time of Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, as they judged it moſt conducive to the good of the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitents themſelves, or neceſſary (according to different circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) towards the Advantage and Edification of the Church in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral.</p>
               <p>To flie in the time of Perſecution, (as well it might, our Saviour himſelf adviſing thereto) was a Liberty allowed by all Univerſally, <hi>Tertullian</hi> only excepted, who, after carried away with the Error of the <hi>Montaniſts,</hi> rigidly deny'd the Lawfulneſs thereof: But was ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly condemned for his ſo doing, by all others of the Orthodox Church in general. Who alſo, when they ſaw it moſt expedient, (like St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> for a while) freely made uſe of that Liberty, no leſs to the commendation of their own Prudence, than to the benefit and advantage of the Chriſtian Commonwealth. Nor did thoſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Wiſe conductors require, that any ſhould, when uncalled up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, needleſly, and of their own accord offer themſelves up as Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to the <hi>Pagan</hi> Magiſtrates, but rather diſcouraged and forbad this practice, as arguing a zeal too Intemperate, and ſavouring of Raſhneſs and Preſumption. To which purpoſe St. <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>St.</hi> Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt.</hi> 83.</note> 
                  <hi>Cyprian</hi> expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thus adviſeth: <hi>Let none of you unneceſſarily and of his own accord pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent himſelf to the Gentiles: But being apprehended and delivered up to them, he ought then couragiouſly to ſpeak, what the Lord ſhall in that hour direct him to; Qui nos confiteri magis voluit, quam profiteri, Who would have us to confeſs only, rather than ſo profeſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They in like manner generally concluded it not unlawful, that a Chriſtian Man, (making uſe of the Covetouſneſs of his Judge, to defeat his Cruelty) ſhould purchaſe his ſafety by a Summ of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, provided it was merely ſo obtained, without his otherwiſe ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or doing any thing diſhonourable to or inconſiſtent with his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion. Tho' indeed the Council of <hi>Eliberis</hi> (the moſt ſevere of any) did paſs ſome Cenſure even upon ſuch Perſons.</p>
               <p>But then as to the Caſe of thoſe commonly called by the Antients <hi>Libellatici,</hi> who, tho' they had neither deny'd nor ſacrificed, yet pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed of the Magiſtrate; a falſe Certificate concerning their having done either of theſe, and kept and produced the ſame for their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity upon occaſion, all the Primitive Biſhops no leſs than <note n="b" place="margin">Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an <hi>lib. de Lapſis.</hi>
                  </note> St. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian,</hi> are juſtly moſt ſevere in their Condemnation.</p>
               <p>The puniſhment they allotted to Idolaters, or thoſe who deny'd the Faith, was to be caſt out from the Communion of the Church; to be forbidden the Aſſemblies of the Faithful; To be obliged to extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Faſtings; To proſtrate themſelves at the feet of thoſe who went in at the Church Porch; To acknowledge themſelves caſt out as Salt that had loſt its Savour; To beg their Prayers with Tears and Lamentation; and to exerciſe many other Acts of Humility and Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification, for ſeveral years together, more or leſs, according to dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:45693:26"/>
Times and Places, as well as the different manners and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of their Offending. In the <hi>Roman</hi> and <hi>African</hi> Churches there was a time when they never admitted them to Peace, who, after Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, had once lapſed into Idolatry: And when afterwards they did conſent to ſome Relaxion, yet even then they were never reconciled to the Church, till either they lay upon their Death-beds, or had ſuffered a very long and rigorous Penance. Nor did they ever think fit to impoſe this courſe of Repentance any more than once; For who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever relapſed a ſecond time, could never be re-admitted to Church Communion, but was to expect his pardon from God alone.</p>
               <p>The <note n="c" place="margin">59. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non. Concil. Elib. apud Du Pin. v.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 244.</note> Council of <hi>Eliberis</hi> or <hi>Elvira</hi> forbids Chriſtians, not only to aſcend the Capital, in order to Sacrifice thereon, but even at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, ſo much as to behold that <hi>Pagan</hi> Worſhip, inflicting no leſs than ten years Penance upon ſuch Offenders.</p>
               <p>The ſeventh Canon of the Councils of <hi>Ancyra</hi> and <hi>Neocaeſarea</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed two years Penance upon thoſe, who were preſent at the Feaſts, made in Honour of the Idols, tho' they carried their own Meat thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, not eating of any thing that had been ſo offered.</p>
               <p>In the year 306. <hi>Peter</hi> the renowned Martyr and Biſhop of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria,</hi> together with the reſt of the Biſhops of the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> made ſeveral Canons, adjuſting the Puniſhments of thoſe, who had lapſed in the time of Perſecution: Some of which more immediately relating to my preſent purpoſe, I ſhall think it very well worth my while to ſet down here at large, as I find them recorded in the Annals of <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Annal. Baron. vol.</hi> 2 <hi>p.</hi> 792.</note> 
                  <hi>Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius.</hi> And this the rather, becauſe, both in regard of the great Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of Caſes with which we are thereby acquainted, as well as in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their ſingular Wiſdom, thorrowly conſidering the differences of caſes, and allotting accordingly different Penalties, by a moſt juſt Severity, tempered with due Moderation, they ſeem to be as remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as any thing of this kind that is to be found in all the Treaſures of Antiquity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As for thoſe (ſaith he) who counterfeited and diſſembled (like David, who to ſave his Life, feigned himſelf frantick, when he was far from being ſo) and did not down-right ſubſcribe to the denial of Chriſt; but being in great ſtraits, and endued with weaker <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings, were, like fooliſh Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, deceived into the Snares of the Enemy; as more particularly, thoſe Perſons who only pretended that they had offered unto Idols, or that they had approached their Altars, or given up their names, or elſe had ſent Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans to offer in their ſtead; becauſe, with the greateſt Caution, they avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed either with their own hands to carry the fire, or to perfume with Incenſe thoſe impure Daemons, as well as, becauſe it is not certain, whether or no they might not do, even what they did, out of mere Ignorance; Let it be ſufficient to impoſe upon ſuch only, ſix Months Penance of Converſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then in the 6th Canon, as to the Cauſe of thoſe, who, (as he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves) had ſent their Slaves, tho' Chriſtians alſo, to offer for them, or any thing of the like nature that was required; He makes this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:45693:27"/>
in the Puniſhment to be inflicted on theſe different Perſons, viz. <hi>Let the Servants, who, as being in ſubjection, and in a ſort under the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtody and Authority of their Maſters, and perhaps terrify'd by their Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, might be forced through the dread of them ſo to tranſgreſs; Let them continue in the Works of Penance for one year only; from henceforth learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as the Servants of Christ to do his Will, and to fear him above All, being aſſured that whatſoever good any one does, that ſhall he receive at his hands, whether he be Bond or Free. But then as for the Maſters, who were free and at their own diſpoſal, let them undergo ſevere Penances for no leſs than three years together; as well, becauſe they groſly diſſembled themſelves, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they (in a manner) compelled their Servants ſo to tranſgreſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>Alexandria</hi> does there perfectly acquit thoſe (as well he might) into whoſe mouths meats ſacrificed to Idols, were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibly thruſt, as thoſe alſo who were ſerved, as in the former caſe of <hi>Baraham,</hi> tho' they might not bear the Tryal in all Circumſtances with the ſame Courage.</p>
               <p>But beſides this uſual one of Excommunication, and the reſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forementioned, the Antients alſo invented, and frequently impoſed upon ſuch Delinquents another very adequate and ingenious Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; which too, in my Opinion, was not leſs ſevere in its kind, than any of the former, tho' perhaps leſs taken notice of under that Notion. For 'twas a common thing with the Primitive Biſhops, to oblige thoſe who had lapſed, by either denying or diſſembling the Faith, before they could be reconciled to the Church, to make fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Viſits to the Confeſſors that were detained in Priſon, and there, in the moſt humble manner, to beg their Pardon, againſt whom they had ſo notoriouſly offended, in ſhamefully denying what the other had ſo couragiouſly confeſſed; and to intreat them likewiſe to interceed for them. Which certainly (if well conſidered) muſt needs be no ſmall ſort of Mortification, for thoſe who had cloathed themſelves with Shame, and were all over polluted with the deformities of ſo ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious a Denial, ſo much, as even to behold the dazling Countenances of them, who ſhined out ſo bright in the full Luſtre of a moſt glorious Confeſſion. And how much more confounded then muſt we needs ſuppoſe them, at the juſt Reproofs which they would hear from them? What better way could there ever have been invented, more effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to Conſult either the Glory and Dignity of the Confeſſors, or the real Benefit and Advantage of the lapſed? Who were by this means, in a manner forced, as men overcome, to proſtrate themſelves at the feet of their Conquerours, and with the loweſt Humility and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of Mind, firſt to qualify themſelves for, and then to procure the Peace of the Church, by the prevailing Prayers of ſuch powerful interceſſors. But yet that which was firſt introduced as a very good Remedy, was, by humane Perverſneſs and Iniquity, at length converted into no ſmall Diſtemper; whilſt the lapſed, quite deſpiſing both the Biſhop and all his Presbyters, of their own accord, betook
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:45693:27"/>
themſelves to the Martyrs, and having firſt extorted from them ſuch petitionary Letters concerning Peace, looked then upon it, as a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Debt, abſolutely owing to the Prayers of the Martyrs, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon peremptorily required, rather than requeſted to be received to the Communion of the Church.</p>
               <p>Conecrning all the particulars of which Abuſes, we may be fully informed from ſeveral paſſages in the Writings of St. <hi>Cyprian;</hi> who alſo diligently endeavoured to correct the ſame. Such now was the prudent Care and Diligence of Eccleſiaſtical Governnours in the firſt Centuries of Chriſtianity, by all the means imaginable to hinder Men from denying, or diſſembling, or any ways being aſhamed of the Faith.</p>
               <p>And indeed ſomething of the like Care and Diſcipline ſtill conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued upon occaſion, for ſome Ages afterwards. For when <hi>Gundebald,</hi> King of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> had been convinced by <hi>Alcinus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Vienna,</hi> concerning the <hi>Arian</hi> Hereſy, and to acknowledge the true Orthodox Faith; but yet, out of fond Shame, joyned with ſome politick ends, endeavouring to diſſemble and conceal this his Converſion, deſired the good Biſhop not publickly to anoint him with the Chriſm, (the uſual way then of admitting Hereticks, when converted, into the Boſom of the Church) but that he would privately, and in ſecret, perform this Ceremony for him: He had this Anſwer; <hi>If you do truly believe what our Lord hath taught us, then do accordingly. Now he ſaith thus; If any one Confeſs me before Men, &amp;c. And again, He that denyeth me before Men, &amp;c. In like manner forewarning his holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles concerning the tryals of the enſuing Perſecutions, He thus admoniſheth them; Beware of Men, for they ſhall deliver you up to the Councils, and they will ſcourge you in their Synagogues, and ye ſhall be brought before Governours and Kings for my ſake, and for a Teſtimony againſt them and the Gentiles. But you (ſaith he) being a King, and ſo in no danger of being brought before any one, do yet refuſe in publick to confeſs the Creator of all things, for fear of the Sedition of your own Subjects. But God cannot be mocked; nor does he love him, who for the ſake of an Earthly Kingdom, refuſeth to confeſs his Name.</hi> But <hi>Gundebald</hi> ſtill continuing in his Refuſal to make a publick Confeſſion of his Faith, and deſire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Greg. Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron de geſtis Franc. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 34.</note> to be thought to be of another Belief than he really was in his Heart, remained juſtly excluded the Communion of the Orthodox Church, even to his lives end.</p>
               <p>And now, if after all this it ſhould be ſtill objected, in manifeſt Contradiction to the known Wiſdom, as well as Moderation of theſe celebrated Guides and Rulers of the Church, that they requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of Chriſtians more than was neceſſary, and were too ſevere and rigorous in their Cenſures; I ſhall next appeal and cite them to a much higher Tribunal, and ſuch as they muſt needs acknowledge to be wholly infallible in all it Cenſures. Which brings me to my fourth General conſideration, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:45693:28"/>
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The Miraculous Preſervation of ſome, and Supports of others, who were ſincere and conſtant in their Confeſſion, and the no leſs miraculous and extraordinary Puniſhments divinely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted upon the contrary Offenders.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>AND firſt then, tho' the Scripture had not otherwiſe (as it does) ſo expresſly commended that of the three Children, who choſe to be caſt into a fiery Furnace, rather than, by bowing down their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies before it, ſeem to Worſhip the Golden Image which <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezar</hi> had ſet up; yet what better Argument could we have of Gods immediate Approbation of that Action, than his ſo miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Preſervation of them?</p>
               <p>The like Miracle we alſo find in the Epiſtle of the Church of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> concerning <hi>Polycarp</hi> the Biſhop of that City, who being up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the like account condemned to be burnt to Death, as ſoon as the Pile of Wood was well kindled, the Flames roſe up round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him at a diſtance, in the manner of a great Arch, or like the Sails of a Ship, when filled with the Wind: Whilſt he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in the midſt untouched, and without harm. Which being taken notice of with Admiration, and ſeeing that it was impoſſible to put an end to his Life by Fire, one of the Executioners was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to run him thorow with a Sword.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pontianus,</hi> who, for refuſing to Sacrifice, ſuffered at <hi>Spoleto</hi> under the Emperor <hi>Antoninus,</hi> after he had been almoſt all other ways mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably Tormented, was then thrown to the Lions in the Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre, who would not ſo much as once touch him. After that he was thruſt into Priſon, there to be Starv'd to death: But being unexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctedly fed by the miniſtry of an Angel, for ſeveral days, the Judge commanded boyling Lead to be poured all over his naked Body; and ſtill when this alſo could not kill him, they at laſt put an end to his Life, by cutting off his Head.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſebius</hi> in like manner tells us of a great many Chriſtians ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> in the City <hi>Tyre</hi> of <hi>Phenicia,</hi> who having been <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſeb. Hiſt. l.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 7.</note> expoſed to Lions, Bears, Leopards, and other ravenous Beaſts, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver received the leaſt harm from them; tho' when tryed with any other Perſons, the beaſts ſell greedily to their Work. Which tho' it juſtly cauſed Amazement in all Beholders, yet their cruel Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, not ſuffering them to eſcape ſo, put them all to the Sword, and then caſt their Bodies into the Sea.</p>
               <p>The like to this we alſo read, happening to <hi>Elutherius, Caecilia, Euſtratius,</hi> and many others in the ſeveral Martyroligies. who, tho' they
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:45693:28"/>
were all ſuffered to die, at laſt by one ſort of death or another, that ſo the Rewards of their Conſtancy might no longer be defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, were yet firſt wonderfully preſerved from ſo many kinds, that it might thereby ſufficiently appear, both how able the ſame Divine Power was to have ſtill preſerved them from any violent death at all; and how miracuouſly Heaven owned their Cauſe, and ſo, how altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inexcuſable was the Obſtinacy of thoſe, who would not be convinced thereby.</p>
               <p>But ſtill moſt Remarkable is that of one <hi>Theodore,</hi> who under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>went all ſorts of Torments for half a day together, with ſuch ſtrange Chearfulneſs and Alacrity, that <hi>Salluſt</hi> the <hi>Prefect,</hi> to whom <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate had given that unacceptable Employment, being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly amazed thereat, and utterly deſpairing of Succeſs, remanded the Man to Priſon; and, going to the Emperour, honeſtly adviſed him to leave off ſuch Cruelties; ſince otherwiſe he would only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure ſtill greater Honour to the Chriſtians, and to himſelf nothing at all but Diſgrace and Shame thereby. Afterwards this <hi>Theodore</hi> was ſet free, and went to <hi>Antioch:</hi> When being asked; <hi>If he felt any</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ruffin. lib.</hi> 1 <hi>c.</hi> 36.</note> 
                  <hi>Pain when in the burning hot Brazen Inſtrument?</hi> He anſwered, That at the firſt he did feel ſome: But ſoon after one in the Form of a young Man ſtanding by him, continually wiped off his Sweat, and bathed him with cold Water; with which he was ſo admirably comforted and delighted, that after he was releaſed and ſet down, he could not chuſe but be troubled thereat.</p>
               <p>We want not alſo very grave Authors, and of unqueſtionable Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit (one of them too, far enough from being any <note n="e" place="margin">Procop. Hiſt. Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal.</note> Friend to the Cauſe) who tell us of a great many Perſons under the Arian Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who had ſtill the Miraculous continuation of the Gift of Speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, even after they had had their Tongues pluck'd out.</p>
               <p>Now, tho' thus to be preſerved from ſo many Deaths and Inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences, or not to be ſenſible of any Pain at all under the hands of ſuch exquiſite Tormenters, is a Thing aſtoniſhing to conſider of; yet for Men ſo to behave themſelves, as all the reſt of the Martyrs did, even under the greateſt Senſe of Pain, is to be look'd upon as neither much leſs Admirable, nor leſs to our preſent Purpoſe. But yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning that ſupernatural Courage, with which they bore their Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, I ſhall not need to beſtow much time; having already (tho' to a different Purpoſe) produced ſo many Inſtances of Extraordinary Conſtancy, which may equally ſerve alſo, as ſo many Arguments of an Extraordinary Divine Support, and conſequently of God's imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Approbation too, of the particular Cauſes for which, and manner after which they ſuffered. The Conſequence of both which, was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſo apparent to thoſe who impartially weighed the Matter, that ſeveral of the Judges themſelves, and many of their very Tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, were ſo powerfully convinc'd thereby, as to become immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Cenſeſſors and Martyrs their own ſelves.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:45693:29"/>
But waving all theſe Examples, both as already ſufficiently well known to moſt, and as too numerous to be here particularly related, I ſhall at preſent content my ſelf with one Example onely, of a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle different kind, which may well ſerve for all the reſt; ſince it is ſuch as, I think, nothing in all Hiſtory can go beyond it. It happen'd in the Perſecution in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> carried on by the Emperour <hi>Maximi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> and was there alſo preſented to the World in the Perſon of a young and tender Virgin, the Beautiful and Virtuous <hi>Fotamenia;</hi> who, eſcaping the double Trap laid for her, by the Complotment of her luſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Maſter and the wicked Judge, Nobly ſcorn'd to ſave her Life, as She was offered, by denying Chriſt either with her Mouth, or by the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture unſuitable ill Life ſhe was tempted to. Whereupon ſhe was preſently condemn'd to be put ſtark naked into a great Braſs Veſſel full of boiling hot Pitch, there ready prepared for that purpoſe. But the heavenly Creature, hearing this Sentence, Thus apply'd her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the Judge; <hi>Since you are reſolved</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>That I ſhall die this ſort of Death, Let me entreat, nay, let me Conjure you by the very Head of your Emperour, which to you (I perceive) is of all Things moſt dear and ſacred, That you would not make an End of me preſently, nor all at once, but let me in leiſurely and by degrees, one Part after another; That ſo you may plainly perceive and know, what Torments, and how patiently too, that God whom I worſhip, and you know not, both can, and will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able me to undergo for His ſake.</hi> Which Requeſt of hers, being both <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pallad. in Lauſiac. c.</hi> 1.</note> eaſily granted, and punctually performed, ſhe bare that unſpeakable Torture for a whole Hour together, with unparallell'd Courage, till at length the Pitch bubling up to her very Neck, ſhe expir'd.</p>
               <p>Now I make no queſtion, but that ſhe firſt felt what ſhe ſaid, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it had been impoſſible, that ever ſhe could have ſaid ſo under thoſe Circumſtances; and much more, that ſhe could ever have ſo made good her Challenge. The bare Conſideration, methinks, of ſuch a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and ſuch a Martyrdom, ſhould be enough to convert, even the greateſt Atheiſt, and to extort from him alſo a Confeſſion, That herein muſt needs be the Finger. or rather indeed the Arm of God.</p>
               <p>But I proceed to the miraculous Puniſhments divinely inflicted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſeveral of the contrary behaviour: Where, paſſing by ſuch of them, as ſometimes immediately followed upon thoſe other juſt Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the Church in General, I ſhall, ſtill more cloſely, confining my ſelf to the Subject in hand, take notice only what followed of this kind upon this particular Sin of Diſſmulation or Denial. Now, if the firſt remarkable Judgment inflicted in the very Infancy of the Goſpel, was that upon <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphira,</hi> ſo wonderfully ſpoken to Death by St. <hi>Peter,</hi> for their Diſſimulation, in endeavouring to be thought to have done, what really they had not, and that in a Matter of good too; where <hi>to ſeem to be,</hi> is no fault at all, provided we really be ſo alſo; What ſhall we then think of thoſe, how faulty and obnoxious muſt we needs ſuppoſe them, who endeavour the ſame in
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:45693:29"/>
an evil Matter, whereto deſire <hi>to ſeem,</hi> as well as <hi>to be,</hi> has in it ſelf alſo a diſtinct Faultineſs? For tho' Piety may, yet Wickedneſs can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be wholly counterfeited. Here, only to <hi>deſire to ſeem,</hi> is alſo <hi>to be</hi> in ſome proportion. Whoſoever can once find in his heart to court it, muſt alſo at the ſame time, well deſerve the Reputation of it: For to endeavour to be thought bad, is actually to become ſo in a great meaſure; ſince 'tis always evil, not to avoid (as much as poſſible) the very Appearance of Evil.</p>
               <p>But we want not Variety of more direct Examples in the Writings of the Primitive Fathers. <hi>Tertullian</hi> acquaints us with a Woman, who, <note place="margin">Tertul. lib. de ſpect.</note> ſo far only complying with the Pagan Idolatries, as to go to their publick Theatre, returned thence poſſeſs'd with an unclean Spirit; who being in Exorciſm, expoſtulated with, how he durſt ſet upon one of the Faithful? Boldly reply'd, that he did no more therein, than what of Right belong'd to him; ſince he found her within his own Territories.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> likewiſe, ſpeaking of the Wonderful Prodigies happning to thoſe, who in the time of Perſecution, had prevaricated from their Profeſſion, relates ſeveral very memorable Stories; which I ſhall give you (as near as I can) in his own Words. <hi>If</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſome unbelieve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Cyprian <hi>lib. de Lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>People give leſs Credit to what is ſtill to come, let them be terrified, at leaſt, with what has actually for the preſent happened. Behold, how many remarkable Puniſhments of thoſe who have deny'd, have we our ſelves ſeen with our eyes? How many of their unhappy Ends do we ſtill lament? Even here they cannot go wholly without Puniſhment, tho' the Day of Puniſhment be not yet come. But in the mean time ſome are chaſtiſed, that others may be thereby amended; For the Examples belong to all, whilſt the Torments to a few only. One of thoſe, who of their own accord went up to the Capitol to deny the Faith, after he had done ſo, was preſently ſtruck dumb. The Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment began from that part, from whence the Crime began; ſo that he was wholly unable to ask Pardon, who now wanted the uſe of Speech, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to ſue for Mercy. Another of the Female Sex, being then in the Bath (for this was ſtill wanting to her former Crimes, that ſhe ſhould preſently betake her ſelf to the Bath, who had ſo lately forfeited the Grace of that Viial Laver of Baptiſm) There the unclean Creature, forthwith poſſeſs'd with an unclean Spirit, fell down to the ground; with her Teeth tore her own Tongue, with which ſhe had ſo wickedly either fed, or ſpoken; After the Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Food had once been taken in, the Fury of her Mouth was armed to its own Deſtruction: She became her own Executioner; nor could ſhe ſurvive long afterwards; but, grievouſly tormented with intolerable Pains in her Bowels, breath'd out her laſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After theſe, the holy Man immediately adds hereto three or four other Prodigies of the like Nature: ſome of his own Knowledge, and ſuch of which he affirms himſelf to have been an eye-witneſs; and then concludes after this manner: <hi>Quam multi quotidie,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:45693:30"/>
                  <hi>daily, neglecting to do Penance for their Denial, or to confeſs the Guilt of their Crime, are fill'd with ſuch unclean Spirits? How many diſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Mind, even to downright Diſtraction, are perfectly overwhelm'd with the Rage of their own Madneſs? Nor need we deſcend to the ſeveral Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtrophes of every one in particular; ſince by the manifold Ruines of the World, the Puniſhments of the ſeveral Offences are no leſs various, than the Multitude of the Offenders themſelves is numerous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this of St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> we may alſo add, that of <hi>Theodoret,</hi> who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms us, That <hi>Julian,</hi> the Uncle of <hi>Julian</hi> the Emperour, having, (to gain favour with that Apoſtate) deny'd the Chriſtian Faith, ſoon after fell into a ſtrange Diſeaſe, which ſo eat up his very Bowels with putrefaction, that he could no more void his Excrements, according <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Theod. l.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. 12.</note> to the uſual courſe of Nature, but only through that polluted Mouth, with which he had deny'd his Saviour: Even himſelf being ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly convinced before he died, that this was the immediate Hand of God upon him, for his Apoſtacy and Perſecutions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nicephorus</hi> likewiſe tells us of one <hi>Heron</hi> a Biſhop, who, having <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Niceph. l.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 29.</note> been guilty of the ſame Crime, ſuffer'd the ſame divine Puniſhment, which made him ſo odious and intolerable a Spectacle, that he was caſt out of doors into the High-way, where he ended his Days, of all Men unpitied.</p>
               <p>The ſame Author alſo ſpeaks of one <hi>Theotecaus,</hi> who, after his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacy, had all his Fleſh turn'd into Corruption and Worms, by the continual Bitings of which, he firſt loſt his Eyes, and then through Extremity of Pain and Anguiſh, growing perfectly diſtracted, bit off and devour'd his own Tongue, and ſo ended his preſent, to go ſtill to far greater Torments.</p>
               <p>In ſhort; How extreamly ſhameful is the Sin, and how Infinitly great the danger of ſuch Denials or even Diſſimulations in the Caſe of our Religion, may no leſs ſufficiently appear from thoſe miraculous means which God ſometimes makes uſe of, in order to recall and reeſtabliſh ſuch Offenders. <note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ex Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taph.</hi> 14. <hi>Decemb. St. Sur. To. S. poſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta Thyr ſi &amp; ſociorum citante Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron. vol.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 54.</note> One very remarkable Inſtance of which kind we have in <hi>Apollonius,</hi> a certain Reader in the Church at <hi>Thebais;</hi> who, terrify'd by the proſpect of enſuing Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and yet deſiring to avoid a formal down-right Denial con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived to bribe one <hi>Philemon</hi> a <hi>Pagan</hi> friend, by the gift of four Pieces of Gold, that, changing his Habit, he might counterfeit the Perſon of <hi>Apollonius,</hi> and ſo, among others, Offer Sacrifice before the Magiſtrate. But this Heathen, being of a ſudden divinely en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened in his Mind, and warmed by the Example of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, inſtead of acting the Perſon of another Man, repreſented his own in good Earneſt; and having openly profeſſed his belief in Chriſt, and being exquiſitly Tormented for ſo doing, ſtill again and again conſtantly perſiſted in affirming the ſame thing, till he was at laſt honoured with the Glorious Crown of Martyrdom. By
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:45693:30"/>
whoſe unexpected Example alſo <hi>Apollonius,</hi> being much Encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and even aſhamed out of his former Cowardice, afterwards with a Conſtant Mind underwent the ſame Combate.</p>
               <p>Nay, Providence has been ſometimes pleaſed to declare the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Rewards of Martyrs, and the Puniſhment of Deſertors even by a Viſion from Heaven ſo manifeſt to their very Tormentors, that they have become Confeſſors thereupon, to which purpoſe in one of <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Baſil. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. in</hi> 40. <hi>Martyres.</hi>
                  </note> St. <hi>Baſils</hi> Orations, we have this following Relation. In the leſſer <hi>Armenia,</hi> under the Perſecution of <hi>Licinius,</hi> forty Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Soldiers were condemned to die, for their reſolute Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt, by being expoſed quite Naked to the Extremities of rigid Cold and Froſt; yet ſo as that any of them might, upon their Denial of their Faith, retire into a Warm convenient Place, near hand prepared to receive them, upon that Condition only. After they had for ſome time bravely undergone the extreme Severity, one of the <hi>Pagan</hi> Officers, who was conveniently placed hard by, to ſee this Sentence duely Executed upon them, obſerved a Company of Angels deſcending, and placing ſeveral Crowns upon the Head of each of the whole Number, one of them onely accepted; who, preſently afterwards being weary of the Tryal and denying Chriſt, was ſuffered to Retreat into the Warm Receptacle, but preſently dyed thereupon. The Officer himſelf Powerfully convinced by this Miraculous Viſion, openly confeſſed himſelf a Chriſtian, and boldly ſtepping into the Place of the Apoſtate, ſupply'd the deficiency of the firſt Number, and with the reſt received his Crown of Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
               <p>Now, tho' all theſe Prodigies and many more, which might be ſtill produced of the like Nature, have been, and are ſtill ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, when well conſidered, to convince even a heathen Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vator; yet we, who believe already and have received the Holy Scripture for our Rule of Faith, need not wholly depend upon ſuch Arguments, as having this other ſtill more ſure Word of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſy for our Confirmation in this Point. Which ſhall be my Fifth Conſideration, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:45693:31"/>
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How Expreſs and Poſitive the Scripture is for the abſolute Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of ſuch a Conſtant Confeſſion upon all Occaſions, and how directly it Forbids and Condemns the contrary Denials and Diſſimulations.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>WHAT can be more plain in this Caſe, than the Words of our Great Lord and Maſter to his Diſciples after His Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection? Act. 1. 8. <hi>Ye ſhall be Witneſſes unto me, both in Jeruſalem, and in all Judea, and in Samaria, and unto the uttermoſt Parts of the Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But had his Diſciples, whilſt under their Tryals and manifold Perſecutions, deny'd Chriſt with their Mouths, tho' they had ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly acknowledged him in their Hearts, they would have been found therein no better than falſe and lying Witneſſes, and indeed none of Chriſt's, but the Devil's Martyrs or Witneſſes, who is a Lyar from the Beginning. And however peculiar this Command might be to the Apoſtles and firſt Diſciples of our Saviour, who alone had the Opportunity of being immediate Eye-Witneſſes of His Reſurrection; yet elſewhere the Injunction is General and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Exception indiſpenſably obliging all Chriſtians in all Ages, as a Duty ſo abſolutely neceſſary, that upon the performance or neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect thereof, will depend our Eternal Happineſs or Miſery, our being owned as his Genuine Diſciples, or our being finally reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as Caſt-awaies at the laſt Great day.</p>
               <p>For thoſe are the Expreſs Words which flowed alſo from the ſame Bleſſed Lips of Truth. <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. 32. Whoſoever ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs me before Men, him will I confeſs alſo before my Father which is in Heaven; But whoſoever ſhall deny me before Men, him will I alſo deny before my Father which is in Heaven.</p>
               <p>Upon which place, thus ſaith the Comment of that Antient and Learned Author, commonly going under the Name of St. <hi>Chryſoſtom, The Faith of the Heart will no more avail, without the Confeſſion of the Mouth, than the Confeſſion of the Mouth will, without the Faith of the Heart. And if it muſt be enough for Chriſt that we know him, tho' we Confeſs him not before Men; therefore, it muſt be enough for us alſo, that he knows us, tho' at the laſt he Confeſs us not before Men. 'Tis not ſufficient for any, to ſay, I retain the Truth in my Heart, and in the mean time diſown it before the World. And therefore he does not ſay; He that confeſſeth me in his heart,</hi> but, <hi>He that confeſſeth me before Men.</hi> And again, Mark 8. 38. <hi>Whoſoever ſhall be aſhamed of me, and of my Words, in this Adulterous and Sinful Generation, of him</hi>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:45693:31"/>
                  <hi>alſo ſhall the Son of Man be aſhamed, when he cometh in the Glory of his Father, with the Holy Angels.</hi> Conſonant to this alſo is what St. <hi>Paul</hi> aſſures us, Rom. 10. 10. <hi>With the Heart Man believeth unto Righteouſneſs, and with the Mouth Confeſſion is made unto Salvation;</hi> And 2 Tim. 2. 12. <hi>If we deny him, he will deny us.</hi> The ſame A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle likewiſe earneſtly Exhorts Timothy, <hi>Not to be aſhamed of the Teſtimony of our Lord, but to be partaker of the Afflictions of the Goſpel.</hi> 2 Tim. 1. 8. In like manner he plainly intimates and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily ſuppoſeth, <hi>That he that denyeth the Faith is much worſe than an Infidel.</hi> 1 Tim. 5. 8. So we are aſſured that it is the Expreſs will of God, <hi>That every Tongue ſhomld confeſs, that Jeſus Chriſt is the Lord, to the Glory of God the Father:</hi> Phil. 2. 11.</p>
               <p>That Apoſtle likewiſe, who by ſad Experience was but too well acquainted with the Hainouſneſs of the Crime, and had wept bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly for his own Denial, does being afterwards converted, (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his Lords Injunction) effectually endeavour to ſtrengthen his Brethren, whilſt he commands us in the name of God, <hi>To be ready always</hi> (that is, even in the midſt of Terrours, and under the greateſt dangers of Perſecution, as plainly appears by the verſe foregoing) <hi>to give an Anſwer to every Man, that asketh us a reaſon of the Hope that is in us.</hi> 1 Pet. 3. 15. Which place of Scripture can no otherwiſe be underſtood, than as neceſſarily requiring our Readineſs at all times, not to palliate or conceal, but openly to confeſs our Faith: For all our Hope being grounded upon our Faith, it is impoſſible for us to give any Reaſon of the firſt, without gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving alſo a reaſon of the Second; And as impoſſible to give any Reaſon or Account at all of either, without making a plain con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion and acknowledgment thereof. To Conclude; In the Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of St. <hi>John,</hi> amongſt other hainous Criminals, <hi>Idolaters, and all that love or make a lie,</hi> are perfectly excluded the holy City, and have their Portion allotted them <hi>in the lake, which burneth with Fire and Brimſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne; which is the ſecond Death:</hi> Whereas <hi>he that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh,</hi> (that is, by a conſtant confeſſion) is there promiſed <hi>the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance of all things.</hi> Rev. 21. 7, 8. and Rev. 22. 15. And in the Epiſtle to the Church of <hi>Pergamos,</hi> our Lord himſelf highly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves of <hi>Antipas</hi> by name, for his dying for the Faith, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends that Church alſo for her conſtancy therein, in theſe Words; <hi>Thou holdeſt fast my name, and haſt not denied my Faith, even in thoſe days wherein Antipas was my faithfull witneſs, who was ſlain among</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>you, where Satan dwelleth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have here all along (you ſee) confined my ſelf only to Expreſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands and prohibitions in the Caſe, together with the Rewards and Penalties, the Divine Approbation or Diſlike, no leſs expreſly ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify'd and annexed, upon the performance or Neglect of what is ſo required. All which are ſo many direct Proofs of the abſolute Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of this Duty of confeſſion. But ſhould I alſo undertake par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:45693:32"/>
to inſiſt upon all thoſe other numerous places in holy writ, which either ſuppoſe or imply the ſame obligation, by a moſt natural and unavoidable Conſequence; I ſhould then oblige my ſelf to tranſcribe (well nigh) the greater part of the whole New Teſtament. For indeed the very Nature and Genius, the whole Tenour and Current of rhe Goſpel runs this way. All thoſe multiply'd Precepts and Doctrines about Patience and Self-denial, obout Suffering and Taking up the Croſs, about our Readineſs to lay down our Lives, and not to fear thoſe who can kill the Body; about Chriſtian Simplicity and Love without Diſſimulation, Giving no Offence, and abſtaining from all Appearance of Evil; All theſe Precepts, Cautions, and Exhortations, and innumerable more of the like kind, are either chiefly for the ſake of, or moſt cloſely im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the Abſolute Neceſſity of this prime Duty which we are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing of; ſince otherwiſe they muſt needs be either wholly in vain, or to very little purpoſe ſo much inculcated. So that did it not ſo apparently gratify the ſinful Inclinations of corrupt Fleſh and Blood, in delivering Men all at once, from ever taſting the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing Severities of the Croſs, one would think it impoſſible, that it ſhould ever enter into the Heart of any to affirm, That, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing their Faith within their own Breaſt, they might innocently deny the ſame with their Mouth, or any other way diſſemble it by their Actions. Since 'tis moſt evident, there's no other Crime whatſoever, the Lawfulneſs of which they could contrive to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, with greater defyance of the moſt broad-faced Light of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture to the contrary. When in the mean time they have nothing to colour over or diſguiſe the deadly Poyſon, but one or two paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages only in all the Bible, and thoſe too moſt miſerably wreſted and abuſed by them. Which again carries me onſtill to the diſtinct Task of a ſixth Enquiry or Conſideration, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How falſe and fooliſh are the pretended Grounds and Reaſons, upon which ſuch Diſſemblers endeavour to Juſtify and esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh their contrary Opinion and Practice; together with the many abſurd conſequences and moſt monſtrous Inconveniences of diverſe kinds neceſſarily following thereupon.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>NOW after that of their moſt beloved <hi>Naa-man,</hi> their only place ſeems to be that of <hi>Prov.</hi> 23. 26. or ſome other ſuch like it, wherein we have it ſignify'd, That God ſees, and chiefly regards Men's Hearts. From whence they boldly infer, That if
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:45693:32"/>
they do but take Care to keep their Hearts for God, by ſafely wrapping up a right belief therein, they may then venture with their Mouths, or by any other action of their outward Man, ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to deny the ſame: Or elſe provided they can but ſecretly keep up in their Hearts a rectify'd Intention, they may then very ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly both be preſent at, and with their lips join, or at leaſt ſeem to join with others, in ſuch Prayers, the matter of which is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe acknowledged to be directly againſt their Duty, and the Divine command.</p>
               <p>Now they who thus teach the Lawfulneſs of Diſſimulation, ſeem even in their very ſo doing, actually to Diſſemble with us, whilſt they teach that, which they themſelves do no way really be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve; and yet would be thought to do ſo, merely out of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign the better to ſecure their Reputation, to cover the ſhame of their own baſe Actions ſo agreeable thereto, and as the only expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to excuſe and take off the odium of their foul Hypocriſie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong their friends, when they happen to be reproved for it by them. So that we have great reaſon to ſuſpect, that ſuch Men do not ſay as they think, when they ſay, they think it lawful, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny what they think. However, this Aſſertion ſeems, in the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral conſequence thereof, to contradict, fall foul upon, and even overturn its own ſelf; at leaſt, to take away the very foundation of its finding Credit with any other Perſon, whom they can never reaſonably induce to think, That they ſay true in what they affirm, when they affirm, That they believe it lawful for them ſo to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny their belief. Since how can we ever be ſecure (according to their own Principles) that they may not as well lie, and in this very Caſe, falſely ſay, that they do believe, what they really do not, as in the other Caſe falſely deny their belief of what they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally do believe? But paſſing from the Perſons, to the thing it ſelf, and leaving them to believe, or not believe, as they will; the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended ground and main reaſon for what they ſo maintain, I'm ſure, is altogether falſe and frivolous.</p>
               <p>For, in the firſt place, it is by no means true, That God has Mens Hearts in ſuch Caſes, or that they do, or can therewith at the ſame time truly ſerve him. Which I'm confident, will very eaſily appear to any one, who (not reſting in the mere empty ſound of Words, without any ſenſe at all) ſhall only well conſider, what that phraſe does truly ſignify and import.</p>
               <p>Now God is then (and can only then be) truely ſaid to have our Hearts when he has the Affections thereof, in ſuch a due Fear, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, and Love of him above all things, as may effectually diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe us, to endeavour to pleaſe him in all the ways of his own direction to that purpoſe; that is, in one Word, by keeping of His Commandments, whatſoever preſent loſs or hardſhip it may coſt us for ſo doing. So that when we can knowingly venture to diſpleaſe
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:45693:33"/>
him by acting contrary thereto, it muſt be alwaies for the ſake of ſomething elſe, which we at the ſame time really more fear, love, and prefer before our Maker; and which therefore (whatſoever we may pretend to the contrary) has our Hearts in good earneſt, and not the Living Lord who ſearcheth them. Such Hypocrites indeed do allow God (what they cannot help) ſomething of their <hi>Heads;</hi> ſince their Underſtandings ſeem rightly enough informed, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what they ought to do: But their <hi>Hearts</hi> he is far enough from ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, whilſt they can find in their Hearts, to act ſo quite contrary to that Knowledge. Unleſs we can ſuppoſe, That they who ſin moſt againſt their own Knowledge or Conſcience, may be ſaid therein, the moſt to give God their Heart. Beſides, the very reaſon why God ſo chiefly requires the heart, is, becauſe whenſoever he has that truely, he muſt of neceſſity have therewith alſo the whole Man; whilſt every Thought, Word, and Action is naturally reduced there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by into a ſuitable Obedience. So that 'tis wholly impoſſible to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate or put aſunder, what God and Nature have ſo cloſely conjoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Whereſoever there is really the <hi>Heart</hi> of a Sincere Diſciple, there will alſo be the <hi>Lips</hi> of a confeſſour, upon occaſion; the Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of our Bleſſed Saviour being no leſs true in the good, than in the bad Senſe, That <hi>out of the Abundance of the Heart, the Mouth ſpeaketh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſtill in the Second place, were it poſſible in ſuch Caſes, That God could truly have the Heart, yet that alone by no means would be ſufficient: For tho' we may, indeed, find that this (upon the grounds already ſpecify'd) is the main thing regarded by him; yet where do we read, that this is the only thing requiſite? Who is it that hath exempted the outward Man from the Juriſdiction of him who equally Created both Parts for his own Glory? We find, its true, ſome perſons, and what kind of ones withal they were, whom the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> brings in paunting it to this purpoſe; yet who can juſtly ſay, or without the higheſt Preſumption, That <hi>his Tongue is his own,</hi> to do with it what he pleaſeth?</p>
               <p>Did we indeed conſiſt of nothing elſe but naked Spirit, it might then be perhaps, ſufficient <hi>to ſanctify the Lord God in our hearts</hi> only: But ſince we are cloathed with Fleſh, and <hi>he hath given us a body, as it hath pleaſed him,</hi> he juſtly expects, as well as expreſly requires; <hi>That we ſhould glorify him, in our body,</hi> no leſs than <hi>in our ſpirit, which are</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 6. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>both the Lord's.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſtill, as this perficious Hereſie is (you ſee) thus utterly falſe and groundleſs, in what it pretends to for its ſupport; ſo the abſurd conſequences and inconveniences thereof are prodigiouſly both great and numerous.</p>
               <p>For firſt, were what is ſo pretended, indeed ſufficient for the purpoſe, as I have already proved it far enough from being ſo; yet where the Love of the Truth is ſo very feeble, and that of the World
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:45693:33"/>
ſo ſtrong, that the Man can prevail with himſelf totally to deny his Faith in his Words and outward Actions, the faint remainders there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſtill ſecretly retained in his Heart, or head rather, muſt needs have ſo ſlender a hold in either, that they are very unlikely to be long-lived with him in ſo unſuitable an Habitation.</p>
               <p>Nay, they who can afford to make it once their Cuſtom, with the outward Man, to join, or but ſo much as to ſeem to join, with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in publick, in ſuch Service or Prayers, any part whereof they verily believe to be, as to the matter thereof, unlawful, and which in their Hearts they inwardly deteſt, there is very great danger of ſuch perſons coming by degrees, to be alſo inwardly reconciled thereto, and at laſt fully and totally to join with them in good earneſt.</p>
               <p>What befell <hi>Geneſius,</hi> who, by order of the Emperour <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> acting on the Theatre the part of a Chriſtian, with an intent to ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicule and expoſe that holy Profeſſion, was ſo ſuddenly changed, that, inſtead of ſo doing, he ſeriouſly profeſſed, and dyed for that Religion; as alſo what happen'd of the ſame nature to one <hi>Porphy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> another famous Actor alike employed by <hi>Julian</hi> to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: Theſe indeed are to be look'd upon as Events very extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary and miraculous. But that of the Wretch, ſpoken of by <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian,</hi> who acting the part of mad <hi>Ajax,</hi> was ſo forcibly carry'd away with the Affection, that himſelf became ever afterwards really diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted; is a thing far leſs ſtrange, and perhaps even in a natural way, fairly enough accountable. And however in a Moral ſenſe, there is no mere counterfeiting of an ill Man, without being ſo alſo in down-right earneſt. He that can once take upon him, or make it his buſineſs only to act the part of an Infidel, will eaſily learn to be an Original, and, acting the part to the very Life, will at laſt naturally become ſuch in reality, to all intents and purpoſes. 'Tis poſſible for a man to tell a lie ſo often, till at length, forgetting it to be ſo, he comes, no leſs than others, to give a real Credit thereto; beſides they are eaſily perſwaded to a total deſertion thereof, who never yet taſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed any thing of the pleaſures of Religion; which yet can never be truly reliſhed without Sincerity. So that what wonder is it, that they ſhould in the concluſion <hi>be given over to believe a lie, who at firſt received not the Truth in the love thereof?</hi> For 'tis difficult long to hold the <hi>Truth in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs:</hi> But having once <hi>put away a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> by ſuch ſhameful Tricks and Artifices, Men come naturally at length to make Shipwrack of their right Faith; which, whilſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they had it, could ſerve for no other purpoſe, but only to make them extremely reſtleſs and uneaſy, by continually upbraiding them with their quite contrary Hypocritical Practices.</p>
               <p>But ſtill, in the ſecond place, could ſuch Men be ſure, that they ſhould never proceed any farther, yet to endeavour to ſeem what they are not, and not to ſeem, what they are, being no other in it ſelf than formal down-right Hypocriſie; To conclude therefore, that they may go thus far ſafely, muſt neceſſarily imply their Belief of the no Neceſſity of that Sincerity, which the Goſpel every where ſo ſtrictly urges and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:45693:34"/>
above all things; and that Hypocriſie it ſelf is far from being really a thing ſo diſpleaſing to God, as 'tis there pretended, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented. Nay, whereas God has ſo expreſly declar'd, That our very beſt Performances are with him nothing at all worth, unleſs they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from and be accompanied with Sincerity; What height then of Preſumption and Blaſphemy muſt it needs be, to expect, That the groſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt Diſſimulation alone ſhould ſo effectually recommend Men to the Favour of the God of Truth, as that he ſhould pardon and excuſe them, for the very worſt Crime they could poſſibly contrive to commit, mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the ſake of, and becauſe it is Accompanied with, the moſt ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Lying and Hypocriſie?</p>
               <p>Beſides; This curſed Practice and Opinion ſeems to be founded in ſecret Atheiſm, and tacitly implies this other diſtinct Blaſphemy; That God is either not endued with ſufficient Power, or elſe not Good or Wiſe enough, to defend and ſupport Men in the due Obſervation of His own Laws, unleſs they ſometimes help him out, by their vile Lyes and Hypocriſie, and having a Recourſe to the ſhelter of Diſſimulation.</p>
               <p>Again; Whereas the Profeſſion of the true Religion is that, which, of all other things, we ought the moſt to Glory in and openly Triumph; ſince thereby we become truly Honourable our ſelves, in ſo glorifying our Creatour: We cannot therefore contrive more effectually to diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour both our ſelves and Him, nor caſt a worſe Reflection upon all His Attributes, than in baſely diſowning of our Faith; whilſt in ſo doing we neceſſarily affix this moſt diſgraceful Imputation upon the holy Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor thereof, as if he had revealed that to us, which we have good Reaſon, to conceal and be aſhamed of. And accordingly, ſuch De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nials are by Chriſt Himſelf expreſly call'd and accounted no better, than <hi>a being aſhamed of Him, and of His words.</hi> And what Thanks, think you, can be due to thoſe Men, who have Thus parted with the Total of their Religion, but only what they cannot yet help the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of? What they are aſhamed to own, and fain would, but cannot for the preſent yet get rid of? To proceed; in infers (quite contrary to our Saviour's Caution) great Boldneſs and Preſumption towards Heaven, and Hearts quite evoid of all due Fear of Him, who has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared Himſelf a Conſuming Fire to all ſuch Offenders, and Able to caſt both their Souls and Bodies into Hell; and yet at the ſame time a moſt cowardly and ſlaviſh Fear towards their Fellow-Mortals, whoſe Breath is in their Noſtrils, and whoſe Power at moſt, reacheth no farther than over the Carkaſs, and what belongs thereto; and even that too per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly limited and reſtrained, according to the Wiſdom and good Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Him, whom they ſo fondly deſpiſe in the Compariſon.</p>
               <p>And conſequently, in the next place, It argues them alſo no leſs void both of all true Love towards God, and Charity towards their Neighbour; Since, in both reſpects, what St. <hi>John</hi> has aſſur'd us, is moſt certain, That <hi>perfect love caſteth out all ſuch fear; whilſt he that ſo feareth, is far from being yet made perfect in love.</hi> For as our Fear is, ſo is alſo our Love. And whoever yet prevail'd with himſelf to deny his Faith, unleſs tempted thereto by ſomething of the World, the Loſs
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:45693:34"/>
of which he firſt more fear'd, than the Loſs of God's Favour; and which therefore he more lov'd, than God Himſelf, and ſacrilegiouſly preferr'd before Him? But he who ſo loves the World or any thing therein, The Love of the Father is not truly in him. And then how can they love their Neighbours, who love not God, for whoſe ſake alone it is they do ſo, whoſoever truly love them? Or what Charity can there be in thoſe, who, inſtead of being ready (as they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd) to lay down their very Lives for the Spiritual Welfare of their Brethren, can be contented in ſo high a manner, to grieve and offend, and (as much as in them lies) by their Scandalous Examples of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial, even to deſtroy thoſe for whom Chriſt died?</p>
               <p>Farthermore; This monſtrous Tenet is directly contrary to the very Nature, and diſſolves at once the whole Frame of Chriſtianity, by ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly making void the Doctrine of the Croſs, and all neceſſity of our ever ſuffering as Chriſtians; and conſequently takes away in a great meaſure, all occaſion, and ſuperſedes the uſe and exerciſe of all thoſe highly commendable Vertues, of Zeal and Chriſtian Courage, of Faith and Patience, of Meekneſs and Forgiving Enemies, together with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Precepts and Injunctions of the like nature, which now make up ſo very conſiderable a part of the Goſpel. For what Occaſion or Opportunity can there be, in this reſpect, for the Exerciſe of any of thoſe Graces, when there is not the leaſt Danger or Neceſſity of ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? And how can there be any Neceſſity of this, if we may lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay or do any thing, in order to prevent it? For no Man being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with the Ability of looking into another mans heart, if we may therefore ſecretly retain our Faith there only, and yet deny the ſame with our Mouths, and Actions, and can conſtantly continue to do ſo, we muſt needs be perfectly ſafe from all Danger of Perſecution upon that Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count: Since the greateſt Tyrant in the World, can poſſibly require no more of us, but muſt and will reſt ſatisfy'd hereupon.</p>
               <p>Again therefore; It neceſſarily condemns the Practice, and ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully reviles the precious Memory of all the Glorious Confeſſors and Holy Martyrs; who, might this Doctrine once obtain for truth, muſt be no longer accounted Martyrs, but even the worſt of Murderers, who could afford ſo raſhly to caſt away their Lives needleſly and to no purpoſe, and offer up to God the mere Sacrifice of Fools. Nay, even all thoſe alſo, who have conſtantly payed ſuch deſerved Reſpect and Defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the Memories of theſe <hi>Heroes,</hi> that is, the whole Church of God in general, muſt juſtly be condemned therein, as guilty of Worſe than ſuperſtitious Vanity, and be thought to have out-done even that ridiculous Folly of the very <hi>Turks,</hi> who are ſaid to believe a ſort of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credneſs in, and to ſhew no ſmall Veneration towards the Perſons of Fools and Madmen.</p>
               <p>Another monſtrous Conſequence thereof ſtill is, That it utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys the main uſe of Language; defeats the very end, for which our Tongues and Lips, and other Organs of Speech were chiefly beſtowed upon us. Which was to enable us more certainly to convey the true inward Sentiments of our minds to one another; to diſcover our ſeveral Abilities or defects; how well, or ill we are inwardly ſtored
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:45693:35"/>
and provided with the Treaſures of Belief and Knowledge, and other Graces; and ſo accordingly edifie and ſupply, confirm and ſtrengthen each other, by receiving, or Communicating mutual helps and aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances. But now, if Men are not obliged to ſpeak truly, what they believe and know; but may be permitted the Liberty of doing the quite contrary, then this admirable Priviledge and Prerogative of Speech, with which Man is endued above any of the Inferior Creatures, muſt not any longer be really ſo accounted of, but be looked upon as given men far worſe than in vain, even to their no ſmall Damage and diſadvantage; ſo that they had far better have been without it. Since, when thus perverted, they muſt either not rely upon it at all, and ſo be ſure never to receive any Benefit thereby; or elſe be fatally miſguided, and eternally deceived and abuſed, if they do depend upon it, as we are naturally inclined.</p>
               <p>To which Inconveniency I may therefore add in the next place, That this damnable Hereſie (if yet it deſerves not to be called by a worſe and more comprehenſive name) does tend wholly to ſubvert all foundation and Poſſibility of a Church viſible, and conſequently of of our Communion therewith, and the Benefits therefrom. For what manner of poſſibility could there be, of ever diſcovering, either where the Church is, or that there is indeed any ſuch thing at all as the Church, were all the Members of it not obliged to any particular Mark or Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, whereby to diſtinguiſh them from the reſt of the World: But inſtead of any ſufficient Sign or Indication of their Faith and Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſhould make it their Buſineſs to hide and conceal themſelves, by joining in their Words and external Actions either with <hi>Hereticks</hi> or with <hi>Pagans</hi> and <hi>Infidels?</hi> Among all the ſeveral Religions that are, or ever yet have been in the World, I know not of any one, but what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires its ſeveral Votaries and Proſelytes, not to deny, but plainly to own their general Belief and Practice. And <hi>for all People</hi> openly <hi>to walk</hi> (as the Prophet <hi>Micah</hi> has it) <hi>every one in the Name of their God,</hi> is a thing both uſual and natural. None ever yet aſſerted the contrary Liberty of Denial, but ſome few onely (as I have already ſhewn) of the very worſt of <hi>Hereticks,</hi> or indeed <hi>Atheiſts</hi> rather, who ſeem there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in profeſſed Enemies to Piety it ſelf, and to have deſigned thereby, if poſſible, to root up all Religion in general out of the World; to which purpoſe nothing could be more naturally adapted. But the Chriſtian Inſtitution above any other whatſoever, has this peculiar to it ſelf, that it more ſtrictly requires this publick confeſſion of all who embrace it, ſo as to be always in a Readineſs to Die, much rather than deny the Faith. And how many Millions have actually done ſo upon that ſcore? Whoſe <hi>Blood</hi> has conſtantly proved <hi>the ſeed of the Church,</hi> to propagate and preſerve it: Cou'd the <hi>Pagan</hi> Perſecutors but once have perſwaded Chriſtians to have acted otherwiſe in general, they would then have effected their own buſineſs which they aimed at; that is, The Church had been deſtroyed, and Chriſtianity long ſince utterly Extinguiſhed. For if every Man may keep his own Faith ſecretly to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in his own Heart only, without being obliged any way to declare
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:45693:35"/>
the ſame either by Words or Actions, what poſſibility is there, That either Poſterity or any others who are yet without it, ſhould ever be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with, or come to the Knowledge of the Truth? Any one Age of Perſecution muſt, in this Caſe, neceſſarily put an end to the Faith, and make it be ſure to die and periſh from off the Earth, together with the Race of ſuch ſecret and conceal'd Believers. And however in the mean time, this quite defeats all the ends of Religious Society, and cuts Men off from all the Benefits of Church-Communion. For if the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Profeſſion of our Faith be not neceſſary, neither is it neceſſary to be in Communion with any Church at all; with which we cannot be in Communion without ſuch Profeſſion; nor conſequently is it neceſſary that we ſhould, as Members thereof partake of the publick Prayers, Holy Word, or Sacraments; ſince all theſe are as ſo many Profeſſions of the Faith; which, according to this impious Doctrine, we may very ſafely be without. Then alſo the Governours of the Church, whom Chriſt has entruſted with the Power of the Keys, have that Truſt given them in vain: Since, according to this, 'tis impoſſible they ſhould rightly uſe them, unleſs they were able certainly to diſcover Mens Hearts; ſince otherwiſe they muſt needs Cenſure unjuſtly in excluding any from the Church even for the Denial of Chriſt, or for Blaſphemy it ſelf, before they were ſure, that the Heart went alſo along with the Mouth.</p>
               <p>They who are conſtantly preſent at any publick Worſhip, are juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſumed thereupon, heartily to join therein, and when they really do not, are thought to put a Notorious Mockery upon God and the whole Society: But yet if we may lawfully play the Hypocrites with the outward Man, then Words and Actions muſt paſs for nothing; Nor will it be poſſible ever to ſatisfy others, of what Communion we are, or to be our ſelves ſatisfyed of this concerning others. But whilſt we think, that we are amongſt very Devout Orthodox Profeſſors, and expect to have our Prayers helped on, and rendered more acceptable and effectual by the united Fervour of many Brethren, we may be all the while very widely miſtaken, and moſt of the Congregation may be either <hi>Socinians, Turks,</hi> or <hi>Infidels,</hi> who tho' they ſeem to uſe all the ſame Words with us, do yet in their Hearts pray the quite contrary.</p>
               <p>Again; if this were indeed allowable, a Man might then indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly go to all, and yet altogether in vain to any place of publick Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; Since by ſo doing he could neither receive, nor Communicate any farther Benefit, than what might equally acrew to him, in the private performances of his Cloſet only. So that this principle utterly confounds and ſubverts all neceſſary Communion, putting every Man into a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of abſolute Independency indeed, wholly ſeparate in matters of Religion from the reſt of Mankind; in a Word, into ſuch a State, as a Man would be in, were there no other Perſon in the whole World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides him. Nor can ſuch Men ever have any motive to behave themſelves otherwiſe, excepting only upon a Politick account; which may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, now and then induce them to make a ſtep to ſome Religious Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, or a ſmoaking Temple, to avoid ſome Temporal Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience only, or to Complement and gain Favour with ſome haughty
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:45693:36"/>
Potentate. For by the dreadful Liberty of this impious <hi>Dogma,</hi> Men may (according to the common Proverb, and perhaps beyond the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of it) not only, when they are at <hi>Rome,</hi> do as they do at <hi>Rome,</hi> but likewiſe upon occaſion, chant it in a <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Synagogue, or Sacrifice in a <hi>Pagan</hi> Temple; nay, proſtrating themſelves, and (according to the uſual manner) zealouſly knocking their Foreheads againſt the Pave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of a <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Moſque, may ſafely ſeem to join with thoſe Miſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants in the verbal Repetition of their Prayers, wherein ſometimes they Blaſpheme our Saviour; and yet all this while ſuffer no Impairment of their Chriſtianity, provided only they take Care, to keep themſelves all along good thorow-paced Hypocrites, not minding what themſelves ſay, nor letting their Hearts go along therewith. Now tho' this, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, is ſuch a ſcandalous and aſtoniſting ſort of Liberty, as may well make the Heart of any Sincere Chriſtian tremble at the very thoughts thereof; ſome there are notwithſtanding, who, ſeeming to be affright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the bare hearing of it, are yet in a far greater Readineſs and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration to make uſe of the ſame upon Occaſion, than them ſelves can now be well aware of. For how many are there in the World, who can allow themſelves, not only to be preſent at, but to ſeem and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to be thought, to join alſo in ſuch ſorts of Petitions, as they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge to be directly againſt their Duty, and in which they cannot inwardly and in their Hearts agree? Now as, it may be, there was a time, when ſuch Men were far from believing, that ever they could have prevailed with themſelves to make ſo large a ſtep; ſo, having once advanced ſo far, 'tis not very eaſy for them, to know certainly, where they would ſtop at laſt; or how much farther ſtill they might be carryed on, by the ſame Temporal motives, upon a ſufficient try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and occaſion. For tho' totally to deny the Faith, and to change ones Religion ſo all at once, may appear at firſt very horrid and abominable, yet they who, againſt their Conſcience, can now afford ſo deliberatly to play the Hypocrites in any one particular, will, by degrees, be at laſt eaſily enough reconciled even to ſuch a general Apoſtaſy. The only ſafe-guard that can rationally ſecure us from any one, will alſo ſecure us from all hainous Tranſgreſſions; and that is the Conſideration of God's having forbid the ſame. This Bulwark once thrown down, as it muſt needs be by thoſe, who knowingly indulge themſelves in the Habit of any one ſin, and much more in the Habit of Hypocriſie, there is an open way made, for any other Wickedneſs to aſſault and take place with us. And they who, notwithſtanding the confeſſed unlawfulneſs thereof, can find in their hearts to join in one forbidden particular, what can hinder but that they ſhould do ſo in another, and ſo on in a hundred, till they come at laſt to the moſt ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous height imaginable? The only reaſon why ſuch Men are ſo apt to think that they ſhould not do ſo, is only becauſe they are now able, to look upon the extreme Horror of the thing without the Abatements and Diſguiſes of prejudice; as being at preſent under no manner of Temptation thereto, from the like powerful motives of Worldly Fear or Intereſt. However, where all Men may ſafely take the Liberty (as all may if any) to communicate any where, or no where, if they pleaſe, this muſt neceſſarily put an end to all Church Diſcipline, and ſo at the ſame time, to all regular Communion.</p>
               <p>But ſtill, to all the foregoing ill Conſequences of a more publick Nature, give me leave to add one or two more immediatly relating to the very Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of ſuch Offenders.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:45693:36"/>
The firſt whereof is, That, beſides their hazarding Eternity thereby, they are far from being ſure, that by this means they can long ſecure to themſelves even that Temporal Eaſe and Safety, which is the only thing they aim at: But have on the contrary great reaſon to fear, that ſuch Hypocriſie will at length even in this World betray them to far greater Inconveniences, than what they hoped to avoid thereby. For tho' this courſe may for a while ſecure them from ſuch dangers; yet when once their Hypocriſie comes to be diſcovered (as, firſt or laſt, it generally is) ſuch Perſons are moſt of all expoſed, and abhorred by all Men. Who, whilſt they are apt ſecretly to Venerate thoſe that plainly profeſs their diſſent from them, and are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſuffer for the fame; yet naturally treat and look upon ſuch vile diſſemblers with the higheſt deteſtation. And however in the maen time, for them to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to act continually a moſt unnatural part; to have a conſtant Guard upon themſelves, leſt any unwary Word or Action ſhould betray them; to force their Bodies (as Hypocrites muſt do) to be always drudging of it, without, and againſt their Souls; To lie under conſtant Fears and Apprehenſions of a diſcovery, like a day of Judgment; all this muſt needs create a life ſufficiently unpleaſant, ſcarce worth the living, and cannot but be eſteemed even in it ſelf ſo Severe a Puniſhment, that whatſoever elſe can be got thereby, is a dear purchace. And yet after all, if ever they do chance to have their Hypocriſie detected, they can look for no other, than to be treated with the moſt extraordinary ſeverities. For tho' (as I formerly obſerved) the greateſt Tyrant muſt be for the preſent ſatisfy'd with a man's plain Denial of his Faith; yet, if afterwards by any chance trip, ſuch a one can clearly diſcover, that he has been only mocked therein, what ſuitable Effects muſt then be expected to follow from the redoubled Rage and Fury of him, who finds, that, inſtead of a ſubſtantial Convert to his own Religion, he has been only Cheated and affronted with the mere out-ſide and Apparition of a Man, or rather a Snake in his Boſom, a moſt loathſome dangerous diſſembler? Upon this account, as almoſt all Ages of the World ever did, ſo this alſo in which we live, does at preſent afford us, not far from home, a very pregnant Inſtance, with what a zealous and ſuſpicious Eye Politicians juſtly think they have reaſon, to look upon ſuch new pretended Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts, whoſe outward Compliances with them in matters of Religion ſeem wholly owing to ſuch external force and fear. From whence alſo, by the way, may plainly appear the great Folly and Madneſs, of perſecuting Men merely upon the account of Religion. Which is in effect no better, than to incur a great deal of guilt and Odium, and to be at a great deal of invidious Pains, to make a ſort of People, whom themſelves can never think fit, when all is done, to rely upon; nay, the moſt dangerous ſort of Men, the leaſt to be truſted, and the fitteſt to be rooted out of the World of any living therein; as being indeed the common Enemies to Mankind and Human Society in general. So that ineed ſuch Proceeding is no other than firſt to Perſecute without, and againſt all reaſon, that ſo they may have a juſt reaſon to perſecute,</p>
               <p>Again, in the ſecond Place, another very great but moſt deſerved Inconvenience more peculiarly attending the Perſons of ſuch Offenders, is, That they who have once imbibed and profeſſed this moſt execrable Hereſie, let them pretend to retract, nay, let them really repent and recant the ſame with never ſo much Earneſtneſs and Sincerity; yet 'tis ſcarce poſſible, by all the means they can uſe to that purpoſe, either ſufficiently to ſatisfy the Church, or to gain Credit with any other conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Perſon, that they are at length in good earneſt. For they who have once pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly taught this Doctrine, or openly owned it as their avowed Judgment, that it is lawful, in any part, or in whole, to diſſemble their Religion or Belief, and have already practiſed accordingly, may ever afterwards very juſtly be ſuſpected, to be only repeating of the ſame Crime, actually making uſe of the ſame curſed ſort of <hi>Libertiniſm,</hi> even in their very Retractation of it, and at the very time when they pretend to repent thereof. So that they who before rendered Words and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:45693:37"/>
ſo wholly inſignificant unto others, muſt now in this Caſe have made them no leſs unprofitable to themſelves: Since unleſs they could give Men an immediate proſpect of their Hearts, they can never be believed in any thing they may affirm concerning it; nor indeed in any thing elſe whatſoever upon their own Denial or Affirmation.</p>
               <p>To conclude; Let but the ſame Liberty prevail alſo in Civil Affairs, (as it equally may and will; for Religion certainly is not the only thing in the World, with which we may thus make bold; but if we may Counterfeit that it ſelf, there can then be nothing elſe in the World, which we may not alſo as lawfully diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) I ſay, of this libertine Principle ſhould once generally take place in Civil Affairs and matters of ordinary Converſation, 'twould preſently make as ſad work in the Commonwealth as in the Church; that is, indeed, utterly confound the ſame, and deſtroy the very being of it. For tho' the World be bad enough as it is; yet ſuch would be hereupon the Miſerable Alteration of it, that every Man would feel the fatal Effects thereof, and be ready to deſire, that the World it ſelf might have a ſpeedy Concluſion. And in the mean time, we ſhould have reaſon to wiſh for it, as the far greater Priviledge, that all Men had been made perfectly both deaf and dumb, ſince the contrary, faculties ſo ſtrangely perverted, would ſerve us only to do, and to receive Miſchief by. What a ſad ſtate of Affairs muſt that be, wherein there could be no believing, or being believed, and conſequently no free Intercourſes, no Trading or Commerce with each other? no Government or Subjection? How wretched and deplorable would be our Caſe, if neither Promiſes nor Vows, nor the moſt ſolemn Oaths themſelves could afford us any thing of the leaſt ſecurity to be depended on? The whole World would thus become one continued Cheat, nothing but Deceiving, and being Deceiv'd. So that there could be no longer any living together, as now, in Cities or Towns, no, not ſo much as in private Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies: but every Man would be forced, as much as he could, to withdraw himſelf from others, and each betaking himſelf to the Wilderneſs, endeavour to live ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and alone by himſelf in ſome Den or Cave of the Earth. And ſo farewel Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility it ſelf, together with all the Benefits and very being of Humane Society. So that indeed, above all other Criminals or Traitours whatſoever, Governours, as they tender the publick Welfare, are obliged moſt vigorouſly to endeavour, to Suppreſs and Puniſh this ſort of Offenders, as Perſons guilty at once of Univerſal High-Treaſon againſt all Government it ſelf; eſpecially, when they find them not only practiſing but publickly teaching and maintaining the Lawfulneſs of ſuch Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulation. And accordingly, all Wiſe Magiſtrates of what Age or ſort ſoever, when ever they could ſufficiently diſcover any Perſons guilty of this dangerous Crime, have thought fit to cenſure them with the utmoſt Serverity; not only as Enemies to Religion it ſelf, without which no Government can be maintain'd, but as imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate and direct Enemies alſo to the Commom Welfare of mankind and the very being of Human Society. Which ſhall be my Seventh Conſideration.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The common Senſe and Judgment of all unprejudiced Mankind of what ſort ſoever conſtantly agreeing in the Condemnation of ſuch Offenders and Practice, as a thing moſt Dangerous, Baſe, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nnatural, and Abominable.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>WHen <hi>Iſdegerdes</hi> King of <hi>Perſia</hi> commanded <hi>Benjamin</hi> a Chriſtian Deacon, to deny the God he Worſhipped, ſtrong and unanſwerable was the reaſoning, by which he refuſed, ſaying; <hi>They that deſert you, O King, you deſervedly put to death: what puniſhment then, think you, is he worthy of, who baſely deſerts his Creator?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:45693:37"/>
Among the Ancient <hi>Jews,</hi> (not without the command of God himſelf for it) they who were found guilty of Idolatry, or any ſtrange Worſhip, or had done any thing in appearance like it, which might juſtly be ſo Interpretated, were preſently Stoned to Death by the Witneſſes and all the People. And we find that when the Pagans had forced Swines Fleſh into the Mouth of old <note place="margin">3. Mac. 6. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>Eleazer</hi> the Scribe, he preſently Spat it out again. <hi>And when they who had the charge of that wicked Feaſt, for the old acquaintance they had with the Man, taking him aſide, heſought him to bring Fleſh of his own Proviſion, and ſuch as was lawful for him to uſe, and make as if he did eat of the Fleſh, taken from the Sacrifice, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the King, that ſo he might eſcape Death;</hi> He refuſed the ſame, thus anſwering, like himſelf; <hi>It becometh not our Age in any ways to Diſſemble., whereby many young Perſons might think, that</hi> Eleazer <hi>being Fourſcore Years old and Ten, were now gone to another Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In like manner, though it may be obſerved, that the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> People all along before, had but very little kindneſs for the <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans,</hi> upon the account of their Worſhiping the Idols of their own Country, together with the God of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> yet this ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and hatred of theirs, ſeems to have been much emproved, and grown to the greateſt height imaginable, ſome time before and at our Saviours comming. The Reaſon of which is plain enough, if we do but a little conſult Hiſtory: For after the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritans,</hi> by the leave of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, had built for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a Temple on Mount <hi>Gerizim,</hi> like to that of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> they preſently began thereupon to magnifie themſelves as now equal to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he <hi>Jews</hi> in every thing; vaunting themſelves for the Off-ſpring of <hi>Joſeph</hi> the Father of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> and alike Worſhipers of the true God. But ſoon afterwards, when <hi>Antiochus</hi> began to Perſecute the <hi>Jews</hi> for their Religion, theſe <hi>Samaritans</hi> terrified thereat, preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly changed their Note, plainly denying that they Worſhiped God, but like other People, the Gods of the Heathen only; giving out likewiſe, that they were not <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> but <hi>Sidonians,</hi> and promiſing to dedicate their Temple it ſelf to <hi>Jupiter</hi> of <hi>Crete.</hi> By which means they clearly eſcaped all the effects of that Tyrants Fury. Now this horrid Diſſimulation of theirs, and ſo ſhameful denial of their Religion, ſeems to have been the true chief Reaſon, why the <hi>Jews</hi> ſo deſervedly hated the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> that they willingly neither talked to, nor converſed with them; but ſhunned them upon all occaſions, as a perfect abomination to them.</p>
               <p>Now, though it be very true, That Chriſtians have no expreſs Command as the <hi>Jews</hi> had, to put to Death ſuch Idolaters and Diſſemblers; yet the wiſer ſort of Chriſtian Princes alſo, ſenſible of the infinite danger to them of ſuch Practiſes, have thought fit
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:45693:38"/>
ſufficiently to ſhew both their Zeal and Severity in the like Caſes.</p>
               <p>That good and mild Emperour <hi>Theodoſius</hi> made ſuch ſevere Laws againſt the <hi>Manichees</hi> of his time, as may ſeem very ſtrange to any one not well acquainted what kind of Perſons they were, for their particular Behaviour.</p>
               <p>We are to know therefore, that the <hi>Manichees</hi> were wont ſo to inſinuate and intermix themſelves with the Orthodox Chriſtians, that 'twas extremely difficult to diſtinguiſh them; whilſt having no regard at all of Perjury it ſelf, they ſcrupled not falſely to affirm and Swear themſelves Catholicks; and if at any time they happened to be diſcovered and convicted for <hi>Manichees,</hi> then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently counterfeiting Repentance, and outwardly feigning them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to abhor that Hereſy, they ſtill continued inwardly what they were before. And that they might be no more found out, would aſſemble together with the Orthodox in their Churches, and preſume alſo to partake with them even of the Holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. So that <hi>Theodoſius</hi> had a great deal of Reaſon to deal ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely as he did with this moſt dangerous lurking Sect of Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creants, by taking care to ſend them all into perpetual Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ordaining withall, let them pretend themſelves Penitents as much as they would, that they ſhould never any more be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Communion of the Church, unleſs when they appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently <note place="margin">Baron. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal v. 4613 614.</note> lay a dying.</p>
               <p>After the ſame manner a great many of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Race, very conſiderable for Wealth and Power, and diſperſed all over the Dominians of <hi>Ferdinand</hi> King of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> having been plainly diſcovered to have play'd the Hypocrites, in that, though they openly profeſſed the Chriſtian Faith, they did yet ſecretly retain and obſerve the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Law and Ceremonies; That King did not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cauſe many of them, who ſtill continued obſtinate in the Crime to be burnt alive, but commanded the dead Bodies alſo <note place="margin">Camp Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goſ. rerum. memorabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium. <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 33.</note> to be taken out of the Graves, of ſuch others of them, who died guilty of the ſame Wickedneſs. Tho' at the ſame time he ſuffered a very great Multitude of other <hi>Jews,</hi> to continue ſafe and undiſturbed in <hi>Spain;</hi> becauſe they fairly and openly obſerved the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Inſtitution, without any ſuch Hypocriſy or Violation of the Chriſtin Religion.</p>
               <p>Nor is it at all ſtrange, to find Chriſtian Magiſtrates thus af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, when even ſome Hereticks themſelves have ſhewn a like juſt Indignation againſt ſuch flattering Time-ſervers, and dangerous Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblers. To which purpoſe we have a very memorable Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in <hi>Theuderichus,</hi> or <hi>Theodoric</hi> King of the <hi>Goths,</hi> one of whoſe Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, before greatly beloved and reſpected by him, ſuppoſing by this means, that he ſhould ſtill purchaſe more Favour with that Prince deſerted the Orthodox Faith, and turned of the <hi>Arian</hi> Profeſſion.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:45693:38"/>
But <hi>Theuderic</hi> Inſtead of being better pleaſed with him, preſently commanded his Head to be cut off, ſaying, <hi>Thou that haſt not kept thy Faith towards God, how wilt thou ever behave thy ſelf Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcienciouſly towards a Man?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To proceed, the very <hi>Turks</hi> themſelves, in this reſpect, are very Wiſe and Politick, who, though they grant a general ſort of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence and Toleration, to the Exerciſe of all Religions; yet, as with them Atheiſts are put to Death, ſo they are no leſs ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere alſo againſt this fort of Hypocrites: For whoſoever is known by them to be barely preſent with them at their Devotions in one of their <hi>Moſqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> (let the motive be what it will that carried him thither) muſt become a <hi>Moſſelman</hi> immediately, and be Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed forthwith in order to it, or elſe be ſure to die for his prophane Hypocriſy and Affront.</p>
               <p>But why ſhould I alledge any of theſe Teſtimonies or Examples? When ſeveral of the wiſer and more conſidering ſort even of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens themſelves, have ſufficiently given us to underſtand, what kind of Apprehenſions they had concerning thoſe Perſons, who either for meer fear or Favour, could be induced to change their Religion, or aſhamed to own it. For though it cannot be expected that thoſe very Perſons, who could think fit to Perſecure Chriſtians, (as moſt of the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours did) on purpoſe to make them ſo play the Hypocrites, ſhould afterwards expreſly reproach or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn them for having done ſo; (ſince this would be no other than to reflect upon themſelves, and to caſt dirt in their own Faces) yet ſome few others of the Pagan Emperours, (as I ſhall anon ſhew) who happened to be more mild, and leſs of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Perſecution, have plainly enough declared, both how mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they thought of ſuch Diſſemblers, and how honourably of thoſe who remained conſtant in their Profeſſion. And in the mean time, that the moſt eager Perſecutors themſelves had alſo the ſame thoughts of them, will, I think, be undeniable, if we do but well conſider what muſt be their very chief deſign in Perſecuting. Now, to be ſure, they could not be ſo Fooliſh, as once to hope by knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out their Brains, to enlighten their Underſtandings, and that all the fears and torments in the World ſhould really produce a different Perſwaſion of Mind, or make them in their Hearts believe any otherwiſe than they did before. And indeed, as theſe cruel Wretches could not ſee, ſo neither did they at all regard what Faith it was that Chriſtians carried in their Hearts, ſo they did but keep it there ſecretly to themſelves, (as ſome of them, you have heard, expreſly ſo adviſed) and in the mean time deny the ſame with their Lips, or be ſure never to declare it either by Words or Actions. This once effected, the moſt raging <hi>Diocleſian</hi> would deſiſt, and require nothing farther. Accordingly, when <hi>Pliny</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior had conſulted <hi>Trajan,</hi> what he ſhould do with the Chriſtians,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:45693:39"/>
the Emperour thus anſwers; <hi>He that denies himſelf to be a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and makes this manifeſt indeed, that is, by Worſhiping our Gods, though he has been formerly ſuſpected, let him yet obtain Pardon upon Repentance.</hi> Upon which account, <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his Apology againſt the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> thus ſmartly Expoſtulates with them; <hi>You do not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed with us according to the uſual Form of Judging Criminals; but whilſt you apply Tortures to others, who deny the Fact they are accuſed of, to extort a Confeſſion from them, Chriſtians alone you Torment, to make them deny the ſame.</hi> And again a little after, <hi>The Man cries out,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I am a Chriſtian, and he ſpeaks therein truly what he is; But ſtill you deſire to hear what he is not: Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> whoſe Buſineſs it is to force out the Truth, from us alone endeavour to extort a Lye. The Man ſaith, I am that, which whether or no he is, you ask of him; Why do you ſtill Rack him, to make him ſay the contrary? I confeſs, and you ſtill Torment me; What would you do if I ſhould deny? Others when they deny, you do not very eaſily believe: But to us, if we once deny, you preſently give Credit.</hi> Now what was the true Reaſon and Deſign of this Method of Proceeding? Did they delight to hear a Lye merely for its own ſake, without any other Purpoſe or Advantage? Or could they think, that Pain alone ſhould alter the Judgment and Underſtanding, as well as the Will? Either of theſe is certainly moſt unreaſonable to ſuppoſe of them. But the true reaſon why the Pagan Perſecutors reſted ſo fully ſatisfied herewith, was becauſe they were clearly ſenſible, that in gaining of this Point they gained all that was poſſible for them to effect, or could be well deſired, even (ſo far) the utter Ruin and Deſtruction of that Religion, which they ſo endeavoured to root out and exſtinguiſh. For if they could once bring a Chriſtian openly to deny his Faith, and to continue to do ſo, than which they well knew nothing was more contrary to the Nature of Chriſtianity and all Religion, then they had a perfect conqueſt over the Man's Will and Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and had brought him therein, to forego all that 'twas poſſible for him to part with; (for a Man's belief is not purely in his own Power, tho' the Profeſſion of what he Believes is) all but only what he could not help the keeping of, and would (if he could) part with that alſo, rather than ſuffer Torment. Openly to diſown his Religion, they ſaw plainly, was to forgo all the Benefits thereof, by the Man's violating his own Conſcience, and keeping his inward Faith for no other purpoſe but to upbraid him: And in one Word, by bringing him to this, they made him caſt all the Shame and Diſgrace imaginable both upon himſelf and upon his Religion; which ever after, without true Repentance and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>confeſſion, could prove no farther ſerviceable either to the Man himſelf, or (through his occaſion, and ſo far as he could hinder) to any other Perſon in the World beſides. So that when all is done, no Man can ſo play the Hypocrite in, or with his Religion, without
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:45693:39"/>
being in good earneſt, as to the Ruine of that, and his own Deſtruction</p>
               <p>Nay, the Perſecuting Heathen, concluded themſelves, to have gained their Point in a great meaſure, if they could but any way ſo contrive the Matter, that a Chriſtian might but ſeem or be thought, (tho' falſely) to comply with them. And accordingly <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſe.</hi> Hiſt. Eccl. <hi>l.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Euſebius</hi> tells us, <hi>That in the Ninth Year of</hi> Diocleſian, <hi>many ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered Martyrdom, among whom there were ſome who underwent the trial without any Benefit or Advantage. For as one was thruſt on by the violence of the Infidels, and brought by them to thoſe unlawful Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, though the Man did not Offer, yet he was freely diſmiſſed by them, as if he had Offered: So another, tho' he did not ſo much as come near nor touch any impure thing, yet the Heathen affirming, that he had Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed, he did not contradict them, but ſilently went away. Another, cried out with a loud Voice, that he utterly abominanated all their Sacrifices; Another, that he was a Chriſtian; Another that he nither had, nor ever would Sacrifice. And yet all theſe by Soldiers placed there for that purpoſe, were violently ſmitten upon the Mouth and Face, and forced to hold their Peace, and then thruſt away by main force. So great a matter did thoſe Enemies of Piety eſteem it, but any way to ſeem, or have it thought, that they had effected what they deſigned upon them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to return again (as I promiſed) to ſome of the leſs Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting ſort of Roman Emperours. <hi>Adrian</hi> (as I before remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) in the Hiſtorian <hi>Flavius Vopiſcus,</hi> Writes in a Stile of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and ſcornful Admiration at the ridiculous Levitie of thoſe <hi>Baſilidian</hi> Hereticks, whom he calls, <hi>ſome Chriſtians of Egypt,</hi> in that they could change their Religion, as they ſaw occaſion, now Worſhiping with the Chriſtians, anon with the Jews, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times again with the Gentiles.</p>
               <p>Again, in that Reſcript of <hi>Antoninus Pius,</hi> forbidding any far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Perſecution of Chriſtians, publiſhed at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Council of all <hi>Aſia,</hi> and ſtill extant in <hi>Euſebius,</hi> we may plainly perceive what cenſure of Diſgrace that mild Emperour <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſeb.</hi> hiſt. 1. 4. chap. 12.</note> was ready to paſs upon the contrary Behaviour, by that honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able character of Commendation, which he there beſtows upon the admirable Conſtanccy of ſincere Chriſtians. His Words are theſe; <hi>Quibus hominibus jam ipſi gravem exhibetis Moleſtiam,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Thoſe Men to whom you now create ſuch grievous trouble, accuſing them as Impious and averſe from the Worſhip of the Gods, that Religion of theirs which they plainly have, you do thereby very much confirm. For they much rather wiſh, that, being accuſed, they may ſuffer Death for their God, than enjoy Life. So that by their Lives, after this manner freely parted with, they reap a greater and much more Illuſtrious Victory, than if they fulfilled the Commands, which you require to be obſerved by them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſtill, above all other Inſtances, nothing can be more appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to this purpoſe, than both the Words and Actions of another
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:45693:40"/>
Emperour, who, tho' Merciful to all, and far from Perſecuting Chriſtians, yet Lived and Dyed a Heathen; I mean <hi>Conſtantius Clorus,</hi> the Father of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great. For when <hi>Diocleſian</hi> and <hi>Maximine</hi> urged him, to reeſtabliſh the Pagan Rites and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours, and to diſcharge all Chriſtian Officers from his Court: This mild and prudent Prince, reſolving to take this opportunity, of trying the Conſtancy and Fidelity of his Courtiers, made as if he would put the Order in Execution; and therefore, ſending for all ſorts of Perſons about him, acquaints them with the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Emperours, exhorting them to yield a ſuitable obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience thereto, by ſacrificing to their Idols, and adding withal no ſmall threatnings in caſe of refuſal. Upon this, his Court was divided into two parts; The one conſiſting of ſuch as had onely diſſembled their Faith before, whilſt they carryed Paganiſm in their Hearts, who very readily prepared themſelves to Sacrifice: The other, of ſuch as undervalued all things in Compariſon of Chriſt; who by no Threats or Promiſes could be prevailed upon to comply. After this diſcovery firſt made; <hi>Conſtantius</hi> thinking fit, to make a true diſcovery alſo of his own real Intent and Judgement, preſently Commanded all thoſe Diſſembling Time-ſervers to depart his Court, utterly denying, <hi>That ever they ſhould approve themſelves faithful to him, who had been ſo inſincere towards God himſelf: But he both retained and highly commended the other ſort; not in the leaſt doubting of their good Behaviour towards himſelf, when they had ſo well acquitted themſelves in relation to the Deity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Such now was the Judgement of the beſt Emperours. Nor ſhall we find any of thoſe to have been of a different opinion in this matter, who among the Heathens were juſtly eſteemed Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers. <hi>Themiſtius,</hi> who as well deſerved that Name, as any one that ever yet bore that Title, is well known, more than once, to expoſe and deride ſuch Weather-cocks in Religion, who continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally changing Colour with the Court, <hi>Adored not God, but the Purple;</hi> highly commending <hi>Jovian,</hi> upon this account, for grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a general Liberty, for every Man to exerciſe his own Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion without diſturbance: By which means (as he aſſures him) he effectually put an end to that curſed Trade of dangerous Diſſemblers and flattering Time-ſervers.</p>
               <p>And long before him, 'twas one of the common Aphoriſms of <hi>Socrates, That every Man ought to endeavour to be really ſuch a one, as he deſires to ſeem, and would be thought to be.</hi> And ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, when he was accuſed, for not believing thoſe to be Gods, whom his Country-men Believed and Worſhiped for ſuch, all the defence he thought fit to make for himſelf, (which yet he eſteemed ſufficient) is grounded upon the general ſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Hainouſneſs of Hipocriſie, and conſequently that none acquainted with him could think him capable of ſo high a Crime.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:45693:40"/>
For, as his Diſciple <hi>Xenophon</hi> aſſures us, all his anſwer before his Judges was no more than this; <hi>This I very much admire, with what colour of Reaſon</hi> Melitus <hi>my accuſer can ſay, That I do not think thoſe to be Gods, whom this City thinks ſo, when both many others have, and</hi> Melitus <hi>himſelf too, if he had a mind to it, might have ſeen me Sacrificing to them upon the publick Altar.</hi> Which tho' it confutes that common opinion, of his Dying a Martyr for the Belief of one God, does yet no leſs plainly demonſtrate, how far he was from the late Doctrine of the <hi>Leviathan,</hi> and how abominable a thing he concluded it, for a Man to diſſemble in Religion.</p>
               <p>How extremely brave likewiſe and altogether free from Slaviſh Fear and Flattery was that of <hi>Calanus</hi> the Indian Philoſopher, in his Letter to <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, extant in <hi>Philo Judaeus? I hear (ſaith ne) That your Friends adviſe you, to apply Force, and lay Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Hands upon the Indian Philoſophers, who were never yet acquainted, ſo much as in a Dream, with any thing of our matters. For you may indeed remove our Bodies from one place to another: But you cannot force our Souls, to do what they have no mind to. You may ſooner make Stones and Logs of Wood to Speak. There is no King or Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in the whole World, that can compel us to do what we our ſelves have not decreed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay ſtill, in the laſt place, (to inſiſt no more upon Pagans, much leſs Philoſophers of that kind) ſo naturally baſe and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is it, for a Man to Lie, or to Diſſemble, that ſome of thoſe, who, one would think, ſhould of all others be moſt void of all ſentiments of Honour in ſuch caſes, yet, retaining ſome faint ſhadows thereof in Vain glory, have had that Principle, ſtrong enough in them, to hurrie them out of the World, rather than ſeem to incur ſo ſhameful an Imputation. For even dull Atheiſm it ſelf, as it has had but too many Confeſſors, ſo has it not wanted alſo ſome few Martyrs, who have choſen to Die, rather than profeſs with their Lips, what they obſtinately pretended, they could no waies in their Hearts Believe. For this was the very caſe of <hi>Vaninus,</hi> who was Burnt to Death at <hi>Tholouſe</hi> upon that Score. we Read likewiſe of another amongſt the Turks, who choſe to Die upon the ſame account: Of whoſe Tragedy we have the particular relation in the worthy Authour of THE GOVERN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENT OF THE TVRKS. Which examples of aſtoniſhing <note place="margin">Govern. Turks. p. 119.</note> Madneſs, are yet not onely parallel'd, but quite out done by thoſe, who, believing Chriſtianity and the unſpeakable eternal Rewards and Puniſhments it acquaint us with, can yet find in their Hearts to Diſſemble, or deny their Faith, rather than undergo the ſhort preſent Sufferings of a moment upon that account.</p>
               <p>Thus you ſee what the Opinion has been concerning this Matter, of all ſorts of the more impartial, whether <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Hereticks, Turks</hi> or <hi>Pagans;</hi> nay, partly, and upon ſuppoſition,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:45693:41"/>
even of ſome Atheiſts. And as it is the ſenſe of all the World beſides, ſo I am perſwaded, 'tis ſometimes ſo alſo in the Self-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned Minds of theſe very Hypocrites themſelves. However, the time is moſt certainly a coming, when they ſhall be thorowly wake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into a quick and never-ending Senſe of Shame and of Confuſion upon this account. Which advances me to my Eighth and laſt Conſideration, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The unavoidableneſs of that infinite Shame and Miſery, which according to the Eternal and unalterable Nature of Things themſelves, muſt needs be the dreadful Portion of all ſuch abominable Hypocrites and Diſſemblers in the World to come.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>HOW naturally ſad muſt needs be the Condition of thoſe who depart hence unmortify'd and full of the love of the World, and cannot tell how to part with ſuch Deſires and Affections, even in a State in which there will be no more World for them to enjoy; The ſame Perſons alſo being (as I have already ſhewn) wholly void of all true Love of God, and of their Neighbours? How is it poſſible for them to enjoy any thing of the Heavenly <hi>State,</hi> (even tho' we could ſuppoſe them in ſuch a <hi>Place</hi> as Heaven) where there is nothing elſe for them to Love beſides God himſelf, and thoſe that love him and are like him? So that ardent Love is the pure Air and very Life of Heaven, without having our Hearts thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly endued with which bleſſed Habit and Affection, we are no more capable of that heavenly State, than it is here poſſible for us, to live without Breathing, or to breath without Air. Upon which account according to the very nature of Things, What good can they ever expect, who leave this World being themſelves wholly unfurniſhed with all thoſe Divine Qualifications, which are ſo abſolutly neceſſary to capacitate Men for their entrance into the State of true Happineſs, <hi>and to make them meet to be Partakers of the Inheritance of the Saints in Light?</hi> As the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 12. The ill Habits we paſs hence with, and want of the contrary Graces, will like natural Inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities, be ſure to conſign us over to our proper Stations, and place us without any more adoe, on the left Hand with the Goats. Every wicked Man and Diſſembling Hypocrite carries with him a whole Legion of Devils, of tormenting Sins and unmortify'd Luſts; any
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:45693:41"/>
one of which is enough to unheaven Paradiſe, and to turn <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Boſom it ſelf into a place of no reſt. Ill diſpoſitions eſtabliſh Hell within Men, and naturally lay the Foundation of their perpetual Miſery, whilſt they ſhall find ſuch curſed Habits will prove thoſe eternal Chains of Darkneſs, to fetter them below amongſt Devils; where Sin ſhall be no more, as here, diſtinguiſhed, but known by its true proper Name, Miſery.</p>
               <p>It is impoſſible that he ſhould be finally miſerable, who does not love ſomething more than God; and 'tis no leſs impoſſible that he who does prefer any thing before God, ſhould not be miſerable, if he be continued at all in being. For to love God with all our Hearts, is our only Duty, and our greateſt Happineſs, and not ſo to love him, at once our greateſt Sin and Miſery. And 'twas certainly the deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Senſe of the true nature of Religion, and a ſtrong effect of the great Sincerity of the Man himſelf, that made a Divine Poet of our own, break out into this Pious and moſt Pathetick Ejaculation; <hi>My God, let me not love thee, if I love thee not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And indeed, our future Bliſs it ſelf will conſiſt chiefly in our exta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic love of God, and in perceiving how we love him, and are beloved by him: Gratitude and Thankfulneſs, and endleſs Love for Love, will be the Life of Heaven. And without attaining here to ſome emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent degree of this Love and Gratitude, our Souls can never be wing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thither. Our Saviour therefore, who deſigned our everlaſting Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, did in order to it, contrive the moſt effectual way, to excite our Love, by loving us firſt ſo well, as to lay down his Life for our ſakes, that by his Precedent and Example, we might be even con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained ſo to love him again, and to expreſs our Gratitude in ſuch a degree, as to be, at leaſt, willing and prepared to die for his Honour, rather than deny or diſſemble our Faith. And as even now any good Man cannot reflect upon his own willingneſs thus to do, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome extraordinary overflowings of Joy and Satisfaction in it: So we ſhall hereafter infinitely more pleaſe our ſelves, and Triumph to all Eternity in the Rembrance and Conſideration of our Readineſs in this frail State, to Sacrifice our very Lives to our Redeemer, and and in perceiving how well God is pleaſed with that Sincerity of our Affections, and how acceptable the ſame is to our bleſſed Saviour. Whereas, were it poſſible that we ſhould ever be admitted into thoſe glorious Manſions, without ſuch Love of God, and having proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo far in Gratitude, we ſhould have nothing to ſupport or qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lify us, for our converſe with and enjoyment of that infinite Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and God of Love: But bring horrour of Conſcience, perpetual Shame and Confuſion of Face with us, even into Heaven it ſelf.</p>
               <p>For tho' in the ſight and Preſence of God will conſiſt all Joy and Happineſs; yet, can as without Holineſs no Man ſee the Lord, ſo true Love and Sincerity is the only thing, which can enable us to ſuſtain his Preſence. Inſomuch that if a Man's own Heart con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:45693:42"/>
him in this Point, (as every Hypocrites muſt then be ſure to do) it is impoſſible <hi>He ſhould have any Confidence towards God in that day of Jugment:</hi> But nothing, on the contrary, beſides Shame treaſured up for himſelf againſt that Day of Shame.</p>
               <p>And how great a miſery and ſevere Puniſhment this will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed prove at laſt, to all thoſe who depart out of this World im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent Sinners, and vile Hypocrites, may (however faintly) be conjectured from preſent Examples, as well of ſome who have dyed with mere Shame, and that too upon no ſuch very extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Varenius</hi> in deſcrip. Regni Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon. <hi>p.</hi> 98. &amp; 99.</note> occaſion for that Paſſion, as alſo of very many others who have gladly choſen Death, much rather than ſuffer great temporal Diſgraces any longer.</p>
               <p>Beſides, it may be obſerved, how naturally apt we are, to wax red, and be very much abaſhed, when we have at any time occaſion to make but a ſet Speech to any conſiderable number of our fellow Mortals. And how much more are we ſtill apt to be concerned, when we happen to be called in Queſtion, and are to anſwer for our ſelves before any more Auguſt Aſſembly, even though we are ſufficiently conſcious to our ſelves of our own Innocency, as to what may be object<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt us to our diſparagement?</p>
               <p>But what then, muſt we think, will be at laſt the diſmal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of thoſe who are all over loaden with Guilt, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves monſtrous by the blackeſt deformity of Sin, come to appear before the moſt dreadful Tribunal of the great God? There to have all that ever they have thought, ſaid, or done, made clearly manifeſt, and there to Anſwer, and to receive Sentence, for all that has been amiſs, in the Sight and Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, not only of one particular Aſſembly, City or Nation, but of all the Men now living upon the whole Face of the Earth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Nay, of all the ſeveral Generations of Men, that have ever, or ſhall ever live upon it, from the Beginning to the End of the World; to all which add alſo thoſe innumerable Millions of Holy Angels, and (which is ſtill more conſiderable than all the reſt) the moſt Holy, but highly affronted Jeſus, who would have been, and took ſuch miraculous Pains, to be their Saviour, and ſhall then ſit as their Judge: 'Tis enough almoſt to make a Man ſink and die but ſeriouſly to think what will then be the Shame and infinite Conſternation of all wretched Sinners, and eſpecially of ſuch provoking Hypocrites under thoſe Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances. And yet alas, the thing it ſelf will be much more dreadful than we can now apprehend, and is indeed beyond all Words to deſcribe, beyond all poſſibility of our preſent Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding; of any thing that has ever yet been here in this World, methinks, what happened in the time of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:45693:42"/>
the great, upon that Emperours embracing Chriſtianity, and reſtoring Peace to the Church, feems moſt to reſemble, how it ſhall be hereafter, at the laſt Day, with all ſuch Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. Some faint glimpſe of which we may be able to diſcover whilſt we conſider how the lapſed were at that time affected. For you might then have beheld whole multitudes of thoſe, who before in the time of Perſecution, had diſgracefully denied their Faith, preſently, upon this great alteration, under the moſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable State and Condition. For how were they pricked to the very Hearts, when they perceived themſelves not only wholly excluded from the Holy Communion, but denied all enterance into the Chriſtian Churches; all Society with the Faithful? How were they confounded at the juſt Honours and profound Reſpects then paid to the noble Confeſſors, and dazled at the luſtre of their glorious Scars ſhinning out, like ſo many ſeveral Conſtellations? And in the mean time, with what extreme Horrour and Regret did they remember their own baſe Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardice, and quite contrary Behaviour, which had rendred them ſo juſtly infamous and abhorred in the ſight of all? So that perceiving themſelves to have now no ſhare in the common Joy, no kind of portion in the general Exultation and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs of all other Chriſtians, but pefectly overwhelm'd with the deepeſt Shame and Sorrow, they betook themſelves to the Biſhops, and lowly Proſtrating themſelves at their Feet, with whole ſhowers of Tears, humbly acknowledged their hainous Crime, and in the moſt earneſt, but ſubmiſſive manner, entreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that after moſt ſevere Penances and long Satisfactions perform'd, they might be at laſt admitted to the Peace of the Church, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their true Repentance.</p>
               <p>Repentance! That bleſſed Word ſweetens and chears up all with freſh Comforts and new Life, like a perfect Reſurrection from the Dead. But alas, How widely different therefore will be the Caſe of thoſe whoſe Shame and Regret ſhall be both in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely greater, and ſure to continue with them to all Eternity, having joined thereto abſolute deſpair of better; whilſt they ſhall perceive themſelves wholly cut off from all hopes and poſſibility of Repentance and Forgiveneſs?</p>
               <p>They who <hi>glory in their Shame,</hi> and they who are aſhamed of what they ought moſt of all to glory in, are both of them in ſo high a degree guilty, that 'tis not very eaſy to determine which is indeed the moſt hainous: Yet methinks, in ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, the laſt ſeems to be the more monſtrous perverſion of the two. For though the firſt gives that to Sin and to the Devil, which belongs to God alone and Goodneſs; yet the other, caſting, (if poſſible) a ſtill higher contempt upon both theſe, do after ſuch a manner treat God and Religon, as they
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:45693:43"/>
ought to treat Sin and Satan. And therefore, as of all things in the World, nothing can be more truly Shameful, ſo there's no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of which Men ſhall be hereafter more unconceivably aſhamed of, and actually confounded at, than of their having been thus aſhamed of their Religion.</p>
               <p>So that ſhould the great Judge, at the laſt Day, be wholly ſilent in the caſe, and leave things onely to their natural conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences; yet the guilty Hearts of ſuch ſelf-condemned Criminals, by an Inſinuation as quick and intimate as the Senſe of their own Souls is to them, would ſoon Read to them their fatal Sentence. And were it then poſſible for them, to make the leaſt attempt of Entrance, their own Shame, like an evil Angel with a flaming Sword, would be ſure to guard them from the Tree of Life, and for ever drive them from the Heavenly Paradiſe, thus lowdly pronouncing their dreadful Doom,</p>
               <p>Depart from hence, Vile Hypocrites, for ever far depart theſe Glorious and Happy Manſions, prepared for the Sincere and Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and ſuch of which none are ever capable of Inhabiting, but Souls Duely qualifi'd, and ſuch onely as are full of Divine Love and Zeal, and other Holy Preparations and Chriſtian Habits, which are the onely Natural means of enabling any, to Live the Life of Heaven. After St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s denyal of him, one look from his Lord, even in his loweſt Suffering, deſpiſed Condition, was ſufficient to make him go out, and Weep bitterly: But now ſince he ſets in his glorified Eſtate, as Judge of the whole World, and Cloathed with all the Majeſty of Heaven, how will you be able to bear for ever, nay but one Moment, to look upon, or receive a look from him, whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> know your ſelves to have ſo high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Deſpiſed, and finally <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eny'd, without Repentance? Beſides, are glorious Saints and Martyrs, who, for the Love of God and their Religion, <hi>Loved not their Lives even unto Death,</hi> are they fit Company for ſuch loathſome Diſſemblers and Apoſtates? What Pleaſure or Delight are you able to take in a Society ſo infinitely different in all their qualities and diſpoſitions? Nay, with what other Face, beſide that of abſolute Confuſion, can you look upon the now dazling Countenances of them, who, to you, alwaies were before, (and now are, than ever, much more) <hi>Grievous even to behold?</hi> Depart therefore, according to the juſt Summons of your own Confuſion, into the Dark and far diſtant, but to you ſuitable Regions of everlaſting Contempt and Shame; the proper Dwelling of Apoſtate Angels, of your Fellow-hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites and Unbelievers, and of other curſed Deniers, Blaſphem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and Apoſtates.</p>
               <p>Nor let any one fondly ſuppoſe it poſſible, for ſuch Sinners then, as now, ſtill to put on a brazen Forehead, or to ſilence this Voice of Shame, or remain void thereof through the like brutiſh Stupidity and Inconſideration which now poſſeſſeth them.
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:45693:43"/>
For Mens Dreams will then be at an end, all their Miſts diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled, and diſguiſes taken away, their Eies be open'd to See things as they are, and they forced to conſider and clearly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend all thoſe eſſential reaſons and inſeparable Circumſtances, which render the nature of their Sin ſo much above all things truely ſhameful. They ſhall then be no longer able not to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, how miſerably they have abuſed and cheated their own precious Souls, debaſed their Nature, and rendred themſelves De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed. They ſhall then plainly ſee, how wholly their Sin was of their own choice, through their own fault, and how certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they might have help'd it. They ſhall likewiſe clearly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, what height of the moſt abominable Ingratitude their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence argues and proceeds from, and with what prodigious folly and Madneſs it has been all along accompanied. In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, all the cauſes of their former Imprudence ſhall then wholly ceaſe and be removed; the expedients they here made uſe of to keep themſelves void and inſenſible of Shame, ſhall have then no more place, nor be any farther ſerviceable to the former Purpoſes; but be turned at laſt only to encreaſe their endleſs Confuſion. For though whilſt Men are here, and have ſtill an opportunity of proceeding farther, in the enjoyments of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden ſenſual Pleaſures; long Cuſtom in the way of Sin, does ſo reconcile them to it, that they can now follow the ſame, free from their firſt Heart-ſmitings, and the Rebukes of their own Minds, and without being ſenſible of any Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Shame: yet then, when they can properly Sin no more, but come to anſwer for their Offences, their ill Habits will moſt of all Gall and ſeverely reproach them; ſo that thorowly awakened with their ſenſitive Smart, to conſider how long and ſecurely they have formerly wallowed in their Mire, Conſcience will be ſure to redouble its force, and to the full revenge of it ſelf upon them, for all their former ſtifling of it, and the Worm that ſhall never dye gain thereby ſo many more ſtings of intollerable Shame and Sorrow. Again, all falſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and corrupt Doctrines of Men, by the help of which they were here enabled to continue in their Hypocriſy, or the Commiſſion of any other Sin, without Shame, can then have no farther place in their Minds; Men ſhall be no longer able to continue Infidels or Misbelievers: But all ſhall there clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly underſtand how groſly they have formerly been miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and how directly contrary they have acted, to their Duty and their Happineſs, and how eaſily and certainly they might have ſeen as much, had they not willfully ſuffered their Eyes to be blinded by the Prejudices of ſome vile Luſt or other, or through their moſt unreaſonable admiration of ſome Idol Teacher of their own ſetting up, and more depending upon
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:45693:44"/>
his Authority, than upon the expreſs plain Word of God to the contrary. Farthermore all thoſe Flattering Excuſes, or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, by which Diſſemblers now endeavour to conceal their Shame, and to countenance and encourage one another in the ſame wicked Courſes, ſhall then have an end, and be turned only into ſo many bitter Curſings and mutual Accuſations of of each other, and of themſelves, whilſt all their Faces ſhall be covered with moſt deſerved Shame for ever.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, all thoſe ſenſual Objects and Delights, in the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of which the fond Hypocrite did ſo far place his Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, that as long as he could have the ſame continued to him, he was able to contemn all Shame, ſhall then be far re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, and he, being made uncapable for ever of any ſuch Pleaſure or Enjoyments, have nothing elſe to fill and take up his Mind, but the tormenting Conſideration of his Sin and Shame and endleſs Miſery.</p>
               <p>To all which, let me now only add this following Caution; Let not any one, (as moſt are to apt to do) think of what I have been laſt diſcourſing, as of things uncertain, or at a great diſtance from them. For as the whole World of our Anceſtors are long ſince gone that Journey, ſo there's no Man amongſt us of any conſiderable Age, but has ſufficient occaſion to conſider, that moſt of thoſe with whom he has been acquainted, are already gone before him into that World of Spirits; and we ſee others ſtill daily a going thither. And as much ſtrangers as we now make our ſelves to that future State, or that to us, there's nothing elſe keeps us here, or detains us from being there alſo, beſides a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Breath, which we carry in our Noſtrils, and which will ſoon expire for ever. There's nothing therefore of which we can be more certain, than that in a very ſhort time we ſhall all, one after another, try the grand Experiment of this Matter, to our end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Happineſs or Miſery; and ought with the greateſt ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Application to prepare our ſelves accordingly.</p>
               <p>So that now ſumming up the whole force of all the former Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations together, within this narrower compaſs, I ſhall thus conclude.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:45693:44"/>
               <head>CHAP. XV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The Concluſion.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>UNleſs we can find in our Hearts to prefer the vileſt of Hereticks, and the worſt of Atheiſts, before the moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Saints and Martyrs; the Doctrines of the <hi>Leviathan</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Precepts of Chriſt and his Apoſtles; and <hi>Simon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> ſhall rightly be adjuged more Orthodox than <hi>Simon Peter:</hi> unleſs to be aſhamed of Chriſt and his Religion be indeed to Glorifie him; to deny him be to confeſs him before Men, and to ſhew a baſe cowardly Fear, be indeed to exert a genuine Faith, and an Argument of true Chriſtian Fortitude; unleſs groſly to lie, and ſhamefully to diſſemble may be allowed to commence Virtues, and become requiſite Zeal, and true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Simplicity: In ſhort, unleſs all theſe, and a thouſand o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther monſtrous Contradictions can be reconciled together; then ſuch diſſembling Time-ſervers can never expect any other than to follow their beloved Doctrines to the place from whence they came, even to the Regions of the Prince of Darkneſs, and to have their Eternal Portion with their Brethren the Hypocrites and Unbelievers.</p>
               <p>But if it be indeed ſo, That the only true Wiſdom conſiſts in taking care by any means, to keep ones ſelf in a whole Skin; if it can be clearly demonſtrated, That the Doctrine of the Croſs is indeed no better than down right Fooliſhneſs; and that they who lay down their Lives here for Chriſts ſake, ſhall loſe them Eternally hereafter; if all the Primitive Martyrs are to be condemned for the greateſt Fools and Mad-men, and Self-murderers; and all the wiſeſt Governers of the Church in all Ages, are to be accounted Fooliſh and Tyranical, in the ſevere diſcipline they maintained, and the Penalties inflicted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the lapſed; nay, if Heaven it ſelf alſo could be miſtaken, in the extraordinary and miraculous Inflictitions upon ſuch Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders; if it can be made out, that God has no right to any thing at all of us, but only a little of a falſe rotten Heart, and that we are not obliged to glorifie him with our Bodies as well as with our Souls; If it be poſſible to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile Light and Darkneſs, the Service of God with that of <hi>Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon;</hi> then alſo may the Thief that mocked him upon the Croſs, as well as he who confeſſed him, be with Chriſt in
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:45693:45"/>
Paradiſe; and then the Boſom of <hi>Abraham</hi> the Father of the Faithful may prove a fit Recepatle for Scorners and Unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers.</p>
               <p>And verily, when there ſhall be no communion of Saints, neither on Earth, nor yet in Heaven; when Hypocriſy comes to ſerve inſtead of Sincerity, and the luke-warm <hi>Laodicean</hi> tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſhall become of all others the moſt acceptable to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty; when Heaven ſhall be quite void of Charity, and of all other Graces; when it ſhall be poſſible to enjoy God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out loving him, or being in any proportion like him; when God can hate Truth, and delight in the contrary; in a Word, when he can deny himſelf, and ceaſe to be any longer God; then alſo will the great Gulf be quite unfixed, and then, and never before then, may ſuch vile Libertines as we have been diſcourſing of, expect to ſee the Lord, and enter into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven.</p>
               <p>Since all this therefore is ſo abſolutely true and certain, what height of Madneſs is it for the fond Hypocrite to imagine it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for him, after this manner, to mock and deceive his Maker? When by ſo endeavouring, he only turns all that lame Service of his into mere drudgery, which when ſincerely performed is the moſt perfect Freedom; and wholly depriving himſelf of all that preſent Joy and unſpeakable Satisfaction, which ſincerity even now affords, and to which nothing in this Life can be comparable, does at the ſame time alſo render himſelf for ever uncapable of the happineſs of the World to come, and fits himſelf only for, and deliberately ſeems to chuſe everlaſting Miſery. For he who thus offends againſt the firſt Commandement; <hi>Thou ſhalt have no other Gods but me,</hi> is guilty of the breach of all, and can never per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form any of the reſt to any purpoſe. Nor is it yet ſo eaſy a matter as ſome imagine, to be able truly to profeſs with holy <hi>David, I have ſaid unto the Lord thou art my God:</hi> Whilſt yet upon this real Ability, or the contrary, does naturally depend all our true preſent as well as future, either Happineſs or Miſery. Conſider then fond Wretches, what it is you part with, and for what. Conſider now in time, what thou art a doing, O Politick Mad-man, who thus vainly endeavoureſt to compound the Matter between God and Mammon. And then tremble thou Earth, <hi>And be aſtoniſhed O ye Heavens at this,</hi> that ever any People ſhould be ſo ſottiſh, <hi>as to commit two ſuch Evils; to forſake him who is the Fountain of living Warer, and to hew out to themſelves Ciſterns, broken Ciſters, that can hold no Water.</hi> Think, O ſerious think! What it is now lulls thee ſo faſt aſlip in thy fatal Lethargy, and for the ſake of which alone thou canſt be ſo well contented to run ſo great a Hazard, and of ſo infinitely miſerable Conſequence. Is it not then the Love
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:45693:45"/>
of the World, and the vain purſuit of ſenſual Pleaſures which now ſtupifie the Mind? That <hi>World which paſſeth away and the Luſts thereof; that Life which is a meer Vapour;</hi> thoſe vain Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of which thou muſt very ſhortly take thy Eternal Farewel, and be capable of reliſhing the ſame no more for ever. Is it fit that thy divine Soul, made for and capable of ſo high things, ſhould be continually depreſſed and fettered, and made a perfect Slave to thy Body? To that Body of thine, which in it ſelf is of no better a Nature than the Fleſh of thoſe bruit Creatures, which thou daily deſtroy'ſt and feed'ſt on, to keep they own lump of Clay together and from mouldering. That which thou didſt eat to Day, was yeſterday or the Day before, as compleat an Animal (bateing thy reaſonable and immortal Soul, which thou makeſt no uſe of) as thy ſelf, and no leſs capable of enjoying the ſame ſenſual Pleaſures, which alone thou art apt ſo much to purſue and doat on; and a few Years at moſt, will certainly put an end to thy Dream; when all that can be now ſeen of thee ſhall be diſſolved, and fall into Aſhes and Corruption; and all thoſe vain Trifles and poor Enjoyments, which now take up thy Head and Heart, ſignifie no more to thee than if thou hadſt never been; unleſs only to encreaſe thy Torments, in a too late ſenſe of thy moſt prodigious Guilt and Folly, whilſt thou remembreſt them. This will e're long be thy Caſe, and may be ſo, for ought thou knoweſt, before to Morrow. So that there is really at this very time, nothing betwixt thee and Hell, but only the ſlight Partition of a little thin Breath, which ten thouſand things may eaſily obſtruct; inſomuch that 'tis a very great Miracle that thou ſhouldeſt be able to live at all, but nothing ſtrange, that thou ſhouldeſt ceaſe to do ſo. If thou canſt make a ſhift to lay aſide all theſe thoughts, and keep thy ſelf inſenſible of any ſuch thing for the preſent, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe thy ſelf to Sleep and Security; yet thy danger is really the ſame, whether thou art apprehenſive of it or no: Nay indeed, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitly greater and more inevitable upon this very account of thy not conſidering it: For thou wilt be ſhortly forced to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, (though too late) whether thou wilt or no, in that State, where Men can continue no more Atheiſts or Hypocrites; and when thou awakeſt, find thy ſelf ſur-rounded with Devils and everlaſting burnings.</p>
               <p>And now, let ſuch hardned Miſcreants (if they can ſtill find in their Hearts to do ſo) purſue their wonted Courſe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take themſelves to their only beſt Argument againſt this, by ſcornfully laughing, for a Moment, at all theſe Matters, till woful Experience ſhall change the Scene with them, and ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly convince them of their Folly. In the mean tim, as for all thoſe who by the Grace of God, are for the preſent far bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:45693:46"/>
diſpoſed and qualified, as ever they deſire to ſtand faſt, and ſtill eſcape the fatal Contagion, ſo let them carefully avoid the Example, the Doctrines, nay, as much as well they can, even the company of ſuch double Minded Wretches, and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate Diſſemblers. Whilſt all good Chriſtians will be ready, moſt devoutly to join with me, in thoſe Excellent Prayers of our Holy Mother the Church.</p>
               <p>O <hi>Almighty God, who alone canſt order the unruly Wills and Affections of ſinful Men; Grant unto thy People, that they may love the thing which thou Commandeſt, and deſire that which thou doeſt Promiſe, that ſo among the ſundry and manifold Changes of the World, our Hearts may ſurely there be fixed, where true Joys are to be found. Give us Grace, that being not like Children carried away with every blaſt of vain Doctrine, we may be eſtabliſhed in the truth of thy Holy Goſpel. Grant us ſuch Strength and Protection, as may ſupport us in all Dangers, and carry us through all Temptations: Graft in our Hearts the love of thy Name, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in us true Religion, and the moſt hearty Sincerity therein, without which whoſoever liveth is counted Dead bofore thee; nouriſh us with all Goodneſs, and of thy great Mercy keep us in the ſame: That thou being our Ruler and Guide, we may ſo paſs through things Temporal, that we finally loſe not the things Eternal; Grant this, O Heavenly Father, for Jeſus Chriſt's ſake, our only Lord and Saviour.</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_note">
            <head>
               <hi>Books of Devotion for this Holy time of</hi> LENT.</head>
            <p>A <hi>Serious and Pathetical Contemplation of the Mercies of GOD,</hi> in ſeveral moſt Devout and Sublime Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givings for the ſame; Publiſhed by the Reverend Doctor <hi>Hicks,</hi> at the requeſt of a Friend of the Authors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Spiritual Combat:</hi> Or, the Chriſtian Pilgrim, Tranſlated from the <hi>French,</hi> Revis'd and Recommended by <hi>R. Lucas,</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Church of</hi> England <hi>Man's Private Devotions,</hi> being a Collection of Prayers out of the Common-prayer Book, for Morning, Noon and Night, and other ſpecial Occaſions By the Author of the <hi>Weeks Preparation to the Sacrament<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Contemplations on the Love of GOD,</hi> &amp;c. with a Dovou Prayer ſuitable thereunto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed for <hi rend="blackletterType">Samuel Reble</hi> at the</hi> Turks-head <hi>in</hi> Fleet-ſtreet. 1699.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:45693:46"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
